Introduction
• •• • 1, t 1 t ~. -I-. /I o. 2'
2' ca t - 17 a 1. • 1_ . • 1_ ,,,. ••
1_ . • 1_ ,,,. •• 1'1_ • r la bt • • • .. 200 t • 1 41" rl&al .
Stratigraphy
• tthe aa • tD.1. ar ... .. r a 10 lp ,a • r " .. ot1 zal .. ( d .. ,_ ._~~w_~~
1 I' -.1 P 1 , The “Quarry sandstone" could not be traéed beyond statims lend 2. Worthward aod southward it fades into the high sand covered ridges, We part§eular equivalent of the "Quarry sandstone" Gould be noted in the exposure between 6 and 7 farther to the north, The prominence of the sandstone at the quarry no doubt results from its characteristic looal hardness, “ho “Quarry sandstone" is probably a lense of harder sandstone within the thiek Sandstone formation covering the area. Its general character, ui th the exception cf its hardness, follows that of the other associated Sandstones of the fornatia,.
The “Quarry sandsteae" and the associated sandatones are wadoubtedly of Tertiary age. The sandstones of sections A, B and G ars similar to the red end yellow, massive, coarse and conglos meratic Tertiary sandstones of Serra do Marisal, lying unctonfore mably over the Cretaceous, as described by Dr. Silvio Guedes under report of Jue 1946. Sections A and B are correlative with section G of the eastward extending Tertiary taboleiro of Serra do Karigale “The Tertiary-Cretaceous contact as mapped by lr. Keller and party lies some 10 kiloweters west of Cips,.
The term "Barreiras Series” is used to designate the Tertiary rocks of the littoral ares and the Reconcave of the State of Bahia, This series is described as composed of red and white soft clays and sands, generally flat lying, and forming high
•
11 • t 1 a • • • 7 t • ti Pl.-
y 
C O NS E LH O N AC I O NAL 0 0 PE TR O L EO
Bre Acile Garner 
- m~ 01' . Gene:r~l Jo I) \,;arlos llarrat.o. " . ':D. P1"6b1deute t . Ccnselho Nacional dO etrol o
811': band 4 r. Br 2;U' s eport S rat1graphl Pos1tlon of the ~ y o.; andstonc outhllest , of C1po"ror ~ nt.
The geolc '1 ot J orthern Bahi 1s rather ccmpllc 4 and hl1. • h ve planned t e have 1Ilr. Braz! rte.ke ra.nhão-Pi ui ar 8 1~'~ of the c1ded he uld be ot gr at help 1n solvlng the north 13ah! prob1 11& a n1t1ng 800 W th r ,~ Uip ent and D • P1au!.
• rt1cular Nl .. ort of r. BrazU as 1.1'1.1 t ge t10n of Dr. J.l 1 r and I'll7S l.t to d t mine tb th c posi t10n ot a p .. __ 4A._ dstone cov j. , na r C1 • • Br: zU · h1 s conclus1on ans s my q stions. t Pr vious to ·iJú.s ork r. Brazil a s1.m11 r to th wesl u th1s f w ct10n t str ti a~h1 t tuture or 10 no t1l rn Dahia.
J nuary 18,
t 
CONSELHO NACIONAL DO PETROLEO o yo~ at t n 10ft tha ra 11 • Bl'&t.U in h1 til' t wcrk b1 o 10 into .~h e rry on bl • Pur ant to a ã1sCU8S1oD ,with Dr. 011vQi:ç-G I r-ec· lended thnt ; "r. Br!l~11 conêl ot a gsolewg1e'" n-in Bortn rn hla in the rielnl t,. 01 C:1:coro 1 of t~:nn1n C ta Z16 _ • éS 1"9'" 1h 1U41 " .
Very truly yours, 
seCTION 8
SECTION A
