(*) Geologist, PETROLEO BRASILEIRO S.A. - Exploration and Predueétion | «a FA so pião: E Department.
(* -It J Ge·o Zogis t" PE'l'ROLEO BRASiLBIF.Ó S" fi. " -fté search .. Center..
( * ) Paulo Tibana
Jo ~ Z c~ de Casi ro ( ** )
. Augus t" -
.TABLE · DF' 'ÜO'NTENTS . ~. , . -. 1 ABSTRACT . . . . . . " ... . . . . . . . " • " ..... " .. . . . . . . . . " • !' ' . " " • " .. " • " " " " . . . . . . ~ .. " . " . . . . . . . . " ' . . . . .. .. . 2 INTRODUCTION . ' 1. .. .. • .. • • • " ..... ' ..... ~ • ' 0 " .. ', .. ... ' .... " •• " .. " ....... " .• , . , 2 ,'.: ;.,. 3 "-" 1.2 Ho)~king !\1ethods . and 1,1icrofacies Tecbn"icju es · ..••••...•..•.• , ••• 2, ' SEDI MENTOLOGIC LOGS ... . . . . . . . . . ... ' ,' .. " ..... ' 0' . . . . " ............. " ........ '" .. ' 3. STRUCTURAL AND STRATIGRAPHIC FRAI\1E \~ O RK . " ....... .... " .... ~ .. " ....... " ... .. 6 7 STRATIGRAPHY AND POROSr(y EVALUATIDN' .••• ••• ••••••••••••••• •• ••• , .. .-4.1YamÇlma Forma ti on. "7 I . .. " . . . . . . . . " . . . . " . . . . . " • • • ' . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . " . . . . . . . . . ' I . . . . . . " ' 1 ' I . . . . . . 4.1.1 Microfacies and Environmental Model 7 '4.1 . 2 Ve rtica l Evolu tion and Dis tr ibution of Facies ..... ,~.. 8 4.1.3 Di agenesis an d Reservoi r Rocks •... ~ ....•......•......• 8 \ . 4. 2 Shuaiba Formation ......................................... ' ....... ... .. 9 ~ . -;,. ' . , -.~~'" .. , " \ . '. : . ' Microfacies and En~irQn mnn tal Model 4.2.1 10 4,2.2 Vertical Evol ution and .Dis tfibution of Facies ......... 11 4.2.3 Diagene's i s and Reservoi}" Rocks .•• ' .........•........... ' 12 13 J .. 4~3 · "\1auddu d Formation ' ........ '. ' .. ~.: .. ,t ' . . . . . . . ~ . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . , • 4.3~1 Microfacies and Environmental Interp ret ation . : . . ....•. 13 .;~.3.2· Verti"cal 'EV olutipn and St.r:~t-jgraphic Correlation ... , ... 14· 4.3.3 Diagenesis and Res~~voir Rocks
15 4.4 .Ahmadi Fonnation .. ............... #' . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . 4.4.1 . Microf~ciés and tnvirbnmental lnterpretation .. ~ ... ~ ... 16 .. . . 4.4.2 Vertical Evo1ution arid Di stribution of Faties ... .. .. 16 4.4.3 . Diagenes is ahd Reservoirs ....•. ~ .. . ... ~ ........•.• :. 17 4. 5 Mtshrif/R ~ma i1a Formations .................. ~ .......... " .. . 18 . . ~ '... <4.5.1 t·ii cl'ofacies and Environmcn tal Interpre tation ..... 18 4.5.2 Vert ical Evo l ution and Distribution of Facies .. ~ ..... ; 19 4.5.3 Di agenes is and porOsHy ............................... 21 4.6 Khasi b 'Formati on .... .. . . . . . .. . . . . . .. .. . . .. ... . ... ... 24· 4.6.1 Micrbfac i~s and Environmental Intetpretation ~ . .. .. . i •• 24 4.6.2 Vertical Evolution) Stra t igra phy and Reservoit~s ....... 24 4.7 Lower 'Sa 'Qi/Tanuma Formations 25 .",,: l~h M\ddie/0pp~r Sa'Di Formation ..... ~ .....•................ 27 4.9 Hal"th a Formation 5. CONCLUSIONS ANO RECOMMENDATIONS . ...... ' ,' ............. ... .. .. ....... .. 29 6. B IBLI OGRAPHY 31. . • . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . " . . . . . . . . . . . . . . " . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . lo . . . . lo . . . . . . . . . . . .. . .. ! 7. LIST OF ANNEXES 33 lo · • lo : " " . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . " .. lo . . . . lo . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ... lo '· . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
,The Cret aceous carbonate , .rocks of the we lls drill ed in the MAJNOON an d NAH R UMR Fi e lds were investigate d by . . m1: cJ."'ofac'l:es ,tech n~q ues, in order ' to define the environments .. , ~e rt ical s equencis .. facies dis tr ibution .. diagen e sis and , r esulting p o vosity typ e s ofth e v ar ious productive formations.
The carbon ate unfts studied belong to the " follo wing for~ ation s .. listed accordi ng ~6 their d ep o sit ional s eq u e nces : ' YAMAMA .. SHUAIBA .. MAUDDUD .. ,A HMA DI .. l:1ISIIRIF /RUMA ILA .. . , KH/J. SIB .. TA NUMA .. SA' DI .. ' and HARTliA. Th es~ rocki were deposi te d f;o m Berria s ian to Maes t~ichtian time and they ' g ene r a lly r epresent th e c u lm inatioris, of regressive cycles.
Poro~i t~ is g~ne rally assóciatedwith ' shoal and sh a~low out er ~helf c arbonates; int erpar ticle-type poro aity is th e most ~mportant .. follow edby leach ed ( moldic/vuggy) and \ frac tu l' e typ es.
Thi s work imphasizes the dir e ct contr~l that p~im ary depo sit io na l-di a g~netic settings exert bn th~ final geom et ry and porosity properties o f ihs carbonate re&irvoir ther:efore.. i ts importance to corre e tly' eva luate the l'ock s a n d.. , behaviour of the carbo na te column as a petroleum res e rvoir.
The discovery of MAJNOON and NAHR UMR oil fields . led toanincrea~~ed effort to imp r ove the knowledge about the stratigraphyof the area ~nd to evaluate correctly the hydr~carbon reserv8S.
The ma in purpose of thi~ project was to stUdy - petrographycally -the Creta ceous ç a rbonates of those fields t:o understahd the gen~sis and the distribution of the main r ~s erv6irs and predict the most porous trends.
MIDDLE CRETACEOUS FACI ES ANO THICK NESSES IN THE ARABIAN GULF LOWER ANO (WILSON, 19'75)
WORKING METHOVS ANO MrtRorACrE~ TECHNIQUES 1 •
The~tudy was c~rriéd out in 3 phas es: f\1acroscopic study of . cores ' at BASRAH, Iraq, of . A we11sMJ-·1 and MJ-2, described by TIBANA , and , MJ-3, NU-t, describ ed by CASTRO. During this phase, a total of 74 cores were sawed, de s cr i bed and p10tte d on é;l.n appro priate 1;20 scalc 10g. The renresentative slabs of each 1itho10gy were photographe d, and a total of 515 samp1es se1ected . ~ ..... f. ~ :>. _ . • i6r thin-~ection studies ; In the zones 1acking gooà repre sentative cores, ditch samp1es were co11ected ' to complete the thin section anaJys es . . · . · -7 The macroscopic descript ionof these samp1es furnished a pre1iminary definition of microfacies ' based on sedimentary structures, textures and identification of recognizáb1e fossi1contents. . ,B Microscopicdescription~of thin section~ - were performe d at PETROBRÁS 1aboratory ~ In this phase t det.ailed analyses of samp1es permi tted the identification of the components and the most ' important features forgenetic interpretation. , . , " . ; li, ~ •. _ •. _ ... __ ... ... 4 .. -t'- . ~ .. ~ ... _._ ••• ~" c The analyses 9f alI 1itho10gica1 dat a al 1 0wed to d ef ine there1ati6nship betwe e n porosities and The vertical deposition~l/diagen e tic parameters. sequenee s and stratigraphie eorre1ations furn~she d the definition of depositiona1~cye1es and spatia1 distribytion of the porbus facies~
\ The sedimentologica1 parameters recorded during the severa1 phases ' of thi s projeet were'plotted in 1:200 seale ~e.dimeYLtoR.ógJ..c.. R.~'g'/.). in order to faci1itate the comparison with SCHLUMBERGER 10gs and ealibrate the 1ith010gic and porosity changes . (attached . sedimentologic 10gs) ~ The .6 e,dimen:to.t.ÇJ gi.c.. .to 9.6 conta in the gamma-ray \ 10g, position' Df core·photographs and thin sections, sedimentary structures, textura1 parameters, mainfossi1 contents, It is important to point out that the fossil contents we re selected after a first ~econnais~ance of alI thin sections and evaluation ' of their importance in the facies composition and interpretation .
Since . the study includes stratigraphic units · of di fferen·t ages, some fossil groups are more common in certain f6rmations, as for ~xample: Pseudocyclammina ' and Trocholina r ~n YAMA MA FOhmation; LithocodiumjBacinella , in SHUAIBA Fm; Alveoli~-ids and Nedzazata r ~n AHMAVr;MISHRIF 6ohma.:tion~; and Loftusia, in HART~A FOhma.:ti on. oth ~r fossils, such ~s green algae, miliolids, orbitolinids and p elecypods (rudists): though being common in the Cretaceou.s uni ts r are good facies indicators . \ The porosity evaluation, indicated iri the last column of the log"was estimated on a semi-quantitative basis. It is important to emphasize the ' relationship b etween the . porosity type andmicrofaci e s to understand the genesis of carbonate reservoirs. Certain types of porosity can b e '. readily seen under .the microscope, while others are . 1ess noticeable due to th~ir sroall sizes (micr6porosity). Porosities' due to fractures and large solution cavities r though directly Petrolcum accumulatici1s in the l-1iddle East are This is also the ca se of MAJNOON and e ssen fially structural . NAHR UMR fieids , where th~ primary trapping is provided by an ant.icliné . However, thestratigra~hic and diagenetic ch~r a cteri s ticsofthe reservoir rocks play an im~ortant c o ntrol on the field beha vior 'and sha ll be c are fully evaluated.
\ The carb6n~te units studied through wells NU-S, ' MJ-l, MJ-2 and MJ-3 belong to the follówing formations, listed YAMAMA, SHU AIBA , ac60rding to their ~epositional sequence: MAUVDUV; ÁHMAVI, MISHRIF/RUMAILA, KHASIB, TANU MA, SA'VI and HARTH A. The~e rocks were deposited during Cretaceous time, from Berriasian to Naestrichtian, and they generally represent the culminations of regressive c.yc les (F-<..glLILe 2) .
~~~ua==~._e'JQ~i;u;::~ai''''''m2t4SU3&lf.m~~~~~~mx~'';UA'1tJU~~~~')'l7;;7WiJíIit!!SUW4lF''~'''.''''''IIDI-IIl.a:"."'r=w,::)azuw""-=-. .. _IIIC. __ .. :u"'G"""_..="' ... "' ... ""~"'"' __ The thi ckn ~ ss of the YAMAMA fo~ma~ion varies irom 320 me ters in NU-8 to 3SÕ meters in MJ~3. It overli es th e SULAIY FOJL n1 Çlt ion.; a , BerriasianjTithonüin carbonate unit.
4.1.1 Michogacies and.Envinonmental Mode? 
Six micrQfacies were reco~nized (Table 1 ) .Except ~ . e for micro facies 3 ' and 2BI the others are very a like petrogr aphica lly, consisting of benthonic fora'min ifers (Pseudocyclammin a l Trocholina), green algae, mollusks and echinoids. The distinction is based on sedimenfary structure and co1or, ~Jhich is predominantly brownish-gray in ,inhér shelf- -lagoonal and greenish~gtay in outer shelf .
Churned and cross-bedded,peloida1 / / intrac1ast/bioclastic calcarenite (packestope and grainstone).Some peloids are a1galic.
Grecnish-gra~, argillaceous, churned to laminated .calcilutite (\..rackcstone) • Trocbolina, LenticuIina,Pseudocycl~ina, da syclads, IDollusks and ostracods. Horizontal fractures.
2-131
4.1.2 Vertical Evolution and Distribution of Facies 
The stratigraphic section of Flgu~e 3 shows the faci e s dis tribution and correlation betVleen the upper co red portion of the unit inMJ -2 and NU-8 wells. Severa l small cycles Df deposition star'·ting with lagoonal-facie s (1) and passing to inner shelf (2), shoal (3) and 6uter shelf facies Lãterally , the facies changes from more (4) are observed. restricted in NU-8 to more marine in MJ-2. rJ'he 'upward increase ° in cl-ay content I as well as the p r edominance cif outer shelf d eposits over the lagoonal-inn e r shelf f a cies, ·toward the top of the ' formation, resulted from , a tran sgression at the ~nd of VAMAMA deposition. This tr a n sgies sive even~ is r~sponsible fo~ the transition a l natu r ~ of the contact of VAMAMA with the overl~ing RATAWI FOhmatlon .
4.1.3 Diagenestis and Reservoir Rocks 
°The most important diagenetic effect on VAMAMA I rocks is the solution of bioclasts in the microfacies 2A and 2B, with conseguent development of moldic/vuggy poros;i.ties. Secondary blocky calcite maypartially occlude these pore s. Also important are the subverti cal fractures that are observed t'a.~~;'&~~.r~~~,A.~J'l'tf:tS,t.tIUJ~~.J:'."IOIr,~~~~~J'L..~~~~_l!5U.' Jzu:t~~~~"'7.S_""'''_'''''"""Cz' "'S&AZ_,~= ..... """,,,,,,~~~~:J mama 3 perereca mm Tees Op We re oS. eee The high energycalcarenites 6f microfacies 3 The original do not show po rasi tiesin ~he inter" al : studied. interpar ticle vaids were .cómpletely cemented by cavity fi lling ... sparite. Typical on mi crofacies' lB calcilutites is the dolomi~ization of the ,borings.
In the studied upper part of VA MAMA , FoAmatloM, .' ,porosity is generalJ.y 10'11 ' and occurs in ~ev era l zones. The , main re servo ir intervals a re associ a ted vli·th moldic/ vuggy and fracture type porosities develope d on the microfacies Z -. this is confirrned by density 10gs as, for example, the i nterva l 38 42 /3850 meters of MJ-Z.
The SHUAIB-A FOfLma.tlo 'n rep res ents a carbonate sh e lf ~edimentation develope~ af the end of the RATAWI - ZUBAIR-SHUAIBA sequence. The thickness of the formation ranges from 150 meters in NU-8 to 165 meters ~n MAJNOON field wells.
About 72 meters of cores are available from the . u pper half ofthé unit in MJ~1 . In addition, 16 othinse6tions from MJ-l and MJ-2 cut~ings were also studied to cover the un cored section .
4.2. 1 Micho6acie~ and Envihon~en~al Model
Six 'microfacies were d efined,and their d e script.i.on a nc'l r e lated - environmenta l in.terpretation are ~resented in Tabl e 2.
Microfaci~s 4, st~diedonly in cuttings, is o - tra nsitiortal to marine shales of underlying ZUBAIR FOhma~ion, Although no planktonic foramini f ers have been found,it is co nsidered to be deposited in subtidal outer shelfenvironment.
The 'more iepresentative sections of microfacies 3 wer~'foundin cuttings from the lower part of the form a tipn. It probably ~epresents high energy, shelf - margin deposits (Twombley and Scott, 1975),
Immediately landwards of microfacies 3, occur
Lagoona
. the rudist-bio'ac cumulated and L1t:.hocodlum/Bacinella bioconstru cted .limestones ·of microfacies '2B and 2A. The setting for these faci. e s have b een describ ed, by T{.()omb.te..y and S c.o:t.:t (19751 at BUHASA FJ.e .t d; Conkad (i977~ also . int~~preted Aptian Li th Dco d i um/B ac inella limes·ton e s from 8\-1 i tzerland as b e ing . , ' , '. fonned betwee.n o o li -te-ree f shoal s.
4.2.2 Ve. h.:tJ.c.a.t Evo l utJ.on and VJ.~tkJ.butJ.on o~ Fac.J.e~ \
The . overall pattern of SHUAIBA sedimentation is regre s sive, grading from a 10w eI?-ergy, more marine facies at the b ot~ om (Orbito1 1 nid ca1cilutites) to a restricted lagoona l ca1cilutites i h the upper parti ·.a com~1ex association of ruéÜst~Li thocodium limestones . and peloidal/Orbi to1inid . càlcar e nites o f inner to shelf margin origin occurs between . thos e blO extremes. The . recurrence of nlicrofacies 4 in the IThe vertical succession of Li thocodiumjBacinella - cons-tructed limest:ones I rUdist-biQaccurnulated limestonesand, finally, lagoonal calciiutites is clearly obse rve din the . cores . . of IA] - 1 (F.<.guJc.e 4). Thi s sequence issimilar to thatdescribed - . , at · BU /-IASA F.<.e.td, · A13LlVHA73I, ·bY -Twon :ble y and Sc.o.:t.:t (1975)jthese . " authors proposed the three environmental belts ("inner," max imum" .. and li out e .r buildup") . and the tridimensi onal model shO\'ln in . Each belt has a characteri sti c vertical evolution corresponc1en-t to a. t-yp ical pattern in the gamma-ray log . MA]NOON wells show a good fitting with the BU HASA'S inner
4,2.3 Diagenesis and Reservoir Rocks 
T·he SHUAIBA carbonateB of MAJNOON F.<.e.td do not show good p6rosities. Apparent porosities observed in . microfacies 1, 2A " 213 and 3 are generally 10vl and mOldi c /vuggy in nature. . This agrees ,,11th the low to fair permeability values of MJ-l formation tests. In a"broadsen~e; th~se micr9f ac ie~ correlate with the s~condary reservoirs d es cribed in . the "inn"er buildupll zone at BUHASA F.<.e.td whereth e -- reservoir~ show rudi~t framework (moldie, intraparticle) and moldic/vuggy poro sities (FiguJc.e.5).
~ . r;~~.~~~=t'~W<»JLLJ:"" ... aCMt .. ~_=QCZ®=ZC _M'''~~~. ___ '.+=,'_,~?=_$= __ ," "AlC~~~~5&~", .. ne<=--'W=-U:_'&UCM"~~. _ ........... lSOI ..
EPE RR TTT AE EIRP DO TST O TE E RUT ISDS SLOSS ARTE PAN LET ENO LT NUDE PELOTAS LR LIE TIE PCI TVA ENT NAL NESTE LEE OS EE SAP OS LIAS DENT SFE A eee oes ae REL PI EE SE I a a ee A a a PÃO q RR RR PE Le A ae ee eee Es E ma cio e rt Sd pp sq a e ie o A a A ca A DO E SSB, q Se RS O q o CR O O co OG OR o rd GC De O O a o DO 6 Te, Accor d i ng wi th the BU. HASA F.Le..td model, the oc c u r r e n ce of bett er ,reservoirs , are pr e dicted in direction of the s h e l f mar gin (" maximum buildup " ) localized basinwards (eas t war ds ) from MÁ ] t'..J a o N area.
This fo rmation represents the main carbonate c omponen t of the Albi a n NAH R UMR - MAUD DUV seguence. The , thickn e ss of MAUVV UV FOhma.;t-.,.éo/1. varies fr.om 180 ' meters in MJ - 2 to '150 me t e rs {n NU-S .
Since only one core i~ avai lable , eight cut~ing s amples'of MJ-l wel1 ,were studied to d efine the vertical evolution o f the unj,t.
4. 3.1
Five microfacies . were identified from'6uttings, a n d oné ( microfacie~ 4 ) was defined fi a m core 12 of MJ-l (T a.b.e.e. 3).
The MA UVVUV ~icrofacies point tiut to a
Inner Shelf lagoonal e a q e a qu a ma
, predominantopen marine sediments, at ~e~st ,for the lower half of ' the ' fo rmation. "' '1'he common occurrence · of calcispheres , and , planktonic foraminifers in rnicrofacies 5 indicate a slope ' ( ?) . ' env'ironme n t , sho~,ring that deep water cond i tions prevail e d since sediment ation of the upper part of NAHR , UMR Fo~matlon (CASTRO, 1978) • The outer shelf peloidal c a lcilut i tes of microfacies 4 are va r y alike those oc6urring in the over lying AHMAVI FOhmatlon. M{crofacies 1 and 2 have b een indi stinctly ' con sidered inner she lf - lagoon al depo si ts.
4.5.2 Vehtlcal Evolutlon and Sthatlghaphl e Co~helatlon
Th~evolution of MAUVVUV Fo~matlon is s,chematically illustrated in élgu~e. 6 . A complete regr ess ive seq u erice from deep water slope ( ? ) through o uter shelf , b a rrier an.d inner shelf-lagoonal sediments is d o cumented in the As o bserved ' in o ther formations (SHUAIBA formation. and AHMAVI; for e xample~ , atransgressive episode is predicted Jn the UpperlGOst , part of the f o rrnatión.
A detailed correlation between MA J I-J OON wells ( 6lgune 6) indicates that thickn~ss variation in the dee p water L~~~~~~!I.:;:tt:r2l!!"l'~_""'j.'U.~1t~w..a~'ft"l~C:'3~":'~!SI;~~!:!.~~.!:a:-!~:x-~"U'.vr.t.'!:::-~r.:Cj..,..~~,!:~azU!.c=~~~~~~""..m."_"'U";~"""''''''''''''iIBi""",.."",_'."":::J:iO)""",,.,.1i:.r==a;:~ facies secti.on accounts for the thinni-ng · of the formation from "MJ-2 ( 180 meters) to MJ -l 0ell(165meter~). This indicates a possibJ.eslope origin for those lower most carbonate s.
4.3.3 Diagenesis and Reservotr Rocks. 
Microfacies 3A and 3B show poor to fai r ip te rgr a nul~r and moldic porosities; c em enta tion wasnot eff e cfiv e enough to plug the o~ iginal interpa rticle . voids . In microfa cies 4, moldic and mitrix porositie s .are poor.
The porous zones defined by d e nsityand soni c "lo g s S110\'1 a goo d mat·ching \-'li th the mi crofac ies analyse s ; for example I the -chick porous sec·U.on developed in · the middle part of · the ~nit coi ncides with the barrier and outer . she lf zones
4.4 AHMAV r FORMATION
The CeriomanianAHMAVI Fokma~lon is rel atively weil documcinted in MJ-l 1 where six cores allowed to recognize the most diagnostic facies. Its uppe rmostpart ~as cored in . MJ~21 and someadditional . cutting ~amples weie used to calibrate

4.4.1 Michotacies and Environmental Interpretation 
Th e eight rni c rofac i es re cognized in this format ion and their enviJ:,onmen 'tal i nterpretation are shown on It was i mpossible to chara cterize the rudist-microfaci e s Z 73 as defined i n th e SH UA r DA F o hJn a.:t.-i. o I'l.. Rudist d ebris incorporateJ in m~crofacies ZA, 3B and 3A, ,however, _ . .. . , sug ges t a , bioaccumulated b ank immedia'tely behind the barrier f~cíes , as ob served in , SHU f. IBA modelo The. AHMAvr sediments be10ng , to a major regressive pha se fo110,vling the transgressi on on top of the MAUVVUV Fm MICROFACIES IA Hassive ca1cí1utites Hith gastropods, sponge spitu1es, Mi1io1ids . Hàssive ca1ci1utite \v1th abunc1 ant 2A porc e J.1àne ous foraminifers, pc~ecypod d cbris. 'Churned j ma s s ive calc,ireni te \"ith 3:8 forarninifers (Alveo1l.nids, Nezzaza ta , etc}, mol1us ks. . Cross-bedd ed to ctJ.urned ca1car enite 3A with pelecypoà/rudís t debris, echinoids. 4A Churned ca1carenit( t Green algae, pe1ecypod debrís. 'i E- -· Churned, pe1oicla1 very fine ca1carenite Hith p~lecypo~s, , echinoids, hyaIine forams. Nodu1ar ca1ci1utite with p1antonic 5 forams , ' Rota1ids, calcispheres, etc. Trangressive, argi11aceo~s , churned calciiutitesj p1antonic anel hya1ine benthonic forams, pe1ecypod dehris, pyrite.
, The ~ppermost part of theunit is characterized byanother transgres sive event, which gave rise to a calcarenite bar similar to that observed on top of SHUAIBA Fo~ma~1on. The evolution of this bar i5 well docume n ted by cores arid gamma -tay log of MJ-2, displ a ying a progradatio~alT shoaling sequ~nce of calciluti te s - Alve olinid, micritic calcarenite - pelecypod ánd sparry c alcaren ites .
'lo. • , The ~ppermost part of theunit is characterized byanother transgres sive event, which gave rise to a calcarenite bar similar to that observed on top of SHUAIBA Fo~ma~1on. The evolution of this bar i5 well docume n ted by cores arid gamma -tay log of MJ-2, displ a ying a progradatio~alT shoaling sequ~nce of calciluti te s - Alve olinid, micritic calcarenite - pelecypod ánd . _. sparry c alcaren ites .
. The most impo r t an t _ diag~n e tic effect on AHMAVl rocks _is the selective leaching o~ gr a ins and/ or matrix o b served in microfacies 38 .and4B r with development of moldic and vuggy porositie s . Non-cementing of original pores is responsible for the good interpartic le po~osity foun d in shoal calcarenites Two main porous interv~ls are o bs e rved in the uni t, one in the midd le and other ontop (61g u~e. 71 . In the · thick e r middle interval, rnoderate porositiesare found in outer shelf and barrier faci es ; . in spite of - the fact th~t most o f porasity ismoldic/ vuggy, some interparticle pores may be also irriportant .

. Othe r import a nt reservoir interva1 is the 'transgressive shoa1 calcareni tes d e v e 1opeª at the top of AH MAVI. These calcar e nit es ,showi n g good to exce1 1 ent interparticle porositi es , are ~e1l d evele p~ di n MJ-2 and MJ-3 ; it d e crease s in thicknes s and porosity towards MJ - 7. , The MlSHRIF/ RUMAILA 6o ~mat io~~ , of Cenoman i a n age , is t11e b est samp I ed un it in the area. Besides the HeI1 MJ-2, which Has complete ly c ered , frequcn t co r ing in othcr weIIs aII owe d to observe I ateiaI reIa tionsh{ps among dif f c r e nt facies.
The 'thickn ess of th e fo rma tion v arie s from 240
4.5.1 Micnogacies and Environmental Interpretation Rock s of this format,ion are ,.made up .of s e ve raI type sof fossils contents \-lhich cha ra cterize the deposi tional el'lvironrnents. PeIecypods (incIuding rudists) I Orbitolinids, AIveolinids and echinoids~ tegether with peloids , are the rnost Se~ime nt a ry te x tur e~ structure and compos i t i on . . t e n recogniz ed mic r ofacies are shown . on Tabi e 5. o f the This environmen ta l interpre tation (6lguhe 8J shows t h a t t he phys i c a l ene rgy gra du ~ lly i hcrea s ê d from low , in i nn e r she l f fa cies 11 to high, in b a rr iei f a cies, t hen Rudist s a re d e creasing towa rds oute r sh e1 f faci e s 5. p r edo~ inant in ~ a ci e s 2, where th e y. a re found bioaccumu1 ated or . revlOrke da1ong channels I common1y being ·transpqrted to th e )~ a r ri.e r faci es . In t h e outer s h e 1f, some Orbito1inid ',' 6 a l ca r e ~i~ es '~re fou nd fo r ming sho a 1 9 . The deepe s t facie s o b~ erve d c an b e assi ~n ed to a subtida1; oute r she lf environrne n t; no pl a nkto ni c~rich, de e p water ( slope ?) mar1 ~as found in t he fo rm ... ti o n.·
4. 5.2
The sequ e ntia1 analysis o f \ve1l MJ - 2 ShO\'IS f,our (6lgLLhe 9 lo, main r e gre s s i ve cycIes in MlSHRl F /RUMAILA tO fl.ll1 a;tloYl.6 The b as al por t i on .of th e t\<ToIowe r cycIes are represented by oü t .e r shelf d e posits, whiIe the same portion in the upper cycles contains only barrier deposits. This permit to infer a
>: SLE DEBE EIT LEONE EOE IDES SSL SEELEY LATERAL UA ZITA 16 TIS IRL a
t.'J G"
Some successions canbe ' seen in the · SCHLUl'-illERGER . . logs, which indic ate also a higher argillaceou~ content for inner s h elf facic s 2 and the "cl ean ll nature of high ene rgy barrier facies ( as .s hown in the gamma-ray log.
In the stratigraphic section of ó-LgulLe. 7, gamma· r ay/SP 1 0g5 , po r05ity evaluation (from 10gs and thin s e ctions) The and localization of. tlle cores were plotted for each ,,,,e 11. ", ~ .. ~ .,. " .' ~ . ", ~nt~rp reta tion 6f fa cies and their spatial di s tribution is tentát ive , since only MJ-2 was completed cored.
'1'he open marine facies 4 and 5 ' are uniformly distributed, as we ll as thc two Orbitolin~ shoa ls that occur in the s e condregressive cyc~e. The high energy facie~ 3 of the s econd cyc 1 e shot-ls thickening towards NU;.. 8 and MJ - 1, \'lhile 1 in the th'ird cycl e , it is restricted to MJ-2 and MJ-1. The " j lagoon a l facies 1 and 2 are not easil~ d{stinguished without cores; the more ~ rgillaceou~ nature of the rudist facies is suf f icient to separa·te them, since they are gradational .
- 4.5.3 Viagene~i~ and P Oho~ ity
The diagenetic evolution -and resulting porosities - ~ are intimately related to the initial fãbricof the sedimento The outer 'shelf calcilutites facies 5, presents only slight n eomorphism of -the matrix in the form of microspar oatche s, as well as pyritization o f the bioclasts. Porosity i5 n o t observed. i t is i 'mportant to In outer shelf facies 4 ~ distinguish between the'calcilutites (wackestones) and th e In the calcilutites it ~alc ar8ni tes (Orbitol i na packitone~) . is fr equently obs e~ved rieomorphism of matrix and dis s olution of grains (pelecy pods, green a lgae )with conseguent development of . mold ic and vuggy porosities; secondary cementation may The calcarenites may present primary qblit e rate thes e pores. rim cementation and some interparticle porosity; . howe ver, t~ey were a l s o sub j ected to leaching , allowing secondary poio si ties to develop. In both textural types, neomorphic syn'cé~xíal grO\-J'th on-echinoderms can be present.
In _the barrier facies 3, two differentdiagenetic processe s have been observed.
In higher energy calcareni tes of f 'acies 3(mainly .grainstones), primary rim ánd syntaxial' growth (echinoderms, pelecypod s ) c~mentirig occurs, without impairing their good iI1te rparticle porosities i a comple~e (irusy filling of the por es , is h a rdly found. The presence bf iarge,transported rudists may add appreciab~e intraparti cle andmoldic porosities, as vIe l l as local intercrystaíline porosi ty ',due to d olomi tization. This facj_es rn~y present pressure vlelding and neomo rphism of ma t r i x (when present )~ and locally internaI sedimento The .transi tional churned calcareni t es "(packstones and ' wackestones) o~ facies 3 exhibit matrix neomorphism and . ,', . ~. ~ g :raü~di~'solL1ti6n \Vith developrnent of con sequent moldic and vugg y p oro sities ; late cements may r educe these pores.
Neom6rphism of matrix ~nd pressure welding are also observed in ,rocks of ' inner shelf facies 2; aswell as , \ c al ci te -filledfractures and local dolomitization. Only matri cial porosity was recognized.
Penecont ~mporaneous 6~~d'~ eye structures and boring~ wi th vadose . sil t a re characteristic of lagoonal to' suppra tidal facies "lB. ' ,Dolomi ti zati on islocalized in ' borings Ol: al'ong argillac e ous streaks. . 'fhese rocks are normally tight.
In surunary , the main porosity types observed in
The di s tribut i o n of poros itie~ in well MJ ~ 2 indicates th a t the b es t r eservo irs are facies 3 caldarenites (inte rparticlc poro si ty), f o llowed by fadies 4 c a lcarenites / jca lcilutites (maldic and vu ggy po r o s ity) . The facie s 1, 2 abdS ~o no t h ave rocks with ade qu a tereservoi r cha~ac teristi cs.
P6rosity di ~ irib~~ion in open ma rine fac ies 4 and shoaljb ar s facies 3 ' shaws good l ateral continu ity throughout the area, except in cycle 111 (Figune 7).
facíes ' 3. and rarely .4C f ~c ies 3 and 2B (7) '. f a cies 2 ~ • 3, Lf
facies 3 f ac ies 3, 14- . , facies 2, 3 f acies 3
The study of ' this forrnation r of Turoni a n ag ~ r . . was limited to MAJMOON area r where two cores . from th e base (MJ-l and MJ-2) a~d twó from the middl e (MJ~3) were available. However, this information ,:Vas ,E::nough to provide a ·goo d under standi ng of the facie s and re servoir chara cteri stic s of the unit.
In the MAJ~OOM are a the thickn es softhe . for rna tion varies fr om 44 (MJ-l) to 62 meter s (MJ-2).
4.6.1 Micnrofacies and Envitonmental Interpretation 
Basicaliy, seven microfacie s were reco gni zed in
4.6.2 WVenticak Evolution, Stnatignaphy and Reservoirs 
The basal deposits of KHASI B ~tra nsg~es s over th e iÍ0Jc.liUl.tioJ1.ó . un~on:formity on top of ' ~nSHRIF/RUMAI L.Á ( faci es 4). . A subsequ ent general ' regres~ion took place, with the facies ranging from subtidal outer shelf to intertida l (barrier?)
Deep \wt e r 10-79 slope (?)
Finaily, a transgression, . culminating with de ep ( f a cie s 3) . water d e posits (faci~s 5), . occurs in t~e 'upper part of the unit In the regressive phase, two calcarenite . bars we r e d e posit e d, which .c a n be trac e d aIl over the MAJNOON a rea The thickest porous upper bar, made u p of cro s s- (Fi guJr.e 10). -bedded jchurned , pelecyb o d s calcare nite with interpa rticle po r o sity , i8 th e main ' res e rvoir of thetinit.
AsIope ( ?) origin for the upperpart of KHÁSI B '. ' FOJtm a.tion could e x plain the' abruptthinning observed ov e r a smal l di stance fr om MJ - 2 to MJ-1.
Thr ee cores (MJ-2) are avail able from t h is
. Fro m the studied samples, only an open marine , outer shelf facies was recognize~which ean be subdivided in . 7 I. thre e b a s ic mic r ofacies (Table Inte icalat ed in the shal ~s , a thin layer (O,jo me ters) of eross - bedded to ehurned limonitized oos parité oceu rs , probably representing o ffsh ore bars.
L_~~~ .. __ ~~=~_?_r ..,..."r ..... ,~ C8A'!'~eee-·~ .. ,.e.,-*~~~~:J
.. . .
. The Lower SA'VI / TANUM~ Sequence was depo site d No barrierjinner shelf sediments during a major regressi~n • . . . were e~counte~ed, confirming · th~op~n marine character of the · . .. . . sediments which ~r~ bounde~ by .the deeper water rock~ o~ KHASIB (upper part) and SA'VI 6o~mation~ (middlejup per pa rt ).
Similar to KHASIB, th~ Lower SA'VI/TANUMA . e thin s from MJ - 2 (60 mete.rs) to MJ -1 (47 meter s ), v.lhereas tIle abrupt thinning from MJ-2 to NU~g, as 'shown in 6igu ~e 10, requires further investigation.
T\>/o reservoirs are found i11 tl1e interval compr ising the LOvJer SA'VI and upper half. ~f the TAÚUMA 6oJuna..;t.,lo l'Ló (FiguJLe. 10). ThE'C . upper one, in the ' Lower SA I VI, consists of éalcareni tes o f micro~ ~cies 4Awith rnoldic low porQsi ties (MJ-2, . core 41. The lowe r reservoir,probably not deposited in NU-g well,seefus t o be of s ame natrire .
: No cores were ava ilable from this interval of Campania n to Santonian age, whose thickeness ranges from 103 meters, in MJ-2, ~o 87 meters, iti MJ-1 (Figu~e 10). Log interpr~tation and correl ~t ion su~gest a deep water depo sition Fi v e cor es' , coupl ed \-li th 10g interpretation, a110wed to de fine ;four basic faci es and to make inferenc es on ,e " the depositional settings of thi s unit of Maestrichtian age (Tab .te S ' ), ' A,t the bas e of faci es 3 calcarenites occurs a Loftusia-bioac c'.1illu lated limestone, vlhich is co"npa~abl e to the A1veolinid-bio a ccumulat ed limestones that directly underlie barrier ca1carenites , in AHMAVI and MlSHRIF/RUMAILA 6o ~m a~ion~.
, Th~ HARTHA Fo~mation is thicker in MJ-2 (~40 me ters) and thins towards NU-8 in MJ-1 (115 meters) J (105 meters), the unit seems tb b e p a rtly fau1ted out. A teptative distribution of facies through the wells is shown in I the stratigraphic ~ectio~ of Figu~e 10~ The unit was ,deposi ted ih a major regressive cycl"e, its more marine facies lower portion being overlain by in'ner shelf ' rudlsts arid l a goonal/supr,?tidal facies. , The uppermost, part of HARTHA FOJ[mation i s transgressive, and it
Subtidal 11-81 outer-shelf
The regr e ssive phase is ,alsoreflected , in the upward decreas ing of the clay conte nto The ma in reservoi r s are fou~d in the upperpart ofthe section (6 ,[g Uhe. 101. They con sist of inner shelf dolomitization is calcirudites f a cies 2 with moldic porositYi very common in t h i s facies add'ing intE~rcrystalline a nd vuggy porosity (MJ~3" core 4).
Probably the best reservoir, not core d yet, is the ca16are~ite facies 3 ~hi~h ocicur s in the upper p a rt6f the ' sebti on. A thin intercalation of thiS facies, ' having moldic/ /vuggy poros! ty f \-la s iden-ti fied in core 2 of MJ :" 2; interparticle poro s ity 15 al s o expect ed to occu r in facies 3.
Two kinds of poros l t y were ob served in the lagoona l / supratidalfacies 1: fenestral and breccia , and fractu re poros ity '(NU-S, core 6) . The ,fir st type seems to be unimportant and the s~cond has to be furtherevaluat e d. \ ' Finally~ the calcilutites from fa c ies4 arenon , ,porous. Though not yet identified, ,it is reasonable ' to pre~ict , the ' deve16pm~nt of green algae-c ~lcareni tes (rnicrofacies 4A ) , with its , cha~acterist moldi c porosity, as soc iated with The el1vironmental conditi0l1S, vertical evolut ion and porous intervals for the v arious studied carbonate un its are sumrnari.zed in ó-Lg U JLe. 11. In order to simpli fy the . illustration, the m;i.crofacies vleregrouped in thr ee bas ic - 21, barrier-. environments, name ly·, lagoonal-inner shelf (1 2:~h~:ülO\.., outer shelf (: - 4) and deep out.er shelf-s lope (?) (5-61. Deep water 6ondition~ started in the basin justafte~ depositi6n of the Albian NAHR UMR sandstones.
The Cretaceous system compri ses several major \ tiansgressive-regressi~e pulses, c~lminating with the deposition of shallow .water carbo nates of the SHUAIBA, MAUVVUV,AHMAVI, - . ". MISHRIF/RUMAILA; TANUMA/LOWER SA'VI and HARTHA óo~mat-Lon6. The carbona~es of the uppermost part of YAMAMA, the upper part of KHASIB and the HiddlejUpper SA'VI óOJLmctt-Lon.6 are tran sgressive.
In MAJNOON area most of the carbonate form a ti ons Exception ~s the SHUAIBA show good reservoir properties. FOJt.matiol1. that exhibits predominance of inner build-up facies; o! a = dn SSS TR a ate Cas Cem . ass oc i ated with b ar rieran~ shallow out ~i shelf sediments Th ebarrie~ reservoirs are the most importantj . j 1). ( .n-igUlLe. they are rep:, .. :e sented by pelecypod/pe loidal/intraclast calcarenites The outer wi th int erparticle and moldic/vuggy p orosi ties·. This s~elf sedime nts show only mo ld ~c /vu ggy' type porosities~ demons tr ates th ~t the depositional fabric is the main poro i ity . controlling factor, followed by solution process e s that may . . , ·. e nhance the original i,nterpa r ticle porosi ty and selecti vely dissolve textural c omponents of the rock. Fracture is algo loc.al lyimportan·t as a porosity agent. The knowl edge of th es e reservoir porosLty cha racteris;i:ics i5 important · because they may. hr:lve different · r eEjponses to compl et ion-stimulation teclmiques . .
The e valuation · of a petroleum field is improved by the ki1O\vl e dge of the geornetr y and porosity of th e reservoir ,~:" ""O""" I This s ~cudy, has demon s trated the direct control of the rocks. deposi~~onal environrnent and dia~enesis on the distrihution and properties ofthe carbonate r eservoirs.
( V eAÜc.a! d~Ií c.1Ú iQ 11 o fi ta b rd. -Ló 1. 1 em)
PLATE
Micro fa~ i es 4
PLATE
PLA TE
Hicrofac.ies 38:
(Verticak dimension of Label is 1.1 cm) 
PLATE
'. ' Transgr essive succéssion 6ntop of Formatje n : t-1 icrof a ci es 3: , Has s ive, ru'dist' calcirudite (pho t o 174), be coming arg il1 a c eous uph'ards (phot o175) and grading to microfacies 5, bioclastic mar1 (pho t o 176) (HJ-2,core 31,2777.6 / 2778,2 m)
(Vertical dimension of Label is 1.1 em) 
PLATE
PLAT.E
PLATE
PLATE
, [VeJl-Uea.t wneYlJ.,iolt 06 .tabet -U 1.1 em)
PLATE
Microfacies 48:
Hicrofacies 5: .e
. . (VeJtUeal cWne;v.;-tOlt. Oó .e.abei. ~ 1.1 CJ1t)
PLATE
PLATE
. Mi crofac i es 3
.. (MJ-2, core 41~ 3906.0m, PT: 166)
PLATE
Microfacies
B - Churn ed, biocla st ic c a lciluti~e (wackestone). Arenaceous foraminifers ' (P~~udocyclamin ~ » Mi li01 ids, d~s~clads, mol1u~k ~ debris, ostracods, sponge spi' cules. ' " .. ;: :~~ ' r (I~J-2, core 37, ,3838. O m; PT 211)
PLATE
PLATE
. A. - Calci1utite (\oJackestone) ' \'Jith planktonic foraminifers, Rotalids, ' ostracods, sma11 echinoid .debris . ' (MJ-l, core 10, 2705.0 m; PT82) B -: Churned,bioc ·1asticcalcilut.ite (wackestone). Planktonic a~d hyaline be nthic forams, pelecypod debris, ostraccids.,echinoidi. Pyrite inside grains. . (MJ~2, core 3', 2778~0 m,
PLATE 15'
~icrof A cies 5
PLATE
PLATE
A .~ · Churned, micritic biocaJcareriite (pa~~st~ne}. Pelecypod ~ebris and -rare echi,noi,ds, behthonic fo,raminifers;. neomorphic spa .. , rare vuggy porosity. (MJ-2, core 10, 2541;~ ' m,
Mi crofac i es . 38
PLATE
A - Bioclastic ·calti1utite (wackestone) .with bent.honic fora mi ni fe r s: . ·(Nezzazata, Hi 1101 ids, Alveol inlds, Cun.eol ina), mollusk and stromatoporoid debri~, ·ostracods . .. Neomor~his~ of ma t rix (MJ - 2, . core 17, · 2588.8 ~, . PT .340)
PLATE 19"
..... . A - ·. Bioturbated, bi~~1astic ca1c-ltutite (w.ackeston~)with planktonic "(Globotruncand) and .hyal ine .benthon ic . (Rota1 ids) .' foramini fers, · ostracods. echinbids and pelecyp6d debri6 • . ' . . (MJ-2,core6,. 2403.3m, PT. :380) (Polarized light 45x) ' .
. :·: ·. ;·;: E "L'~~h~~·;hed-;:>'· bio~:f~s·tic 'calcisi1tit~ wi 'ch 1adie rud"ists and gastropod~(?) • . Porcel1aneous (Alveo1 inids, Mi 1 i01 ids), arenaceous and o hyal ine '. ' benthoni~ fora~inifers; ostracods, green , a1gae; sponge. . Very low poros i ty.
