DOCUMENTO CONTÉM DADOS ILEGIVEIS.
Sands·tone samples from four offshore basirrs of northern Brazil were studied to. àetermine the petrographic and diagenetic features that control reservoir quality. Se veral hundr~d thin sections of samples from Cassipore, Ilha de Santana, Ceara and Potiguar basins between depths of 10 to 40 m in offshore wells wereexamined, and point counts were made' of 99 samples. A few samples from depths of appr.2. ximately 30~m from onshore wells in the Potiguar basin we-t re s tu d i ~ d a 1 s o·.
Sandstones from all the basins are arkoses, ty pical of rift-basin deposits, but the sandstones differ noticeably in types of rock fragments and ratios of plagiocl~ se to K-feldspar. Sandstones f rom the Cassipore basin are rich in plagioclase and volcanic rock fragments of interme-, diate co~position; sandstones "from the Ilha de Santana ba sin are rich in plagioclase and have sub-equal minor amounts fragments ; of volcanic, sedimentary and metamorphic rock sandstones from the Ceara and Potiguar basins are rich in to tal f e 1 d s p a r a n d h a vem i n o r a m o u n t s o f s e d i me n t a r y a n d 1 ow grade metamorphic rock fragments. Plagioclase is three ti mes as abundant ~s K-feldspar in the Cassipore and Ilha de Santana basins, but is of equal or lesser abundance than K feldspar in the Ceara and Potiguar basins.
All the sandstones under study had excellent re servoir properties at the time of deposition. lhe present reservoir quality is entirely the product of diagenetic pr.2. cesses. Sandstones responded differently during diagenesis because of original differences in composition (influenced type of cement), texture (influenced permeability and flow of cementing and decementing fl~ids), and depth of burial (in-o PETROBR~S--------------____________________ __ PETROLE O BR ASILEIRO S A i i i fluenced th~ degree ofc6~p~ctionl. Al , thoug~ the sequenee of diagenetic events , can b~ established reasona61y well, it is not possible to deferrriine ' thedepths at which parti'eu 'lar event took place.
The 10ss of poros!ty thro:ugh compaction t nc~e.! ses with depth of burial. Even at' shi1low depths of 5uria1, however, sandstones with 'abundant mica and s,oft 'SRf's and MRF's (chief1y fine-grained sandstones) lost ~uch or ~ost primary porosity by compaction.
In most sandstones, however, 1 qss of priJuary 'P.2, rosity occurred 1arge1y by cementation. Cassip~re sandsto - ' . . . , . . nes are cemented chiefly by corrensite (regular1y inter1aye' red ch10rite-smectite) ca1cite and zeo1ite (laumontitejheu landite). Sandstones from the other basins had a more corn-· plex history of cementation. Ca1cite was the main ear1y di~ genetic cement, and kaolinite and ch10rite are the main la te diagenetic cements. In the Ceara and Potiguar basins, kao linite has not been detected below 3,000 m, where~s i11{te is common deeper than 3,000 m.
A1l porosity inthe sandst'One :' today fs se:conda ry porosity that developed chiefly by t-h:e 'di 's'soluti 'on of c.ar bonate cement, plagioclase grai ,ns, and ca1citized feldspar and to a ' lesser degree by the dissolution Df la~mont;'te, K feldspar, rock fragments, ferromagnesium minerals and possi bly authigenic c1ay mi'nerals. The on1y possi'ble primary P.2. res are small pores among corrensite cement in Cassipore sandstones.
From core an~lysis data itis possib1e to est! blish three types of reservoir quality: Type Rl is excellent, Type R2 is fair, and Type R3 is non~economic. Although few Type Rl sands are deeper than 3,000 m; there is only a poor correlation of Type R1 sands with depth and no corre1ation with depositional environment. Petrographic data indicate that:
1. T y P e R 1 s a n d $ to n e s a.r e c o a r s e r 9 r a i n e d o r be t . ' ter sorted than Type R2 or R3 ' sandstones. Type R1 sandstones developed exce11ent secondary porosity and lost very 1it i i i
3. Type R3 sandstanes are thase that , develaped anly tri vi al secandary poros; ty ar nane ~t . ill. T-be -':-l'a~tt'er' " sands include thase that lost allparo~ityby ~ compã'C~fi dn~~as well as those that lost porosity by compactior{ com't9i ' r;'é-d~i;th : cementation. Type R3 sandstones are typical of thei~ Cá's:g1iP.2.:: re basin, and the red beds (or once-red beds) of , ttié dee'jJ'er : p a r t s o f t h e I 1 h a de S a n ta n a a n d P o t i 9 u a r b a s i n s . "' '" c • ,.
Fi ve di ageneti c zones were defi ned for the sand~ tones in the study area. Zone 11 in the depth range of-15:00 : -2500 m has the best reservoir propertijs associated t6 ih~ maturation window. Therefore,it fulfills the paif ' ~átutati : on/reservoir requirement, which in an exploratory ( di~ision making process it plays a very important role~ "" :( In view of the intense diagenetic transformati ons acti ng upon the reservoi r rocks' ~th'êre i s gOO(1' 'poss ;i b'i lity of finding dia.ge~etically t~ap'ped reser'voirs in "the ba sins. In adition, diagenet;'c 'traps 'does nol have necessarly .- to be related to structural highs .
Recommendation for additional exploration is to seek the coars~~t and best-sorted ~ahdstones. In general, this suggests ~oving preferably in updip directions. Sands that have the bést primary permeability generally develop the best seco~dary secondary porosity and permeability. , , , Good reservoir quality is shown in samples from . " the onshore Poti~uar basin arid tin the Alagoas ~i~h in the :., 1 Ilha de Santana basin.
Because of the abundance of clay mineral ceme~ ts in the sandstones studied, caution must be used during well K a o 1 i n i te 9 r a i n s c a n t e a r 1 o o s e f r o m s i te s o f stimulations. flow to block pore throats; corrensite and attachment and with HCl to f ~ om iron-hydroxide sludge; and chlorite react iv corrensite may be somewhat ' ~értsttiije to fresh water. Initial· sá~dito~e ~ ~dmposition pre - programmed the later diagenetic ejé~ts. r p6~~~t1on waters ~eatted with volcanic rock debris and ferromagnesian minerals in the Ca~ sipore basin sands to produce corrensite and la~montite and with feldspar in sands in the oth~r ' ba~in5 ~ ~0 develop ka01! nite and possibly illite. The sourte of the · ~biquftous ca~ bonate minerals i5 unknown, but much · cal~i~m ~as probably released during the albitization of plagioclase. Kaolinite i5 slight1y more abundant in sandstones beneath unconformi ties but is not restricted to such areas.
Most pyrite in the sandstones apparent1y formed when oi1 and H2S passed through the sands and reduced ferric iron-oxide present as grain coatings (in red beds) and in ferromagnesium minera1s to ferrous iron su1fide. Kao1inite cement (except possib1y the coarse-grained form) is oil stai - ( ned andpreceded hydrocarbon migration. Hydrocarbon migration and entrapment must have been late because we found no difference in diagenesis between oi1-wet and water-wet sands tones. lhe purpose of the phase 11 of "Diaginese dos reservatórios terrigenos da foz do Amazonas ate a bacia Po tiguar" is to introduce a regional diagenetic study and sum marize the reservoir rock characteristics of the offshore ba sins of northern Brazil.
Duri ng phase I of the present project ,fi ve di a genetic zones were determined from eletrical logs. Petrogr~ phic and petrophysical analysis perfor~ed an core samples confirmed the variations observed for the diagenetic zones detectedin the earlier work.
The zones are distributed within there diagen! tic provinces (Fig. 1). , w·ith i.'1creasing reservoir quality to wards Potiguar basin.
Four basins - Cassipore, Ilha de Santana, Cea ra and Potiguar - were selected for the study (Fig. 1). The depth of sampling of these Lower Cretaceous sandstones va ries from 10 to 40 m in offshore wells: a few onshore samples are available at a depth of approximately 300 m in the Potiguar basin (Table 1).
The basins underwent essentially the same tec tonic histo r y and are characterized by normal faulting (horst and graben) of Early Cretaceous age. Lower Cretaceous rocks are overlain unconformably by Upper Cretaceous/Tertiary pa~ sive-margin sedimentary rock. The sedimentary rocks analy sed belong to the continental sequence of the Rift phase.
Three main depositional facies were identified during previous work-alluvial-fluvial~ fluvial-deltaic, and deltaic-1acustrine. The facies were defined on the basis of pa1eonto10gical data and core and 10g ana1ysis {Figs. 2, 3, 7!>JO - 000 - 0t:i4JO
INTRODUCTION
4}. Cas.sipore basin rocks are of deltaic-lacustrine origins; those of the Ilha de Santana basin are alluvial-fluvial at greater depths and deltaic-lacustrine in younger rocks. The sedimentary rocks analysed from the Ceara and Potiguar ba sins were mainly of deltaic-lacustrine type, with minor flu vial-deltaic facies.
2.
Petrographic analysis of core samples was the basis of the present work.
Initially, using thin sections, samples were vi sually separated into two groups on the basis of grain size using a low-power microscope. Two grain size classes - coa.!: se/medium and fine/very fine were subdivided with a bounda ry value of 0.25 mm.
A plot was then made of porosity versus permea bility (Fig. 5). The result of such a plot guided the thin section study. 99 thin sections were point counted using an average of 250 points per slide to determine mineral compo sition and the percentage of various pore types.
_ lhin sections were stained for feldspar using sodium cobaltinitrite to allow a quick ~nd safe identifica tion between potash feldspar and plagioclase. The petrogr~ phic analysis focused on the framework composition, mineral cements, pore geometry and diagenetic history.
.. lhe use of the scanning eletron microscope(SEM) and X-ray analysis were necessary and useful to identify th~ minerals, particularly clay minerals, carbonate and zeolite cements. Late in the course of the study an EDAX unit was added to the SEM, and it was possible to identify minerals at the time of SEM investigations.
Finally, permeability and porosity data toge ther with the macroscopic core descriptions were added to the microscopic results to provide a wider and better unde~ tood picture of the diagenet;c processes and responses.
-Methodology
The present mineralogy of the sandstones under study (Tables 2-14; Figs ~ 5a-j) is a function of the comp~ sition of the sand supp1ied to the basin of deposition plus modifications (precipitation of authigenic minerals, disso1ution of others) that took place after deposition (that is, diagenetic changes). Although the original sand framework composition _of many samples has been modified to some degree by the calcitization of feldspar and s~e rock fragments and by the selective dissolution of plagioclase, the original compos~tion of most samp1es can be inferred fairly reliably. We find a noticeable difference in sand framework mineralo gy among the four basins. Because the basins have a simi lar tectonic setting, and deposition was within anarrow ra~ geof depositional environments within them, the observed dif. ferences in sand composition reflect different source rock~ Sandstones from all the basins are arkoses, typical of rift basin deposits, but the sandstones differ noticeably in ty pes of rock fragments and ratios of plagioclase to K-felds pars. Sands from the Cassipore bas;n were derived from a terrain chiefly .of volcanic, hypabyssal, and high grade me tamorphic (amphibolite) source rocks. Acid plutonic and vol canic rocks and reworked sandstones were lesser contributors. The Ilha de Santana basin detritus was supplied by subequal amounts of volcanic-hypabyssal, high grade metamorphic, and sedimentary rocks. Plutonic rocks were of minor importance. The Ceara and Potiguar basins received considerably more pl~ tonic detritus than the other bas;ns, significant amounts of reworked sedimentary rocks, but only minor volcanic detr; tus.
4.
=::= ~~!E~B~~~~&~ ----------------------------------------------~ 5. mineralogy, data for each basin are summarized on QFL trian gular diagrams and QmPK triangular diagrams (Figs. 5a - h). Data for a11 basins are p10tted in Figure 5i-j. Feldspar composition varies regiona11y. P1agi~ clase is three times as abundant as K-fe1dspar in the Cassi ~ore and Ilha de Santana basins, but is of equa1 or 1esser abundance than K-fe1dspar in the Ceara and Potiguar basins. In order to search for relations,sandstone com position, grain size, depth of burial, and reservoir parame te r s c r os s p 1 o t s we r e ma de (F i 9 s. 6 - 38) . A 1 t h ou 9 h t h e re i s considerable scatter of data, the plots confirm general im pressions made during the thin-section phase of the study. Some cross p10ts have essential1y random data points, whe reas others show weak trends and a few show strong trends. For exemple, Figures 7 and 8 illustrate p10ts of depth ver sus fe1dspar content (5 to 45%) and mica content (O to 20 % ~ Feldspar composition varies regiona11y. P1agi~ clase is three times as abundant as K-fe1dspar in the Cassi ~ore and Ilha de Santana basins, but is of equa1 or 1esser abundance than K-fe1dspar in the Ceara and Potiguar basins. t Sand framework composition played a major role in determining the types of cements that formed. Two main a s sem b 1 a 9 e s o f c e me n t m i n e r a 1 s a r e p r e s e n t (T a b 1 e s 3 - 1 4; F i 9 s. 12-25): In the Ceara and Potiguar basins kaolinite has not been detected below approximately 3000 m, whereas illite is most common deeper than 3000 m. Coincidentally this depth is roughly the boundary between the fluvio-deltaic and del taic-lacustrine facies (Fig. 10). In the Ilha de Santana ba sin kaolinite extends to greater depths but in lesser amo unts (less than 2.5%). Carbonate cement is most abundant at a depth interva1 of 2 to 3 km but occurs at al1 depths.
1. corrensite/ch1orite-zeolite (laumontite) carbonate (Cassipore basin). , 2. carbonate-kao1inite-chlorite-il1ite-quartz feldspar-smectite (a11 but the Cassipore ba si n ) .
5.
The Cassipore basin is 10cated at the norther~ most portion of the rifted basin and received an abnorma1 amount of vo1canic detritus. This detritus reacted with p~ re fluids to provide a unique mineralogica1 cement assemb1~ ge, the type commonly found in basins of active spreading margins. The sandstones can be c1assified as l ·ithic arkose (Tab1es 3, 4). Heavy minerals make up to 4% of samp1es and have a predominance of amphibo1e (Table 5). The fe1dspar con tent is dominated by plagioclase of albitic composition(Fig. 26). Figures 23, 27 and 28 show that permeability is slig~ tly negatively correlated with epimatrix.and carbonate con tent, and has a slightly positive corre1ation with grain si ze. The number of samples ('14) is small, so no detailledst~ tisticaltreatment shou1d be performed. However, thin sec-t tion analysis supports the trends mentioned above. The occu~ rence of laumontite associated with corrensite/chlorite is indicative of a diagenetic paleotemperature in the order of 90QC (Sudo and Shimoda, 1978; Hoffman and Hower, 1979).
Samp1es from the Ilha de Santana basin have few 1ithic fragments (no more than 5%). The feldspar content shows a distinct difference throughout the depth sequence. The shallower sámp1es of deltaic-1acustrine facies have higt"Er K-fe1dspar content (2-12 %), whereas a11uvia1-f1uvia1 facies at greater depth have almost no K-feldspar (0-1 %), (Fig. 29, 28a). Kao1inite and carbonate are the main cements, with chlorite present as a coating on detrital grains and as a minar pore-filling cement.
Most of the sandstones below the unconformity at approximately 2600 m were once red beds. Traces of hema tite are still preserved inside some clay clasts and micas, and as thin coatings on other detrital grains. Apparently Ilha ~e Santana Basin
7.
The major difference between Ceara and Ilha de Santana basins is in feldspar composition. Despite similar framework QFL compositions, the K-feldspar in the Ceará ba sin is significantly higher (Fig. 5f, 5j; Table 10). The high feldspar content and dominant K-feldspar composition most likely reflect a thinner metamorphic cover in the sou~ c e a r e a . A _c 1 e a r d e c r e a s e o f f e 1 d s p a r c o n te n tis r e 9 i s te red for depths greater than 3000 m (Fig. 7)r Figures 30 and 35 s h o w n o c o r r e 1 a t i o n b e t w e e n f e 1 d s p a r t y P e s . I n t h e P o t i 9 ua r basin there mav have been a preferential destruction of pl~ gioclase by calcitization and dissolution.
Kaolinite an9 carbonates are the most comrron ce ments. Locally, quartz and feldspar cements can be of appre ciable quantity (up to 8% and 4% "respectively, Tables 11, 14). In the Potiguar basin below a depth of 2700 m, chlori te and illite cement dominate, followed by the dissappeara~ ce of kaolinite cement.
.. Figures 31 to 38 show possible weak correlati ons between grain size and different cements with permeabi lity. A positive correlation with permeabilityis assigned to grain size, and a negative correlation is obtained for kaolinite, carbonate and epimatrix cements. Despite the small number of samples (69), there seems to be a threshold value before cement starts playing a more effective role in influencing permeability values.
Ceari and Potiguar Basins
8.
From a regional evruuation of permeability and porosity data, three basic types of reservoirs with the fo1 lowing characteristics were identified (Figs. 39, 41,43, 45 and table below): The above c1assification e's ta b 1 i s h e s a practi-ca1-economica1 re1ationship in terms of permeabi1ity and p~ rosi ty of the rocks. Therefore, a Type Rl reservoi r wi 11 ha ve good qua1ity, a Type R2 reservoir wi11 be a fair qua1ity reservoi r, and, dependi ng· on other factors (Tab 1 e 15), either be . commercia1 or non-commercia1. Fina11y, a Type R3 reser vo i r w i 1 1 b e r a Ute r - ti 9 t h ..
P~tro-graphic studies were conducted wi th the above c1assification in mind. With respect to permeabi1ity and porosity, it was found that (1) the same facies at the same depth may have different porosity and permeabi1ity va lues, {2} different facies at the same depth may have simi lar va1ues, {3} different facies at the same depth may have different reservoir qua1ity~ and {4} the same facies at the same depth may have the same reservoir values (Figs. 2~ 3, and 4; and Tab1e 15).
We tried to identify the factors that were re~ ponsib1e for the different performance of each reservoir ty pe (most of which are extremely heterogeneous). lt was found that the permeabi1ity and porosity properties of the reser voirs are a function of one or more of the fo11owing param! ters: (3) OlFFERENTlAL OlAGENETlC EVOLUTlON due to a greater or 1esser f1uid circulation (diagenetic trap)~ ce mentation, etc.
·Additional factors are the thickness of sand and sha1e beds in the sequence, degree of compaction, proximity to unconformities, etc. (Tab1e 15).
10.
To better understand the permeability-porosity behavior of the above mentioned basins, various plots, dia grams and histograms were constructed for each basin, and for the Ceara basin, for every wel1 that had a significant vol~ me of data (Figs. 39 to 62). The permeability-porosity be havior of the four basins studied can be summarized, on the basis of data considered in the present report o , as follow: /
/ CASSIPORE: based upon samples from wells l-APS -18 and 19 it is clear that the sandstones have such poor reservoir quality as to constitute economic basement.
ILHA DE SANTANA: sandstones have reasonably good reservoir quality in deltaic-lacustrine facies of the top of the Alagoas high. These sandstones have potencial if hydrocarbon maturation is adequate. The continental red bed facies have reservoirs of poor quality. Special attention should be given to the Upper Cretaceous reservoirs in this • basin.
CEARA: the best values Df permeability and p~ rosity are present in this basin (Mundau area), especially in the depth range of 1500-2500 m (Fig. 63).
POTIGUAR: the basin is similar in many res-pects to the Ceara and has similar reservoir quality, both in the Lower Cretaceous section and in the Upper Cretaceous (RNS-5 for instance). Reasonable reservoir quality extends to the proximity of 3500 m (Fig. 64).
In the onshore area, despite the small number of available data, the results obtained are highly encoura ging (Figs. 46 and 47).
11.
All the sandstones under study had excellent r~ servoir properties at the time of deposition. Although th~ re were differences in grain size and sorting and, thus, inl tial porosity and permeability, studies of modern sands in dicate that they had excellent reservoir quality at the tl me of deposition. The present reservoir quality of sandst~ nes from the Brazilian offshore basins is the product enti rely of diagenetic processes. Typical ~f most sandstones, those under study display a complicated sequence of diagen~ tic events. Within individual basins the sequence of events seems to have beeen the same for all sandstones, although the sandstones did not all undergo the same events nor undergo them to the same degree of intensity. The relative import~ ce of each diagenetic step in influencing present reservoir quality of individual sandstone samples is shown inTab1e 15. Sandstones behaved differently during diagenesis because of original differences in composition (influenced the types of cement) and .texture (influenced permeability and the flow of cementing and decementing fluids) and depth of burial (i.!! fluenced compaction). Certain diagenetic events, such as compaction, cannot be dated precisely. Compaction is shown at an arbitrary position in Figure 65. Late-stage pyrite probably formed when H2S invaded the sandstones.
Although the sequence of diagenetic events can be established reasonab1y well, it is not possib1e at pre sent to determine the depths at which particular events took place. Most sandstones underwent one or more episodes of uplift during their burial history.
When discussing the porosity in the sandstone
1 2.
A brief discussion of each diagenetic event ~d its role in inf1uencing reservoir qua1ity is given in the following pages.
A11 porosi ty present in the sandstones ana1ysed is secondary porosity. The only possib1e exception is sma11 may pores among corrensite in the Cassipore basin - these by be preserved primary pores. Secondary pores developed
Importance of Secondary Porosity
13.
....... PETROBRAS - .... - -____________ _ . . . . . . - PETROLEO BRASILEIRO 5.A 14. the disso1ution chiefly of carbonate cement, plagioclase grains, ca1citized plagioclase grains, and to a lesser de gree by the disso1ution of 1aumontite, K-fe1dspar, rock fra~ ments, ferromagnesian minera1s and possib1y authigenic c1ay minera1s.
The disso1ution of minera1s from sandstones in the subsurface is a common feature in many basins, and in some,it is the chief stage in reservoir development (McBri de, 1977; Schmidt and McDonald, 1979a; Hayes., 1979). De carboxylation of organic matter during therma1 maturation of hydrocarbons is a presumed major subsurface source of CO 2 to produce carbonic acid for this diss01ution event(Schmidt and McDona 1 d, 1979a). Other aci d wa ter may come from during c1ay diagenesis when H+ are re1eased.
Textura1 evidence for the orlgln of secondary pores inc1ude the f01lowing (cf. McBri~, 1977, Schmidt and McDona1~, 1979b):
1. oversize pores (Figs. 74, 88,94,96, 97, 111). 2. "honey-comb" or ske1eta1 detrita1 grains (Figs. 70, 93, 99, 100, 114) ·. ..-4 3. re1ict c1ay coats on detrital grains 4. intragranu1ar pores in rock fragments and micas and fe1dspars (Figs. 106, 107) 5. patchy carbonate cement in sandstones that have the same degree of compaction in cemented and uncemented areas (Figs. 88, 89). 6. e10ngate pores (cana1s) in quartz fe1dsparand heavy minerals that formed when clacite diss01ved from hea 1ed fractures (Figs. 71, 90). 7. b r o k e n s i 1 i c a te 9 rai n s : u p o n di s sol u t i o n o f c a r b o na te cement, rocks compact rapid1y and some grains fracture (Fig. 96).
Disso1ution pores vary in size, shape, and di! tribution. In some samp1es all carbonate cement minera1s w~ re dissolved to produce exce11ent reservoir qua1ity. Subse quent partial cementation by clay minera1s genera11y redu-7530 - 000
14. ced secondary porosity considerably. And in some samples dissolution was minor or trivial such that only micropores or widely scattered, isolated mesopores developed.
In the Cassipore basin very fine sandstones had a different diagenetic history from medium to coarse-grained samples (Fig. 65). Finer grained sands had more detrital clay, mica, and clayey rock fragments . . They lost much pri mary porosity by compaction of these soft, flexible grains. Most remaining pores were completely filled by corrensite c~ ment (Fig. 66). The corrensite is probably a reaction pro duct between aqueous pore fluids and volcanic rock fragments, calcic plag~oclase, and ferromagnesian minerals. This fi ne-grained sandstones did not develop f\oticeable porosityd.!! ring the late diagenetic dissolution events.
Coarser-grained sandstones had a more complex history. They underwent a minor amount of cementation by quartz and clay (chiefly ~hlorite as a rim-cement) and then were tightly cemented by corrensite and the zeolite laumon tite (Figs. 67,68). These latter minerals precipitated, in part, simultaneously. Heulandite and laumontite also repl~ ced some detrital grains (Figs. 69, 71). Minor amounts of 1aumontite, plagioc1ase (Figs. 67, 70), and possib1y corre~ site and ferromagnesian minerals disso1ved during a late diagenetic event to produce some secondary pores (Figs. 67, 71 ) .
Compaction effects are shown by mashed rock fra.9.. ments (Fig. 72) deformed micas, and in p1aces, by pressure solution contacts between detrita1 grains (Figs. 67, 73). Clay fi1ms between detrital grains somehow promote pressure solution - a role played by corrensite in these rocks.
Essential1y al1 pores in sandstones from the Cassipore are micropores among corrensite (Figs. 67, 68) or intragranular pores in uncompletely dissolved feldspar (Fig. 70) and volcanic rock fragm~nts. Extensive m;croporosity
Cassipore Basin
1 5 ~ Sandstones of this basin show some differences in diagenesis as a function of depth of burial (more compa~ tion in samples deeper than 2,000 m), grain size, and stra tigraphic position (Fig. 65).
For samples shallower than 2,600 m, there is so me eoarse-grained kaolinite that probably is very early di~ genetic based on its texture similar to early-formed kaoli nite in the Ceara and Potiguar basins (Fig. 78). Quartz c~ ment is present locally (Fig. 79), but is trivial except in some well-so'rted medium-grained samples (e.g. l-MAS-8,3299.2 m). Some sandstones (e.g. 1.-MAS-8, l63~.9 m) were complet~ ly eemented soon after deposition by ealeite and did not d~ ve1~p seeondary porosity (Fig. 81). Otners (e.g. l-MAS-8 , 1630.2 m) developed minor seeondary porosity when some cal eite cement and plagioclase was dissolved. Some seeondary po res were subsequently filled by clay cement lmixed-layer or ehlorite~ Figs. 83, 84). Sample 2584.8 m (1-MAS-8) lost most of its primary porosity by the compaction of micas and therefore had no porosity left at the time that calcite ce ment formed in most other sands.
Most sandstones deeper than 2600 m were once red beds as shown by remnants of hematite in these samples and the presence of some red shales in the cores. The deve lopment of hematite grain coat was the earliest diagenetic event for these samples. Most samples then were strongly c~ mented by calcite (much of it poikilotopic). During deeper burial, some of the carbonate dissolved to produce seconda ry pores. Some secondary pores at shallow depths were fil led by kaolinite, whereas those in deeper samples were coa ted by chlorite (e.g. 3842.3 m; Fig. 86). It is not cl ea r whether the chlorite precipitated directly or wheter it fo~ . med as an alteration oroduct of kaolinite that formed a t a , shallower depth of burial.
Ilha de Santana Basin
16.
Severa1 samples (e.g. 1-MAS-8, 3299.2 m) under went a later, probably deeper stage of dissolution whith mi nor amounts of plagioclase partly dissolved. These late-for med secondary pores are free of clay mineral cements but they are toa small and too few to have improved the reservoir qu~ lity much.
Although some samples from the Ilha de Santana basin have porosities greater than 20 percent (Figs. 41,42), most pores in the samples are micropores that produce low permeabilities (Fig. 42). Micropores are present among the clay mineral cements and in incompletely dissolved feldspars and rock fragments. In addition, younger clay cements (ka~ linite and chlorite; Figs. 83,86) line ar fill some ofthe secondary pores and retard permeability. Although seconda ry mesa - and megapores are present locally, they are too scattered and isolated to produce good permeability. t t The deeper sandstones are poorly sorted, typical of red beds, and they 10st considerab1e primary porosi ty through compaction as we11 as by cementation by carbona te. On1y minar secondary porosity was deve10ped in these once-red beds. Sufficient permeôbi1ity developed to permit H2S to invade the sandstones and convert ferric iron in he matite to ferrous iron in pyrite.
Sandstones of this basin had a fairly uniform diagene~ic history (Fig. 83c). A few samp1es (e.g. 1-CES-41, 2700. m) developed trivial early kaolinite (Figs. 118,119), and quartz cement (Fig. 88) and then were total1y cemented by calcite and have remained tight to the present (Fig. 89). Most sands underwent trivial cementation by quartz, a mode rate amount of compaction, then complete cementation by ca! bonate. Later, considerab1e secondary porosity developed when carbonate and p1agioc1asegrains dissolved (Figs. 90, 91, 99, 100). Most sandstones saw the 10ss of some seconda ry porosity when kaolinite a.nd minar ch10rite gre\'1 in the
Ceara Basin secondary pores (Figs. 93, 94, 99). Kao1inite occurs in sandstones from the Ceará and Potiguar basins with three grain-size modes. The coar sest mode is about 20 to 40 f in diameter (Fig. 87) and common1y deve10ped as an a1teration of mica grains (Fig.72). This coarse-grained mica is demonstrably very early in some samples (i't precedes quartz cement Fig. 87 . ). Possibly all kao1inite with this coarse-grained mo de in Qther basins was ear1y also, but definite proof is lacking. The other two modes of kao1inite (approximately 5 to 10f and 5p) are late d i a 9 e n e t i c 9 r a i n s t h a t 9 r e w i n s e c o n d a r y p o r e s (F i 9 s . 93, 9 4, 98,99 100). This late kaolinite preceded hydrocarbon entra~ ment because it is present in both oi1-wet and waterwet co res (Fig. 110). The a1uminum and si1icon in kaolinite pro bab1y were derived, in part, from disso1ution/alteration prQ ducts of feldspar grains. A few samples (Figs. 95, 95) ha ve tiny overgrowths of feldspar (mostl~ K-feldspar) on de trita1 feldspar grains. These overgrowths developed during early diagenesis, also probably from alteratior.jdissoluticr. products of other detrita1 fe1dspar. Many sandstones ~ave both calcite and ferroan Many sandstones ~ave both calcite and ferroan do10mite (ar ankerite) cements (Figs. 97, 117). Based on textural ' relations and evidencc from other rocks (McBride , unpub1ished data), calcite probably was the first carbonate cement and during later diagenesis much, in places all" was converted to ferroan dolomite. Iron probably is released fran shales during clay mineral diagenesis (Boles and Franks,1979). Many carbonate grains are corroded and are evidence of in complete dissolution (Figs. 91, 97). Carbonate replaced so me detrital grains, chief1y p1agioclase (Fig. 89).
Pyrite formed during the passage of sour gas through the sandstones. It replaced micas, cement and sand grains (Fig. 117) and occurs as scattered concretions in ma ny samp1es (Fig. 98).
The reservoir characteristics of sandstones from the Cear; basin have been summarized ear1ier. The wide ran ge in reservoir qua1ity reflects (1) the degree to which the 1ate-stage dissolution of c~rbonate cement, calcitized grain~ 1530 - 000 - Ot.i·lJO
18~ and plagioclase developed clean secondary pores (Figs. 95, 96) and (2) the extent to which late-stage clay minerals (la.!:. gely kaolinite) plugged the secondary pores. In general,the best secondary porosity exists in sandstones that initial1y had the best reservoir quality: the coarsest grained and best sorted sands. Considerable microporosity (and atten - dant low permeability) exists in samples with only minor se condary pores and in areas of kaolinite cement.
The Potiguar basin samples show the greatest v2-. riation in diagenetic events because of the wide range of textures and of cored depths. Early events include develo~ ment of coarse-grained kaolinite (alteration of micas ?; Fig. 101), thin chlorite coats (Figs. M02, 103) and quartz and feldspar cement (Fig. 104). A11 had trivial effect on r e :; e r v o i r q u a 1 i t Y . C o m p a c t i c nl wa s t r i v i a 1 f o r $ h a 11 o'.'! s a m - p1es but increased in importance with depth (Fig 105). All samples underwent strong ~ementation by calcite (later alte red largely to ferroan do1omite; Figs. 106, 117). During deeper burial, variable amount of carbonate (Figs.l07, 108) a n d p 1 a 9 i o c 1 as e ( Fi 9 s. 1 09, 11 O) wa s di s sol ve d to p r o d uce s ~ condary porosity of exce11ent reservoir qua1ity (Fig. 108). The best secondary porosity developed in the coarsest sand~ tones (e.g. 7-UB-14, 2403 m; Fig. 111) and secondari1y in the best sorted sandstones. A11 sandstones subsequentlylost some porosity by the precipitation of late-stage kaolinite in secondary pores (Figs. 109,111) in samp1es shallowerthan 2 , 6 O O m a n d b Y c h 1 o r i te (F i 9 s. 1 02, 1 03, 11 2) a n d i 11 ite ( Fi g. 113) in samp1es deeper than 2,600 m. Similar to the pro blem for the Ceara basin, it is not c1ear whether the i11ite and kaolinite formed at different depths or whether kao1irii te altered to illite with increasing buria1. Ch10rite pla te1ets are abundant in some samp1es and produce baff1es that serious1y reduce permeability(Figs. 156-158).
Most sandstones underwent a 1ater stage of d;~ solution in which sma11 amo~nts of p1agioclase diss~ved(Fig.
Potiguar Basin
The time of hydrocarbon entrapment with respect to the late-stage of secondary porosity development;s un certain. The presence of hydrocarbon at one time in most sam ples is inferred by the presence of scattered pyrite.
One of the deep samples (1-RNS-23, 32l9,9m) has undergone extensive argillation of feldspar and rock frag ments. All plagioclase and rock fragments and nearly all K feldspar have been altered to illite (Fig. 105). It is not certain whether the argillation occurred early during the de velopment of red beds or during deep burial. Because of the abundance of authigenic clay, much porosity was lost by com paction in this sandstone.
The best reservoir quality. in the Potiguar ba- ( sin exists in the onshore area because, (1) extensive seco~ dary porosity development there ando (2) there was less po rosity loss by compaction at shal10w depths. It is not clear at present why the onshore sandstones underwent more exten sive dissolution. Possib'le reasons include (1) more exten sive leaching of downward-moving meteoric water and, ( 2 ) i d e a 1 11 P 1 um b i n 9 s Y s tem 11 sue h t h a t u p w a r d - m o v i I) 9 c omp a c t i o n a 1 waters from the deeper basin were particularly abundant.
In the offshore part of the basin we find the same relatinnship, in general, as in the onshore basin: the best reservo;r sands are the coarser grained and better sor ted samples. These sandstones developed the best secondary porosity and did not lose all of it during subsequent events. Deep burial adversely affected sandstones by permitting mo re extensi ve compacti on and the growth of i 11 i te cement, both of which acted negatively upon permeability.
20.
Three major provinces of reservoir rocks are present in the study are. They are primari1y controlled by the initial detrital compcsition, texture and fluid compos~ tion. The framework composition plays a major role in the characterization of the diagenetic product. Figure 1 shows poro~ity zones defined from density logs and three diagene t i c p r o v i n c e s w h i c h som e h o w a r e r e 1 a te dto t h e b a sem e n t ro c k. The northernmost province (111) is characterized by poorly developed secondary porosity and low ptfrmeability (Figs. 39, 40). The southernmost province (I) has well developed se - condary porosity and better permeability (Figs. 43, 44 49, 50) finally in between we find a province (11) with interm~ diate characteristics (Fi .gs. 41, 42). Three diagenetic zo nes are temptive1y defined for Potiguar and Ceara basin(Fig. 118). Thepetrophysical and petrographic data support the zo nes defined by eletrical logs.
Zone I is characterized by high porosity and permeability and is chiefly cemented by carbonates and minor kaolinite. Reservoirs of this zone are composed mainly of the types Rl and R2. Zone 11 has high porosity but fair to good permeability, it is cemented by carbonate and kaolini te similar to Zone I. Reservoirs of this Zone are domina ted by the type R2. Zone 111 is characterized by somewhat 16wer porosity and permeability, it is chief1y cemented by carbonates and 2:1 clays (ch10rite, illite). In this zone k a o 1 i n i te no 1 o n 9 e r e x i s t s., r. e s e r v o i r s i n t h i s Z o n e a r e dom i nated by the type R3.
21.
We would like to acknowledge our collegues for their cooperation and cri ti cal comments during the various stages of the present project. Special thanks go to WAGNER M. CRUZ - DEPEX/LABOR for hi s support duri ng the sampling st~ ge. Thanks also go to col1egues from SECEPO/SENORTE-DIVIB and Paleontology-LABOR for providing valuable informations and materials.
ACKNOWLEDG~lENT
22.
BOLES, J.R. and S.G. FRANKS, 1979 - Clay diageneses in Wi1-cox Sandstones of southwest Texas: Implications of smectite diagenesis in sandstone cementation: Jour. Se dimentary Petrology, v. 49, p. 55-70. CHANG, H.K., TERRA, G. and MENEZES, S.)(, 1980 - Diagenese dos Reservat5rios Terrigenos da Foz do Amazonas at~ a Bacia Potiguar, Fase I, Relat5rio de Progresso-Julho/8U HOFFMAN, JANET and J.R. HOWER, 1979 - Clay mineral assemb1a t - ges as low grade metamorphic geothermometers: applic~ tion tothe thrust fau1t disturbed be1t of Montana: SEPM Spec. Publ. 26, p. 55-80.
McBRIDE, LF., 1977 - Sec.ondary porosity-importance in sands tone reservoirs in texas: Trans. Gu1f Coast Assoc . Geol. Soes., v. 27, p. 121-122.
REFERENCES CITED nc;, 1e - CROSS PLOT OF PERCENTAGE PLAGIOCLASE VERSUS K RICH f'ELDSPAR FO-R CASSIPORÉ, I. SANTANA, CEARA' ANO POTIGUAR aASINS , 7530 - 000 - 0658' 7530 - 000 - 06~ 7530 - 000 - 0658' 7530 - 000 - OIl:lB
·7530 - 000 - oe'.l
7&30 - 000 - 01l!l 1530 - 000 - 7530-000-0Il!l DR ss a O EE *_ EL
