BSE-119/
Mr. Walter K. Link Depex - Petrobrás Rio de Janeiro
I concur with Mr. Bender's recommendat' n t~la.t the southern part oí the basin be mapped in detail and that th~s work should be supplemen ed by a gravimetric survey. hough the report concludes that no possibilities exist íor the economic accumulations oí oil in the nortà ern or marginal portions oí the basin it will be necessary to carry on detail stratigraphic studies in these areas. A comparison oí the geologic map which accompanies Mr. Bendert~report with a cross-section recently - prepared by Mr. Blankennagel shows a major diííerence in structural - interpretation, e~pecially in the vicinity oí Euclides da Cunha. Mr . Blankennagel shows the Santa Brigida íormation cropping out along the western margin oí the basin whereas Mr . Bender is oí the opinion that I the overlying B member oí the Jeremoabo íor ation is exposed along this belt. The problem at the present time is the recognition oí stratigraphic units , thus the necessi y oí lithologic studies along the margins oí the basin .
Salvador, August 23 , 1958.
15.000 ·11 / In light of our better understanding of the Cretaceous stratigraphy of the Reconcavo and Sergipe basins, it was con sidered advisable to re-study and correlate the Cretaceous section of the Tucano basin in northern Bahia. Dr. Bender, transferred from Sergipe to the Reconcavo district in January, was assigned this task. In the above listed report, Bender presents the results of his field studies covering the periàd from February to May 1958. In addition, he ' h&s incorporated into the report the results of Dr. Freydanck's field survey of. the Tucano-C~p6 area which the latter worked from February through April 1958, and the geol.ogic data which had been documented by early inves tigators in the Tucano basin.
The report, unfortunately, adds little to our knowledge of the basin. The solution offered for the stratigraphic sequence and nomenclature, particularly along the northen D8rgin of the basin, le es much d. A more regional. approach utilizing and developing leads gleaned from pollen correlations and structural si.Ja111ari ties wi th the Reconcavo basin would have added considerably to the merit of the reporte With due justice to the author, it must be noted that a minimum of field and office t~e was spent on the project. A full year had been budgeted for the Tucano survey, however, Dr. Benderls contract terminated at the end of June at which time he re~ed to Ger.many.
STRA!IGRAPHY
1. Since he found no clear breu in li thology, Dr. Bender has discarded formational names and divisions establish ed for the Cretaceous by early workers He has divided the Cretaceous into an upper sandy phase, a middle shaly phase and a lower sandy phase. He has grouped these various phases into one formation - the Tucano formation.
Our views are not in accord with those of Bender on this subject. Although we concur that the stratigraphic sequence presented in early reports is often confusing, there are, nonetheless, very definite and distinct breaks in sedi mentation. This is best illustrated and indicated by:
August 6, 1958.
I P E· "
DI-177/
2. We are not entirely in accord w1th Bender's correla t10n of the various sandstones in the Jeremoábo and Santa Br1gida areas. We bel1eve for example, that Bender's "A" sandstone on Morro do Sta Cruz at Jeremo4bo 1s the probable equivalent of the sandstone r1dges in the Santa Brigida area and that this sand stone, northward, is transgressive onto baaement rock. That there is confusion in his correlation of the var10us sandstones 1s demonstrated on Bender's geologic map. For example, east and west of Jeremoábo sandstone scarps, some 2-1/2 km apart, are correlated as nA" sandstone. Taking into account the re latively steep dips, and the lack of faulting, it is a geometric impossibility to correlate these beds. Mr. W. T. OlHara has presented a more logical division of these sandstones. (DEPEX Report n 71 - Cross-section Jeremoábo to Brejinho).
3. Bender postulates the total thickness of sediments to be about 2,900 metera. An encouraging note is the increase of shale content in the Cretaceous section from north to south. The deepest part of the basin is thought to lie in the area south of an E-W line through the town of Tucano.
1. Sediments were deposited in a N-S striking graben about 250 km in length and 100 km in width. The N-S fault system has parallels in the Reconcavo and Sergipe-Alago~s basins. The major E-W fault1ng 1n the Jeremoábo and Santa Br1gida areas, however, 1s apparently unique to the Tucano bas1n.
2. Cr taceous sediments are affected by considerable block faulting and t1lting. We concur with Benderts statement that there 1s no evidence of compressional stress. As stated earlier in these comments, we believe the surface expression of anticlinal features due to draping over faults. a) The Santa Br1gida sandstone which is transgress1ve over red beds and granite rock to the north. b) The surface expression of ftant1cl1nes" wh1ch, explor1ng our knowledge of the Reconcavo bas1n, 1s probably due to draping adjacent to faul t1ng.' Hence, there are strong 1nd1cat1ons of early periods of faulting w1th subsequent erosion, similar to those of the Reconcavo. c) Pollen studies from the Piranhas and Tuc"ano w1ldcat wells point to the age equivalentsin the Tucano basin of the Ilhas and Candeias for mat10ns of the Reconcavo.
- 2 -
I P E - PETRÓLEO BRA§ILEIRO l!iio Ao
DI-177/
3. Supported by p011en data and geophyeical informa tion, a connection with the Reconcavo basin ie assumed to have exieted. Cretaceoue beds, at the end of lower Cretaceous time, are terrestrial deposite in the mapped area, hence, Bender assumes that the connection with the Reconcavo was probab1y eea1ed at that time.
ILLUSTHATIONS
1. Geo10gic i11ustratione submitted with the report inc1ude a 1:250,000 geo1ogic map (3 sheete), a 1:100,000 geo logic map (6 sheets), schematic crose-section Santa Brigida area, schematic cross-section "Macaco 1" we11 and a generalized stratigraphic co1umn. a) The geo10gic maps conform to DEPEX grid syetem and inc1ude geo1ogic data from ear1y maps by J. Brazi1 and H. Keller. The 1egend on these maps ie poorly presented, however, no modification 1e cons1dered necessary at this time. The writer be1ieves that the stratigraphic sequence must be rev1ewed and proper revisions made on the ge010g1c map prior to final presentati on. b) The cross-sections and co1umnar sections ehould have been c010red prior to submittal. c) Addit1Qnal i1lustrations which m1ght have been submitted with the report 1nc1ude:
ii) E-W cross-section across the basin. PETROLEUM POSSIBILITIES
1. During an ear1y reeonnaissanee to the Tucano basin in 1956, Meesrs. Mora1es, S. Oliveira and the writer searched in vain for an oi1 seepage reported by Mr. Brazi1, in the Santa Brigida area. Dr. Bender wae s1m11ar1y unsuccessful after a three day search despite tha fact that he had the same guide who had accompanied Brazil.
2. The sedimentary section, where exposed, is reportedly poor in organic matter. Bender euggeste that eource rocks may be preeent in the deeper, south central basin area. About 70% of the exposed eection consists of porous and permeable eand stones.
i) Lithologic 10gs of Piranhas and Macaco wells indicating zones of po11en correlation.
ii) E-W cross-section across the basin.
- 3 -
I P E - The report author considers the marginal and northern part of the basin unpromising. He is more optimistic about the oil possibilities in the south central area , and , suggests a detailed geologic survey of the area south of late 112 40 to tie in with the northern Reconcavo. This is in line with the original program as budgeted for 1958.
Sino e the area is largely masked by Tertiary sediments , the author further recommends that a gravity survey be conducted over the same area.
RIm/Ir File: Report n 922
Richard K. Blankennagel
I P E · JUNE 30, 1958 BY
F. BENDER
ABSTRACT • • • • • . . .. . • • • • • • • • • • page 1 • • • • INTRODUCTION . .; • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • 3 • • • • GEOGRAPRY • • • • • • • • • • · . . • • • • • • 6 • • GElIERALIZED STRATIGRAPHIC COLUMN • • • • • • • 7 • • • • STRA7IGRAPBY • • • • • • • • • • • · . . . • • • • • • 8 aeneralized Stratigraphy Summary • • • • • • • • 9 12 Tucano Forméltion •• • • • • • • • • • • • • • • Marlzal Formation... • • • • • · . . . .. • • • • 15 16 Cicero Dantas Formation. • • • • • • • • • • • • ., . . • •• GEOLOGIC STRUCTURE » -18 • • • • • • • » • • • Regional Structure • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • 1.8 Local Structurea • • • • • • • • • • • · . • • • 19 GEOLOGIC RISTO RY • • • · .. . .. . . . . . . . . . . . 22 · . • • • PETROLEUM INDICATIONS •• • • • • • • • • 23 PETROLBUH POSgIBILITIES. • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • 24 CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMENDATIONS • • • • • • • • • • • • 25 BIBLIOGRAPBY • • • • • • • · . ., . . . • • • • • • • • 26 .. . .. • • • • • 27 APPENDIX . . . . • • • • • • • • • • • •
T A B L E O F C O N T E N T S.
Reconna1 sancc field ork from F bruary to the end of ! y, 1958. and a compilation of data fro previouo invcstigations result-ed in the follo~ing goologic concept of the Tucano B s n: D ing Cret c ous and Tertiary t e, a. graben-like, north - south striking depreasion existed north of the Reconcavo B oin. Tbia graben ia about 250 km long , and 100 km ide.
A monotonou series of clastics ere transported into the preaaion bil terreotric-fluviatile, eolian, lacustrine, and fine claatie sedijl~ ater enviro e t prevail d. Th shaly - ith a subordin te lime content ~ enta of brackisb .ater origin, increase to ardo the aouth - central part of the baoin.
Depoeition upon tbe subsi ding basecent eomplex was initia! d by about 200 ma of generally coaroe sandstonos.
The subsequ nt deposition of up to 1800 ma of finer claatics and ahales points to a further aubsiding basin ith mino r oseillationa of aubmergence and emargence. Periodically during thio time, a connection exi.oted with the -~econeavo hich alle :'lcd the brackish embayment atora to transgress ao far north ao the northern Tucano Basin ..
Dominantly coarse clastic deposito of a thickness of about 300 ma torminate the Crctaceous oedimentary cycle.
A period of non-deposition followad, hen block faulting and tilting took place chiefly along atrikes of N20 , N-S, 120 to 30E, nd East-st . Thcre are no observ tions pointing to co pres-sion 1 forceo in the basin.
Upon thc tectonically affected ediments, the generally flat lyAng I arizal-aandstonea of terrostric-fluviatile, in part colian ere depooited . Theoe clastics of supposedly lo er tertiary re up to 200 ms thick.
ABSTR f, CT
A sU-abt rcj1iaVeMtion o'E teetonie CQ-VC onte tllonc t • ol.d lines oi C~1nec6 oecurred b~toro tbe ter.restrio.fluv1at1~ . custrillG elastic ot tbe Cieel'O Tb 1 tter 10 thiCfk. out A ~sit1vabl. up11lt, loUowe4 'b7 penep}. tio d aligbt., opirogenical.l.1 Soutbeoot tl1tinS .t T2'á at~ th. <Sapo 1tio • in the Tucano Ba.D. .. jor norc. faults of tbesq di.r&ct_o O pnJ'tl1' t . 11'1 te tbe taulte. 4 b!n(J; b in Q.GaiD&t th-e 00s ellt eomplez ia t G st. 1D tho North. d u the
,nu:ik1.ns hoYnt blooko uu4 Cr: ''O» ' " ,traqu&ntly t11.u'\1 up to 15 • No pot~l 1ndlcctiona avo b en found in tbe booin ar • poor in QIl7 or roc' • Blook t nul t1ns and til tina to &till f'arthet" 1,n\l'oot1cat1ons 1t ia tI the "" ..... ~...... 1TItlft' thê follo1rl oCGerlratiOJl&. sll y portion 0.1 the Cret c«nao s d 1. T d to ard $Outblrnrd the 1Imcr baain lU" -_ ; ther-etore. bottet' woaibi11t1o-o QQJl bo-expe.cte4 tOl" aoureo ~ék. Ild to~ botéor ~over rocko.
2. The enrlronment of sedlmentation in th$' eouth~n central Tucano and in t h~Reconc'avo &&111 ia siJililar .. SinQe th1s eny1ronment hae led to 011 generating conditions in the Reconcavo, it might have done so in the southernparts of the Tucano Basin as Vio11 ..
To invostigate these pose1bi1ities, a , geologic , s.ufac-e party abould gather more data along the southern margin ot th~ basin. S1ncethe olltcrop eondi tions are poor in tM s area, II g1"av1 t,. meter ,aurvey 16 recommended in the aouthorn central Tucano Basin, wh1ch ties in the known outcrop beita. Based on the resulta of thia surve~ and at a structurally suitab1e locat1oD. a etratigraphie test _e11 ehauld be drilled to the basement.
The purpose of this :t"eport 16 to summarize tbe fieldwork accomp11sh ed by TG-9 from Februar,. to May, 1958, and to compile the gco1ogic data obtained b,. previous investigations in the Tucano Basin. From the compilat1oll and the nC\TI data available; an attempt ia mada to formu1.a.te a coneeption af stratigraph)" and structure of' the basin as a who~e. in the South, Serr~nba - Inhambupe; Tobias Barreto - a point appr. 20 km East ~f Jeremoabo; in tbe East, in the ~Torth, a po1nt appr.20 km South of Paulo Afonso-Canudos; Euclid-es da Cunha ~ Araçi. In the West, c These towna circumacribe tlle area occupied b;y Cret·aceous and ;younger, sedimentary rocks. Tbe area oontains about 27 000 aguare kilometers.
Reconnaissance fieldwork bl TG-9 has beeo done in the northern part of the bnsin, and a10ng lts eatern margin from Canudos to Euclides da Cunha (F;BENDER). from there towards Tucano-Araçi, and along tbe southwest margin (G.FREYDANCK; reI. accamp. map 1:250 000).
The reoaining area nas boeo transveraed by jeep in order. \ to get a general idea of topography and geology. The geologic in-formation app."ring on t he maps 01' th'o r 'emaining area have been
1 N T R O D U C T I O N
PETRÓT.EO BRA§ILEiRO S. Ao added irom previous work of H.KELLER Bn.d J.BRAZIL (1946-41). Since the ext.ensive arca \tas be covered in less than 4 months, th-e natur! or the surveX "as a fast reconnaisaance. A base camp with - " C ipo, otherwise party offiee and supplies WBa estab1isbed in fI,. h camps .ere used whel"e opera tions demanded. As to the method pf nrk: 'i'be chosen traverses _erefirst wo:rked by the geologiat, the station number s were painted on t he ro.cka. The topographic survey -.as done in 1.1:20 000 and 1:50 000 Gca1e with plane table and alidado. The surve, .as later re«uced to 1:100 000 sca1e in order to be tranaterred luto the exis-ting topographlc base mapa. ~e latter were pantogPaphed from Ir 250 000 mapa of the Departamento Nacional de Geographia. Thesa mapa arlÇ ineorreet as to distances and details, but might serve for reconnáiss anee work. The perponnel of TG-9 eonsiated of: F. Bender, party chief, G.Freydanck. geologist (February - Apr.!l) ., Eraani Lopes Filho, asaistant. Boaventura Couto Pinto, topographer, Fernando Carvalho, topographer, 3 drlves and 4 workmen. Transport ere 3 jeeps and 1 pickup. Previous investigaticns in the Tu.cano· Basin ha v'e been aeeomplisbed by Conselho Nae1.onal de Petroleo, in the years 1944-50 ..
As to the method pf nrk: 'i'be chosen traverses _erefirst wo:rked by the geologiat, the station number s were painted on t he ro.cka. The topographic survey -.as done in 1.1:20 000 and 1:50 000 Gca1e with plane table and alidado. The surve, .as later re«uced to 1:100 000 sca1e in order to be tranaterred luto the exis-ting topographlc base mapa. ~e latter were pantogPaphed from Ir 250 000 mapa of the Departamento Nacional de Geographia. Thesa mapa arlÇ ineorreet as to distances and details, but might serve for reconnáiss anee work.
J.I.BRA ZIL (1946/47) completed the first geologic reconnaissance map of t he basin, and suggested a strat igraphic subdivision. B.P.KELLER (1948/49) worked on s ome structural problema near Tucano, and in the area of Itapicurú-ollnd.1na.
W.T.O' GARA (1948/49) carried out structural studies along the Rfo Vasa Barris i n the northern part of t he basin, and did general reconnaiasance fieldwork .
Silvio VUa Guedes (19'+8) at.udied some "etructuree East of Jeremoabo.
A complete liat oí previoua reporte and maps ia compiled in the bibliograph1.
Some Gcatter~d areas of the baain have been airpbotograph-d. 1948, by Cruzeiro do Sul. Since the available copies are poor in contrast and faded they have been of no great valu8; however, Gome of the photogral'hs may be still useful for more detailed studtes.
A rcfraction &&1smic aurv61 has ~een carried by a few lines iA the southern baain area, in the year 1945. The depth of penetration, and the approximate depth of the basement ia given at a fell locations on a map of 1:500 000 seale. There exista alao a map presenting Q number or strikea and dip. for about )0 km along tbe principal roada trom Nova Soure to arda Southwest and Southeaat. Tbis map is apparently derived frem the same survey (Oct.19~5).
drilled b,. C.N.P.t
Hacaco 1, a pr.18 f Tucano, spudded in Apri1 19. 1948, tias comp1eted Jan. 17, 1949. at a total d.epth or 1861.4 ma, ao a uater _el1 (m~neral vater, +380 C), ati11 in non-metamorphic oediment ry ocks. ---=:......-::::::---. (J ~ , Piranhas 1, appr .. 27 km st f Jeremoabo, spudded in Oct.19.1949 was compl-eted Ju1y 1. 195&, at a total depth of 1526".4 ms, as dry ho1e, in non-metamorphic sedimentary rocks.
In 1944. tVlO sballow, atratigrapbic test vella were dri11ed 'by C.N.P. near CipÓ, another one near Nova Sourel Ciat-l-Ba TD 433.4 IDS, C1st-2~Ba, TD 315,5 ma; So-l-Ba TD 641,6 Jlm. According to A. W{ND-RLEY (C.N.P.Re1ator10 1944), ,u 'J C ist .. 1-Ba and Cist ... 2-Ba ere abandoned in t!e Bendo For ation which ia apparcntly equivalent1y nth J.BRAZIL's Uarizal Formation. " " , So-l-Ba penetrated th~ Bendo fl1 ith an appr.30 ma thick b sal conglomerate at about 195 ma, and entered more consolidated sand&tones below. (Pro'bably the upper sandy phase of the Tucano n~). Cist-2-Ba bit a Gu1phur therme of a temp.rature of 34cC, wbich produeed 150 000 liters/hour.
Aceess to the Tucaao Bas1n ia by t$'deral. highway 12 (dirt and graveI roada) from Sa~vado~ via C1pó-Ctcero Dantas-Jeremoobo, and by federal h1ghl'l&Y 1.3 fl'om Fei.ra Santana via Euclides da Cunha to Canudos. Both roada o.rejoined together by the East-West running federal. higbway . 27" trom J~remoabo to Canudos t in tbe nor-thern part of the baein. Away from these ronda. the ac ce-ssib11it,. 1& difticult du& to the usual 1,,. dense eac-tua-bush vegetation (Caatinga) t particularl,., north of the federal btghway 27# The Q.l1ma~e ia tropi4al. .. semiarid. with oeeasional. rEdnfall dur-ing April to S.eptem-ber .. Most or the b-nein ia covered wi th a monotonouscactus and 'bush vegeta_ ti91l.- witheome high tl"litee and forests a lo.ng tM s--ivers anã major 6td~ riachos. 'i G .,. L1...,in8 conditions are fair in ·1po,. in a11 éther t ,owns and viJ.J.age~ primitive,. the laek ot clean water beingtbe main handieap. Topographicall.x. tho baoin nta7 be separat.ed 1nto 4 llnitst 1. The ete:epl3" dissected Jll&aas and th~i.r remains in the vicinity of C1cero .mtaa, w1th altitudes up to 800 ma above se-a. l~V"el. 'l'bey apparently represent the remains af a peneplaned area .hicÁ ie morphologically above the taboleiros. 2 .. The extensiva tabole1.ros witb altitudes: up to 550 ma abCtve soa level, wh1ch cover about 3/4 of the total baaia. and mask the central and 50utbern hasin area entirely. Towarda West and along the major eroalan fronte tbo taboleiroa ~ermiDate in stoep esea rpments of a vertical altitude of UI' to 70 me .. 3 .. The gentll' J"ol11ng MIl c'ountry ith occaai.onal sandst-ones cliffs along major drainages. \'11th al,titudea gene.rally be101l 500 lile. It ocC'upieo the, marginal basin areas. where Cret-aeeous sandstonits and shalea oc--eur. 4. 'rM steep mesa M .. l1s, and the reund hi1l eo-untry, formed by the ditterent r()cks oi thebordering basement eomplex,with occG.aional. remaina 01 sandstone escarpments.
G E O G R A P B Y
- 6 ...
General The sedimente in tbe Tucano ~1n .ere deposited in a continental. graben like depression. wbile terrestric fluvlat~1e. lacustri ne. and brackish .ater environment prevailed.
The brackish wator environment ia apparent1y leGa pro-nOWlced in the North. than it ia in the central, and the South of the basill~ whoro a connection witb the Reeoncavo ia postu1ated .
Froa Gurface dnta obtained in the northern and estern marginal arc~s, a total thicknesa of about 2 900 me of unm'etamor-phiz.ed rockaia believed to overly the baaement comp1ex. Due to lack of expoeurest no thicmees data are available in the inner and southern basin area. .
The sedioenta.ry roeks expoaed in the northern third of the baain are composed Gf about 80 % of broWJl., red, and grey whitish. frequently caol1nic-arkoaic sandstones, and of about 20 % of marooD, vi01ettish-red, purp1e, and aubordina te greygreenish and grey abales. To.arda the South, and along the western margin, the aandstone/ehale ratio 18 about 60:40. The shale content probab1y still increases in the inner and aouthern basin .hich ia entirely masked under Tertiary, fla t lying claatica. About 5 % of the known, ehal,. section ia calcareouo.
Rap1d lateral facies changes trom co ar se to tine-.clastics, , and 1enticular1ty are trequen througbout the sect10n hich la characterizod by deposita of dom1nantly continental env1roncent. The shal7 s action wbich apparently repreaenta the main portion of the brackieh .ater perioda ia more continuous. though, as seen trem the correla tioll posaibili ty between the \'1el1a l.facaco 1 (Tucano) t and Piranhas 1 (Jeremoabo) over a distanee ot about 110 km.
S T R A T I G R A P H Y
- 8 -
Yel,brn,red,greYfmottl.ss; th1c bedded,croscb,mass; poorly 50 t poorly solid; cont.var1ing dmOW of caoline and arg.matt r; r qu~nt interbeds of varicolo.ed silt5t, fine-ss, grave]s d co lomerates .. discont1nuou~, and lenwing la1-ers ~f m~~s1vel ar thickb~dd d x-beaded, aroi 1. ~r. • viol, purple,tlélroo,u.,greY shales alternat'ng with red and brn arg. S5 , s11tstones, and a Yellow, ~r~i11 15 beds.
The variou,p attempts for strat igraphic subdivisions as .mude by pravioue s ,tuden ta have been found valuable for the tJ'Pe localíties concerned o!Íly. From the avarall field\York, no clear break in li't;.holoQ, or an,. other cri terium M .a been found w1 thin J the ereta'ceous seetion .bieh would justif;y a aubdirla1oD. into tOL ma~ions being correct for ' the entire bas1n.
There ls, bowever, a phase of dominantl;y sandy depoaition in the upper part of the Cretaeeous sequence, a dominant11 abaly t middle portion, and a lower, again: dominantly sand,. phase. Slnoe these unit,s are not clearly defined as to their top and base, they are not conaidered as yet to represent dif'forent f'orma tions. They might ,ba mappab1e .. thougb, by detailed geologic fieldwork. Aa attempt haa been Illade to map the upper, aandy portlon, anel the abaly aequenee, i.n the n-orthern part of the baain.
River deposita, and redepoaited clastics from the Cicero Dantas - and :fl'om the Mar1zal FM ••• appr. 50ms Uplift - SGutheast-Tilting - Peneplenation CICEBO DAnTAS FORMATION yell-brn, red, grey1sb, mottl. SS, poorly solid., m,ed.ium-gra1ned-well sortedt-01" coarse grai.ned-poorly sorted. Massiv8, thickbedded, crossbedded. Vary1ng content of Kao11nic and ~rg111. matter. Interbeds of m(lroOD, 1"ed, grey. purple oh, siltst., argill. fine-ss. gravels, and conglomerates-.. The fine-clastics are f1"equently micaceous •• appr. 40ams Sllght Faulting and Tilting
LOVIEB TERTI ARY ?
HARI ZAL FO~lA'l' ION .,.e11., brnt red burf, massivc ... thickbedded as. Generall,. . In zones coarse, pebby, fine-grai~ d't argill .. , 80ft. conglox:1eratic,x-bedded . Steep wall, castellated, OI' pinnaeled forma by weathering. Baeal conglomerate af subrd-well roundeu bouldera of varioU$ baaemen t a.n~ non-metamol"phic rocks ....... appr. 200 l'.IlS Angular Unconformity Due To Blockfaulting And Tilting
CRETACEoUS
TUCANO FORMATION
A. In the l'1ôrtbern third of the basin. I 6 ~ Upper Portion. includea Jeremoabo FM, Member A grey ~d brn, maaaive-thickbedded-x-bedded sandstone. Medium-coarse grained, fairl;y hard" Kaolinic and ferru ... gUi. in soltes. Contains frequently sCllttered pebb1es and graveI lenses. Subord. wel1 stratit. argill. tin'e-ss, particularly, towards base ••••••••••• appr. 150 ma Jeremoabo FM, Hember B , M1ddle Portion. inoludes u " n ti Curitiba ni of n . " Santa Brigida. .FM , and J.BRAZIL .. alte:rn.ating 2"'ed, brn,violet-p-trple,grey. argil.l.fine-ss, olltstones, silt,. sh, and ahales, 1'1el 1 stratified,flasgy. Interbeds ot lenticu1ar.massivc,argil1.,Kaolinic ss with ferrug .. concretions and marks af sub-aquatic sliding •• 1500-17oOms Loue:r Portion'c includes "Santa Brigida Ff·f'.. and the n fI lower part of J .BRAZIL's Curitiba FM • grey and yellow, massive, or obscure1,. bedded, hard ss, medium to COêU"se gl'ained; mostly poorl,. sorted, conglomeratic in zones. particu1arly at base • . Frequently silicified, appr. 100 ma locally ferruginoous ......................... .
_10 ..
'u . .. Serra Velha FM • UMa%" Porticm, bcludes J .. BRAZIL·s l'4af3sive to stl"atitied, darkre8 and brown fin.e-ss, and coarser, brown .. in plaees pebbl3' ss;subordinate grey, 300 ma purple. !!1aroon~ and gr.eygre-eniah abales ...... appr. V " .. .. 1:'1\"#" iddle or~l()Jl..incllldas the Tucano Fl~ t the Poço arde 1: I."~ It M P .. u and tho Rio Vermelho »t oi' J .. BRAZIL . 1nterbedded red., brovm. buri, purple. w-ell strat1.fied ss, violettish. purple, maroon, grey, and greygreeldsb sh, varieolored micaceoUB ailtst ones, yellow, argillaceous t 01" silty, tbin limestone bede, discontinuous, lensing, massive to thi.ckbedded. x-batided argill. as ••• 1500 - 1800 (1) ma xe.er~ortion,. the 10we1",. sandy phase as observed in the n-orthern third of the ba1311'1 has not been as-certained in the touth.
Angular-trneonf'o-rmity PJmMIAlf? t SILURIAN? , AlW OLDER. BASEl-lENT COl.u>LEX Perlldan (1) "Loreto m" oi J.BRAZIL = Eitancia Sandstone; hard. partI,. s11icifiri. purr le and red 8S; bordara tbe basiD partly in the East. S11urian C?) " ., tf Jua-Conglomerate of J.BRAZIL; metamorphi.zed t hard eonglomerate of sma11, angular sehist-fragrnents, and subrd cttz ... pebbl.es. bQrders parta of the basin in the North-east. Silurian ('I) ulates,greywa.ckes, metamorphic limestonee; tbe7 bordar great parta o f the basin in the Nortbl'lest and in the Wa·st. Granites, aplitee, granite-gneiss; isolated occurrences in the North and in the West of the basia.
. 1 - Gel1eral: '1'ha narre Tucano Formation was o'riginal.ly used by: J.BRAZIL (1947) to de-signate the :Lntorbedded sandst.ones, silt 'stonest and ahales 1'10801" Tucano... 'l'he writerbelieves,. that the other formation names ae eetablishe4 by J • BRASIL (a.na Velha FM t Poç'o Verde Fl4:, Rio Vermelho FM~ Sta B-ri.gida m., Curitiba FM) d·esignate fa.cies equivalent d.posits of the Tucano n·!. No clear brenk. in litho-lo-sy., 01" a'llY otbe-l" cri teM.Udl nas )let been faund to juetify a subdi. d.àion of the Cretaceoue déPosi te whien WQuld bl! correet for tlle whole area.. In this roport, the namoTucano Format1i)u ie therefore UBed for alI Cretaceous sedimente in the basin.
A phaso ar dominant17 sandy deposition, a ahaly phase, and another eandy phase af deposi.tion atthe base have b~n traced throuK out the greater part of tbe basin. Sinee these phaaes are not e~ea1"lJ' deflned as to tbeir t.cp and base contacts, they are not considered to repr~Gent different format1ons.
The tzpe section for the upper sandy phase ia the eandstone above the interbedded ahales and siltstones o.n tbe Serra Santa Cruz. at Je~emoabo. The shaly phase is b.est exp.osed along tha higrlay Tucano Rio Vermelho. The t ype seetion for the lQwer sandy phase ia the sand. atana ridge South of Santa Brigida, which directly r~ate upon th~ basement l"oeks.
tithology; 2 - to eoarae grained~ fair17 hard f Kaolinic and ferr.Q gine.ousi contains frequent scattered pebblos. g~avel lenses and conglomerates. interbedded, red, br1'l-t bufi, VI.ell a'tratif. at"gU1. se and vo.ricolore.d ailtstonea, ahales, anã subordinute argill. lim~st. Diseontinuous &nU 1ens ing 1ayers of mass., thiekb., x-bedded argill.,Sa; vio1. t purple, maroon, grey sbales, altarnating with red and brown argill. ailtatones, and a few, argi11. limost-one beda.
C. Sandy Pbase I
:5 - Thiclmes8 and Areal Extent, Tbe tbiekDeas of the dominantly sandy, upper pol'tion of the Tucano Formation ia about 300 ma., The more shaly seetion mensures 1500 - 1800 ma according to data obtain~ ed in the v/estern outerop bel t. These figures are not very reliable becaase normal tau! ting occura in· t he section wi th unltnowu displace m.ent. The lQwer sandy: phase ia about 200 ms tbick.
The Tucano FM le exposed along a 25 to 35 1m wid-e bel t al~ng the western margin of the basin, in the valley of thé Rio Vasa Barris õetween Cancbé and Jeremoabo, in th~ area Jeremoabo to Santa Brigida, and in iso1ated occurrences along the eastern margin. 4 ~ Stratigraphie Relationahips: The top oi the Tucano n~. .all marked by an angular unconformitYf ia overlain by the Marizal FM. There ia a great a1mil~ity, however. blittueen the upper , sandy phase of thc Tucano Fr.f, and the Mariza! FM. If tha angular unconformit.l ia not expo3ed. the distinction of both formatlona ia diffieult.
The base p! the Tucano FM t10wer aandy phase, "Sta Bri gida m") resta, directly OQ: the cl"ystal1ine basement eOlllplex with llear base conglomeratic sandstones, and frequently si1icified aan-dstones. 5. - Facioo' There ia a general change af fac1es trom coarser to fineI' clastics going southwards trom theRio Vasa Barris vallvy. Calcru;-eous abales and al"gillaceous li.mestone interbeda appear South o! a 1ine conneeting Massacará ~ith Pombal . whitiah grey; Y811,- brn 8S; thickbedde-d, x-bedded; in general ~oar.ae to medium grainedl poor17 sorted; usual1y hard, oftell ferrugineous, and in $ones ailic1fied; containa freq.scattered pebbles.
- 13 ...
6 "-,,. Age anel PaJ.eontology: On the preaence of Eotheria. Oetraeods t S1'!lal1 f'ish teeth. sc:laee and bones (J.BRAZIL.l941), c-rocodile teeth and bones (G;FREWDAUCK.1958) .. and on the preaonce of pollen and hystl"ichoepherids equivalent to tho.ee f'ound in the. Ilhas and Candeias FK o~ the Reconcayo (R. MfiLLER ). the Tucano ~orma-tion has been &saigned a Cretaceous age. S11!.cif1ed .ood ia 10-eally abundant in the dominantly sandl portions of' the formation •
., - Origin: The interbedded sandy t abal,. t subor-dinate la,. deposition ith ti pocr, but loeally abunàant fauna of Esthp.t'ia, Ostracoda, sma11 pelecypods and gastropods 9 tbe presance of cro-codile anel fish rema.i ns, and the pres-ence of' pl.a.nt remains point to periodically changing. shall.o., bracldeh water, anel freah V/ater eonditiona. The residual type re-d abale, and the occurrenee of windkanters (taeeted pebbles) in what appears to be eolian aands tone indicate intermittant d7Y periods.
8 - Oil and Ga.s Poasibilities: li great number or porous ano permeable sandstone zonas occur throughout the Tucano Formation, which may aet as reservoir rocks under favourable trapping eon-ditions_ The 1ncrease i n shal1 del'OGition towards the South ma,. provide sufficient covar rocks and source 1"Ocks in the soutbern, central basio parta. 9 - Hineralogy: No mineral.ogic studies have been done.
Marizal Formation 
~he name is here restricted to tbo claslfcs above th. angular uneOIl:to~ty rith the Tucano Formation~ and 'below the Cicero Dantas Format1on.
'l'he txpe }.oeation ia the Serro. do Mariz.al, about 15Km Eaot o f Tucano.
'lhe Marizal n.t consista of gonera11y r:1ne-grairied. 2 - Lithology: 80ft, yellow. red, brown or butt, argil.1aceous sandstonea. lt ia ma13131v~t or thickbedded, and frequênt17 croesbeddcd. "Po,ckets, lenses and laycrs of pebbles. and conglomerates are common. It weathers in characteristleal, castel:lated ar p1nnacled forme. The base of the formation ia formed by a 10 to 30 ma thick conglamerate of subround ed boulders of varlouo basement rocks (Southeast of .Tuoanolt. and subordina to non-metamo:rphie roeks (East of Poço Verde) •
., - Tbickness and Areal Extent: A thi-ckness 'Of about 200 me ia câlculated ifone assumes that the top cf the extensive . tabole1roa represente also the top of the Marlz.al FM.. 1'ho Mar1zal FM blankete about 2.;, of the basin a~ea., and masks the central and southern . parta completel,..
4 - Stratigraphic Rela tionshlps: The Marizal ~t underlios the Cicero Dantas ni. the conta.ct haa not been observed directly. lt :Ls ãrewn alo-ug the foot of the hills w111eh are morphologicall,. 'lhe base con taet 1 th the Tucano loca ted above the taboleiros. Formatioh ie marked 01 ao angular uneonformitYt nnd by n s11ght change cf litb<üogy to generall,. more eonsolidated sand.stones below. .5 .. Faciost No cha ngea 'of the clastic fae1es bave boen nQted.
PETRÓLEO BUASILEXUO S. Ao
6 - Ab~ and PalecntoloCT' J.B~~Z~L (1947) has asoigned a Teztlary age to the Marizal ~{. apparently on tbe observation that the generally tlat ly1ng torm~tion ~verlie8 tbe Cretaeeous Tucano Formation .ith anangular unconformit,.. 'l'hero 1a no foasil eTidenee 7et for a defiDitiv~ age determination of this formation.
The Marizal Fõrmation was deposited in a ahalIo. basin 7 - OriginJ when terrestrieal, fluviat11e, laeustrine. and eolian environments prevailed. No oboervations have beea made po1nting to the existence of any brackish .ater a~diment in the Harizal FM. 8 - Oil and Gas Poss1b11itiesI Oil and gas poasib1l1tieaare not expe.eted in the Narizal Ff.{, hecause neitber trapping conditions nor any covar rõcks exist in both. the Mnrizal, and tbe overlyine C1eero Dantas Formation. 9 - Mineralogyl No mineralogy studies have yet beea done. 10 - C rrelationa 11 - Clastic Ratio: 100 % clasties 12 - Bibliography: J.BRAZIL(194?). Cie~r9 Dantas Formation. 1 - General; 'l'be format1on was named in 1947 s by J .BBAZ!L; it iíi re-defined in this report.
Tbe type section runs along the road fr(l1!1 CiceI'O Dantas to Monte Alegre.
2 - Lithology~ The Cicero Dantas FM ia charaeterized by its bright colored. poorl,. solidifie-d, and in general poorly sorted clastics. Ye1low, brown, red and greyish sandBtonea r~ing from massive, s-bedded to ·.ell stratif1e-d. alternate .ith maroon, red. grey, and purple shales micaceous siltstones, and argillacQous fine-sandstones. Lenses and layero of eong10~erates are trequent. Several ehert horizons oecur in the upper portion of the formatione 3 - Th1ekneas and Areas E;tent: Th1ekness data of the Cicero Dantas FM -lre questlonable sinee 1ts base cont "' et 1a nO"t c1eerly defined by a li-
~ thologic break. From the morpbology (from the top of the l!arizal pene plain 9 the highest altitude in the basin) a thickness of about 400 ma ia assumed.
PETRÓ:r .. EO BUASILEIRO S. A.
The for11'lation oecupies the are& a'round, mui Nortb_est of Cicero Dantas f/hlch i.s lnOl"phologl.ea11y above thetabolelros. 4 - Stratigraphic Relationsbips: The Cícero Dantas FM ia the youngest extensive dopoGition in the Tucano Basin. It lo underlaln by tbe litholo.s1cally slmilar~ though generally somewbat finer grained and better sorted Marizal Fi". Tbe eontact has notbeen observed in exposures.
5 - FaciesJ 'lhe essellt1a11,. elaatic tacue becomes coarser. and more conglo~atic northward trem Cicoro Dantas. 6 - Age anti Pa1eontolog;TJ Ou the presence of a traah water fauna of emall 11sb remains and cruataeea t anti Gome plant remains f'ouncl 5 Km ffbeyondlt Cícero llantas (no alear descr1.ptio.n of the locality) ' L.I.PRICE (1940) se·ems to have attributed the Clcero Dantas FM to t he Cretaceoue.
Duo to its charactor as the youngost depos1t in the basin, and bocause it ia not tecton1cally attect~d, J.BRAZIL (1941) asoigned a Tertiary uge to tb1e tormatlon. B.cause it ia poorly co..'lsOlic1ated, alwaya nn.t lyillS. and together with th. un-er l.,.!ng J1ar1.zal FM separa! ed trom t r.e ~ucano ~t below by an angular unconformlty, this designa-tion aeems justifiec.
7 - Origins The Ci.cero Dantas Formation \fas d.posited in a shal.l ... baai nunder terrest..-ic t fluvlatile .. and laeustrine condi t'Íone. 8 - Oi1 and Gas Poss1.bi1itiest Because it ia the younge,? t deposlt in the basin. and heoause i.t is essenti.!Ü~7 'clastlc throughout the: section, no o~ or gas possibillties are expected in the Ci.cero Dantas Format1on. 9 .. Mineralogy= No rnineralogic atudie:s ha.vc y~t. beel1 OEU"r-!,:ee out. 10 - Corre~ntionJ Aeeording to 'the l!t'hologic eim.11arlty..~ ~ similar \\ d~positioDal environment-... the C1cero Dantas FH might be time ~qu1valent .\ ~ \ and cOZ'relate v1tll the Barreiras FM in the Reeoncavo. \ , \. 11 ·-Clast1c Ratiot 100% claetic$.. \ \ \ \ 12 - B1b1iography: DE OLIVDI!M., A.I.(1943); J" BRAZIL (1947) l' \ \- Regional Structure.
The basin sediments vere depoaited in a Nortb-South s t rlking graben of about 250 km in length, and about 100 km in width.
The depth of this trough apparently lncreasee trom North to z South. he deepest parta are thDught to occup,. t ! e area betwe,en an Eaot .. n West line throught Tucano, and the high of denser rocks as indica ted by selsmic data trom Inhambupe to Esplanada. l' he dominant directions of t he raul t contacts with the basement complex are NIO to 20."1,an": N20 to 30E. Due to offsets along trana-verse, more ar lesa East West fren ding taults. tbe general North-South direction of the graben remains pres erved.
'1'heae regional tectonic directions are present i n the Reconcavo Basin. toa. They could not be directly connected because of the aepara ting Inhambupe-Esplanada High. Recent refraction se·ismic Burveys between Alagoinhas and Ouriçlngaa ( E S 12, June 1958) point to a North Soutb graben. whicb ia about 35 km "ide and connects the Reeoncavo nth the Tucano Basin _est of the Inhambupe-Esplannda High.
The western crya,alline contact of the Tucano Basin bet een Euclides da Cunha and west of Tucano has the chara cter of a hinge (scissor-) fault with au increase of the displ&:cement towards South. 'l'he appar~nt shallower northern part of tbe basin ia terminated b,. East-West running faults, or by normal overlap ot Cr~taceoU8 clasties upon tne basement complex. as onthe road fl"Om Jeremoabo to Paulo Afonao.
Due to poor outcrop cond1tions, the eastern fault contàct with the crystalline rocks eould be only conf1rmed 10cal1y.
For the same reaaon, the character of the structure ia still unknown whi ch terminatea t he basin in the Soutb against the Inbambupe-Esplanada. High.
GEO L O GIC S 'l' RU CTU RE
... 18 -
PETROBRÁS PETRÓJ_EO BRA§ILEIRO s. A.
The Cl"etaeeoue sedimente ia t he bll.sin are affected b,. eODsidérable block faulting and tilting. chiefl,. along the sarna directioJ18 as the e;rystalline contaets: NlO-20W" N20-30E. and Eaat-West. ilhere are no observations as to the existence of compress1onal toreesresulting in anticlines, to the contrary, alltectonic phenomena Cân be explained by the exi stence of tenaional forc es in the basin.
Dips of 10-200 are common in the Tucano Formation. The Mariza1 Ff.1 le generall,. fiat lying but shoVls mode-rate dips and fraeturing in the marginal arens.
No dir a have been observed in the Cicero Dantas Formation. Local Stl"ucture.s
1. The San •• Brígida Graben.
From the road trom Jeremoabo to Paulo Ato,uso whieh paral-lela the N20E running crystalline contact, a ,structura1 graben extenda to.arde the Eo.st for about .30 lan. lt le nbout 10 km .1de near Santa Brígida, and n~rows eaatwards.
In the North and . in the South, it ia terminated by more or lesa East-West striking. major, normal f'aults. The southern one transversel,. cuts the N20E running erystalline contaot and passes further westward into the embayment. On both sides of the graben, gr~ites and various otber basement rocIte are exposed with some overlpng remnants of' the " ") lo_er sandy portion of the Tucano Formation ( Sta Brigida FM • The disp~acmnen.t along the limiting taults seems to decrease eastward ... here a abal10w (? 80 me) sandstone section directly overlies the granite.
2. The Jeremoabo Fau1t.
About 40 km south of the SaDta Brigida Graben.,another East-West striking fault cute transversel,. tbe N20E trending mau crystalline contact. On the southern, downthrown bloek the Cretaceous sediments bave been of'tset about 18 km to.ards the Bast. 'l'his fault has alGO been trae.ed further westward into the embayment, for about 12 km.
3. The Strongly Fractured Zones Between Je~~ooabo And Canudos. Some t eJlty strongly fractured zonas have been mapped in the Tucano Formation, along the !ederal hjgbway between Jeremoabo and Canudos. A11 of them strike N 10 - 40 E.
'lhe !ractures and fissuras in the aandstone areu8ual1y filled with aandy material whieh ia somewhat 8111cif1ed and therefore more reaiatant to eroaion than the adjacent sandstone. 'lhe fractured sandstone eathers therefore in form of aharp "ridges whieh can be traced for many kilometers. They even could be follow-ed by plane continuing very atraight to arde the Nortb and the South where they disappear under the tabol~1rost Little, or no displaeement has been obG&rved along these fractured zones. Their a1gnificance lias in the fact that they often repreaent the lines of an abrupt change of the-regional d1p in both degree and d1rection. 4. 'lhe Piranhas Structure.
11 S.V.GUEDES (1948) mapped an ti ant1eline about 2 ka East of Catuni, on the R10 Vasa Barris, appr.24 km Weat of Jeremoabo. 'I'he long axis atr1kes N50E ~ along the Riacho das Piranhas, and .as traeed for a cout 6 km from the lItouth of the Riacho in the Rio. Vasa Barris towards NE. n n (C.N.P.Relatorio p.). 'lhe wildcat Piranhas 1fas then drilled on what was consldered the crest of tbe anticllne, and abandoned as dry hole at 1526.4ms. still above the basemtnt. 5. 'lhe Western Cryetalline Contact.
Major, normal faults of N20-30E, NIO-20W. and Nortb-.5outh directions term t be contact between the bas1n Gcdiments an4 the basement complex in tbe lest of the basin. 'lhe,.· were traced tor almost 200km trem North of Cocorobó to Araçi.
From Euclides da Cunha soutbward te Tucano, the displaeement along the fault 1s increasing. More or less East-West running trana-~" verse faults cauoed frequent offeets.
Duo to the lithologie similarity of the series involved the actuol aJ..'lount of th(J throw ia d1. f ficu1t to. 8accrtain. It ia baliev-ed to be Soo - 1000 ma in the area ef Araçi.
PETRÓJ .. EO BRASILEIRO S. A.
. The Eastern Crystail~ne Contaet.
Dlps up to 70Q in tbe Cretaceoua aandatones point to a fault contact with the crystal11ne ou the 8asteru sid-e of the-bastn, too; however, the fault itself has not been fOl,lnd expos-&d.
There is anotber observation po'iu-ting to tbeex1stenec of a bidden fault in the area East of Poço Verde, on the east side of the basin, appr. 30 km Southeast of Cicero Dantas.
In th1s area. the Marizal FM overlaps the cryatalline contaet with a basa! conglomerate,. and conaequentl,. maaka an,. posa blT exist ing tault~ The souree of the basal conglomerate is located aomewhere in the eastem hinterland where metamorphie limestones Viere expoaed when the eonglomerate was formed. Therefore it cons1*ts entírely o~ boulders and cobbles of me-tamorphica. This continues westwards to a carteia point here 8andstone boulders appear amon, t ~ e metamorphics. If one connecto t 1. e points where the first sandstono boulders are observed in the conglomerate ODe obtaina an appr. N 20 W running straight 11ue "hich apparentl;y reflecta tbe masked fault belo with sandstones ou the western, downthrown blo~k. 7. The Tucano Structure.
About 5 km South of Tucano. an appr. N20E striking ho~t la indicated bT reverse dips. Thia structure has been mapped in the Tucano Formation; it eould be traced for about 10 km in length, nnd about 5 km in width.
The C.N.P. wl1dcat •• n Macaco lhas drilled through the upper, western flank of this structure for 1861.4 ma and was ab ndoned as water well (mineral Vlater) etill not having penetrat~,d the Tucano Formation. 8. The Hassacará Structure.
About 29 km East of Euclides da Cunha, at Massacar&, another structural unit has been mapped.
8 km South of Massacará, the Cretaceous sandstones strike N40E. and dip SE. Tbis continues towarda tbe North . towards Mass-o.co.rá. where it ia terminated ou a u40E striking atrongly fractured zone. North of this zone, the dips are reVerse, e.g. to ~ards Northwest. Little . or no dia-placement has been observed along the fractured Zona; as on the road Jeremaabo-Canudos, it apparently representa a line of abrupt cl ange af t he regiona l dips .
I:tISTORY GEOLOGIC
Because no older deposita than low-er Cretaceoua. a.ce have ;yet been fOcund in the Tucano Bas1n., the initial tectonic movementa leading to the North-South strildng depresaion are throught to have occurr-ed in early Cretaceous t1me.
Dominantly coaree clC' stics Viere then transported into the d""os1on under terrestric, fluviati1e, and lacuatrine c-onditions. Further subsidence allowed brackish embayment _atera from the South (Reconcavo) to enter the Tucano Basin. At this time, the ~ore ahaly portion of the Tucano Formation was deposited. Periodical elevations closed the eonnecting cbannel as lacustrine and terrcstric deposits alternate ~ith brackish water sedimenta.
Accord1ng toa correlation af palIen stratigraphic horizona, " a connection between the Reeoncavo and the Tucano Basin ia postu1ated during the time of the upper Candeiaa and the Ilhas Formation(H.Mttr.tER. 1 // 1958). nowever, the source of the pollan might have been the satne in the adjacent are as of two separated baains as _ell. Tbe existence ar a connection ia conf1rmed, though. b,. the diacovery af a deep, reIati-vel,. narrow, North-South atrinking graben zo.ne through the west end of the Inhambupe-Esplanada Righ, (E.S.12. June 1958), and by the mere exi,!! tence of braekiah _ater deposita in tbe Tucano Basin.
To.arda the end of the lower (1) Cretllceous the connection .1th the Reconcavo "as apparently closed oft becauee tbe u, per, sana,. phase of the Tucano Format1on ia of terrestric nnd fluviatile origine Before the aedimentation of tbe Marizal n~, a hiatus in tbe deposition due to a :flegional uplift ia assumed 011 the obnervation that no upper Cretaceous sedimente have been coníirmed 111 tbe Tucano Basin. During thia time, the main per10d of tectonic movements occur-red , resulting in block faulting and tilting.
22-
PETRÓI .. EO BRAS][LEIRO S. Ao
!Jle MarUld m ot SUPPGlle417 10W'BZO Tertlar)" age -..11... th. çretaceoua aed1mentawith a dist1nct angular uneonfoftd.*,._ The oonaecUla' wlth the Reeollcayo d1d DO't open agaia because there is no oba.ervatl_ as to bracld.eh.ater infiuence 1D post-Cretaceoua depoSita.
A 811gbt rejuvenatioD ot · tectonic aovemente aff.ecte. the Harj.zaj, m, partiõu1ar17 in the marsinal areo. bel • • the tlat .l.71a& G1.eero Dantas FH .as d.p.~1ted.
A general up11ft. anel a sl1ght, .pjozoogen1cal Southeas,-~ut­ ing term1nated the se41mentaJ'7 c)"c1 •• It .la thought that tlte upllft_ ocnrre41J1 two ma1a etages 'becaue the reaa1nder. of an eu17 pa.p1aAa - t!.01l (top Cj.eero Dantu FH) and a yOUDgel' pellepl.a.1.c (top Mar1&a1 FH) are preserved.
PETROLEUII INDICATIOBS
J. BRAZIL (1947) reporta a .eopap of U •• oU ? ka Nor",-East of Sta BJoJ.sl.d&, at cal.4eizoão. ia th. orosabedde4. re4 and bro __ utO.D:eB of his "Sta Brlg1.d.a iH" (çper sand)" phaee 01 the Tucano Fa). lIa alao . mentiona ara occurnllo. of' d17 oU about 7500 -ma Nortb-NOl"tlt-East of Seta ~.igLda • .1D. bard s'i1tstones of the SUl. format1oa.
Although the wr~ter apen~ tbree day. in th1s aTea anel h1r64 the same gu1de .ho bad ace.o.paniecl Nr. BraaU . U 7eara aso. 1. t _&8 Ilot been poas1.b1e to locate these oU soepage. agaiD .. nol" Mq other ODe in the bae1a.
No oU or gaa allo_ .~r. reported troa the two w11dcata and the tbree ehallow stratigrapb1c •• 118 drilled b7 C.B.P.
PETBQLEUM POSSIBILITIES
SOU'ce R~.
Th. outerç be1ts co .. r tb. ma.J""-S1Dal basiD areaa <IIll7. Ia thls area, alI rocks obserTed are .xce.ding17 poor in Ol"gan1o matter, ... th. abâles. The wi1dcata ba .. pea.trate4 thi4k sect~ODa of grey and d~., abal.&8 .hieh a1ght !lave 71elde4 b1.tum1n-.. mattel'" though AO black ahales. or ld.tWlfinoua ahalea are reporte4.
~. posslbiUt7 exista that. 80UFC,. roeu are preaent mthe de.per, s.outhen central basiD parta. that. ta.. in the area Scuth of 1'Llca D..O to the Inbambupe-Eaplanada High. Reservoir Rocka.
'lhrougbout. th-e sediDutntV7 co-].uma theze are 1l\UUZ"OU, exc.el1ent .. potential reservo.1r rocu; udee4.abou~ 10 %01 the e%pose4 eectia consista of poroua anel peftleabl. S&Deist . . . . . Cover Roeu.
No auft:Lc1ent17 th1* cover rocu have be • .n note4 ia the .ço .. el secti.olb SiDo. a general ÜlCreaa. of th~ shal.,y daposi t1.OI1 ia boa t:. •• tOWarcls th. 1Jm.~. sou..the.b.aeia area, thi.f$ sea11nC shalee fl"e expectecl to ex1st in tM..e part of the througb .. Keana ot Accuaul..aru'oe. nu. to th. iDteu. bl.ock. tault.b.g and tUting. stZ"WItural trap OOllditions are posaible at yarioua pl.ac-••• Stl'1l&tura1 trap poaalbU1tl •• __ re obaenecl along the outcrop belta .oi the aer:a1JlalareM (.e. local atructure.), tbe7 continue und_r the Jlaak;l.ns tert1ar7 deposita towarcla the inner baaia parta.
Stratigraph1c trap condit101l4 are expeete4.. toe, b-ecalUl. of th. enYUODmenta1 «=l:larae-ter to tbe deposita. We4g1ng of porou. and perm.able atrata in a ahale sectiOD. rap14 lateral tacies changea f~ coar-se elasti" to 1mpel"Tiouarocka. and lenauc. !s COllUIlotL .iD ae41aellt. o~ alternatiDg terre.tr1eal. n" ... 1atu •• lacuat.rine.and bract:Jeb .. ater origixh .
CONCLUSIONS ARD BECOMHENDATIONS F r o • the Obseryatlona outl1ned in thia repozt ~t 18 c:u •• ludecl that DO posslbUJ.t1es for econOld.c ac.c'Wl1ll.atiol18 of oU ezia' inthe marginal. an4 northera aroas of the baau whlch cou14 be 1nyea'tigated b7 geolog1c 'surface 'IIon.
,Oi1 poaalbUitle. can be expectd 1D the eoutheftl, ceJltra1 bas1n parta which could Dot, Ar onl7 tndirectly be lnvestigate4 b7 . . ana of surface .ork~ due to pOQr outcrop c:onditio.na. genoZ'atJ.ug oonditions iD the RecuJlloavo was pe.r1od1.cal17 a1ao pr esent in th. .ou thera, 1nn.,. parta of the Tucano The a01lthward general17 ucreasing aJ'IlOUJlt of eha.l7 depG81ta JDa7 have 71.1484 8Ufti.clen~l,. th10lt COTar rocka, aad source r"u .. t.lo inV9stigat.' these posaibUiU.ea, a 88Q10g10 surface pa,rt,. ahauld c.omp1ote & d~tai.led map 0.1 the southena edge of the iUC8.I10 Bada. ot the área. oc01lpie4 b,. the IDJuiabu,-pe-E8Pl.anada H1gb. and the grabeA weat of 1t. and t1. in the Buriace _ork dane in the I1Orth.rn Reconca'f'O. Th1a area ia roughl)- lim.1ted by the tollow~ towna't AJ'ac;i. - 0ur1ç1Dgaa - ~Dtre Rios - Esplanada - Itaplcurá - Araçi.
Sino. the outerOp COâditioaaa are POQr. part1cularl.7 in the central part ofthe southen Tucano BasiD. a gravit7 .eter eUl"ye,. 18 x-.OQIDIMuuled _hícll should cover the SalDe area. and 'continue turther llorth to a Eaat-West line tbroush TU~ano in arder to tl~ 1n structurall,. better lmo_ &reu.
Baseei OD the deta1led geolog1c aurtaoe .orle and oa the gray1t1Dleter sur.e,.,on a structurall7 tavourable locatiem. a atratigaph1c test •• 11 shOUld be dr111e4 t-o tbe baaement_- Salvador. Juu ~, 1958.
25 - PETROBRÁS PETRÓT ... EO BRASILEIRO S. A ..
BRAZIL, dele 
DIXON, LeHe 
FREYDANCK. G.
O'GARAçÃe Tr. 
GUEDES, 8.Ve 
BlBLIOGRAPU
T1.Icano-Serra Velha-Salgado Cr.e-ek Area 01 lhe ItaplcUI'Ú Riyer Valle7. aeport No..111 1.946 Stratlgraphlc Posit19B of the Q,uarl",7 Sand - stOlle Seuthweet of Cipó. Bepo:r\ No., 14, ~ Beau' of G.o1oa~c Recotmaissance o-f the North Halt of the Bahia S~entaz'7 Eldtqment-. ~la. and W-edge' of Sergipe. ~p. No.20.!2!tZ. ReconnaJ.ssance Ge~~oS7 of the N\Y pari, o, neGOI{\ cayoJ BepOl"t BO .. 5i. l2!t2 Progresa Repor\ on 'th. WeaterD S14a of the Tucano Ba.stal.. Report NO ... 1.22! . Prelim1na l"Y »UCUSlliODO~ the Riaoho elas Piranhu StruCtur4 wi'h Ptteliminal7 MaP. Repor\. No. 30. ~ ~ Oeo100: and Structul'e of Rio Vasa BaJ';ri. tz~ arej1uho to CalludM t , Rep. No. 39. ~ The Struc,tural G801087 of the Rio Vasa Barria frca Gere.oabo. to Brejinho .1th Mapa and Cr~Secti0D8 neport No. 4" !2!!2 neCODDaiaaance Map of the North Balda Baa1Jl .. PrOgre88 Report Presented aa Part1al Resulta of tu F1eldwork for the Per104 10/48 te 8/49. Repore IÍO. 4.5. ~ Repor. No .. 29. ~ B.port No. 1', l2!!7. Hea.randua OD Tucano Strueture. nep. No. 21" 194Z Geo1og1c Report on. Tucano Structure. B.Z4. ~ PETROBRÁS PETRÓJ,EO BRAS ILEIRO S. A.
HUELLEB,B. Con-elatiOll of tb. Wella Me-l-Ba an4 PR-1';'Ba " (both Tucano Bà.a1a) with Wella tre. tbe .Reoonca.o Baad... Report No •• ~ Oliveira,A.I. a.ologia do BruU. p. 518-19 .. Rio de Janeiro, ~ v cit. de .LIVEIlU. Geologia do Bras:U, p. 518, ~ PRICE,C.I. ,.. Relatório .ôb.re area Norte e Nordeat. 40 Reconcayo ROSA,H. BaSaDO, Report 50.81, ~ " Relatór~o .ôbre a Bacia Sedimentar de Tucano. Report 50.154 • .!22.Z C.B.P. RELATORIO 1944, »p 16-11. Area ~ BDYa Souro o C1pó p 139, p 86, C.N.P. RELATÔRIO 1948, pp" 82-8J, Ire. Sedimentar ao Norte de Reconca.o C.B.P. RELATÓRIO 1949, pp 98-100 !rea Sedimentar ao Norte do Reoonca.o &aI Geoph"sical Conto~ Mapt RecoDDaiSSaDCe m: aoconcayo ES 1958. b7 l.A.. LONG (UD1ted G.opb .. ) G.oloste Map ar tbe RecollCayO BasiD.; compUed b7 Cb.A. "ANDai: Inolude4 with tbia ~eport ar. tbe follow1D.c Uluatratiou and map ••
1'- Coab1Md, General:ized Stl"atigrapb1c Col_. 'l'tIo.aJ10 Baaill (p.1) 2. Geo1og1o ReeoDDa1saance MaR 1.100 000, CARUDOS ( ,. aeologi. Ro.cmaaia8ance MIIp 11100 000, SANTA BRIGIDA '< 4. Geo1 "g1.c RecODJlsleeance Map 11100000 , EUCLIDES DA CUNlIA / ,. Goologlc RecoDDoi-sano. Map 11100 000, sIMIo DI; 6. aoologie ae.ODDs18aanc. Map 11100 000, TUCANO 1. Ge"olog1c R.o.ODnsissanc. Map 11100 000, TOBIAS BARRETO j 8. Geologi. ReOODDSis8ance Map 11250 000, TUCANO BASIJI j
A.P1!ENDIX area do Tucano Poço. C1-1, C10.2, 80-1 Secção Geologia Inhaabupe -
Bo.a Souro
9. Sehemati e ross-Seetion Santa Brigida Gr ben " " 10. Sehe tie Crosa-S et i on Mae eo 1 - Tipirien •
•• ••••• ••• ••••
IP E -
30.000 - 6-
