& Th1s prel1m1narT report consists of a br1et d1scuss1on of the results "obta1ned by a study of the sporomorphae and hystr1chosphae r1ds in shalT rocks ' of paleoz01c age from the Amazon reg10n. Two samples from the Paleozo1cs of the Maranhão Basin (well TB-l-MA ) have been added because of the good preservat10n of the1r (foss1l , content, and because the forms encountered m1ght plaT a role one daJ also in the Amazon reg10n.
The ma1n purpose of th1s report is to g1ve a general 1dea of the usefulness of the sporomorphae and' hystrichosphaer1ds 1n age determ1nat1ons and correlat10ns of the beds 1n the area of quest-ion.
The following core samples (shale) were ava1lable tor thls studT:
14 samples trom l80Zm to 2748m, 1nclud1ng the format10ns TR-l-AZ: , , , Maecuru-Ariramba, Curua-Barre1r1nha, Curua formatlon Upper member, vi th Spirophyton and Protosalvin1a, Monte Alegre and Ita1tuba. 4 samples from 975m to 1345m, Trombetas format1on and MB-l-AZ: , Curua format10n. 3 samples from 2688m to 2735m, curuá format1on, Upper Ro-4-AZ: member with Frotosalvin1a and Spirophyton. 2 samples from 3245m (ques.t1onable Ma~curú tormatlon) NO-3';'AZ:
· PETROBRÁS
PETRÓLIEO BRASILEIRO . S. A.
and core Ng 10 of unknoW,D age (no data avallable at present).
UR-l-AZ: 10 samples from 2026m to 265Om. Trombetas tormat1on, , , Maecuru format1on and Curua format1on. XU-l-PA: 6 samples, cores Nos.; 6 to 9, and 11 to 12. Maecurú formatlon, Ar1ramba member, and curuá tormat1on, Bar re1r1nha member. GU-l-PA: 2 samples trom l632,5-l634,0m and 1954,98-l958,28m. Quest10nable Pennsylvanian, probably Nova 011nda fo~ mat1on.
Fossll content and state of preservation
A ta1rJ..y large number of the s11des prepared trom the above -ment1oned rock samples merit belng called richly tossil1ferous, however, the preservation of the foss11s 1s relatively poor compa~ ed with the Cretaceous rocks of the Reconcavo. Type speclmens vere selected only from those samples that showed a good enoug~ preser vatlon, w.hlch depends to some extent on metamorphism. Already a sllght metamorphism (reg1onal, or b~<ing by intrusives) may destlOy entirely or partially the tiny and sometimes rather de11cate forms. Finer ornamentat1on and other valuable features, which could serve as discernible characteristlcs, are then destroyed or are 1nsurr1-c1ently preserved.
That s11ght metamorph1sm plays sueh an important role 1s c0I. roborated by the observat1on that 1n wells with no or few diabase
. PETROBRÁS intrusions, and also in relatlvely shallow vells, tbe preserva tlon ls much better than the average. The probable best preser vatlon was observed in the two samples from the well MR-l-AZ, w.here no diabase intrusions occur and wbere the highly fossl~l­ ferous Trombetas shale at the comparatlvely low depth of about l30Qm (Curuá shale at about 975m) has preserved the finest detalls 1n hystr1chosphaer1ds. Rock samples rrom the Carboniferous usually show a somewhat better preservat10n of the sporomorphae (hystrl chosphaerlds arealmost entlrely absentl) than those of the older formations, but are mostly less rleb 1n fosslls.
Most of the time has been consumed ln the select10n and estab11shment of tlform genera" and "form spec1es", and 1n the determ1nat10n or the1r characterist1cs. This study estab11shed 11 form genera (des1gnated as Hystrix-A, -B, etc.) each of which comprises a vary1ng number or form species (carry1ng numbers, ror examplea Hystrix-A-1, -A-2, etc.). All the types have been drawn and are present in the file of the Po1len Laboratory. Microfoto 'graphs are stl11 in preparation and may 1ater serve as an addl tiona1 help to recognize the dlfferent forms.
For the sporomorphae, the same coding system has been adopted as ls in use for the Reconcavo, however, the paleozo1c forms have been numbered 1ndependent1y. forms have been numbered 1ndependent1y. The stratigraphic results are summarized in the accompany lng chart 1, so far as the hystrichosphaerids are concerned. In thls chart, the type specimens are ~arked with (+), whereas their range ls marked with +. In all those cases where a further dlscr! minat10n or subd1v1sion of a form genus into form species was not poss1b1e(most1y because of 1nsufflclent preservatlon), a bracket '---.....,--J marks the occurrence and range of the undl vided form in the who1e.
Chart 1 demonstrates:
Devon1~, but d1splay in several cases a remarkable d1fterence 1n var1at10n (and also 1n the number of counted specimens per s11de) 1n the d1fterent tormat10ns;
2) that there 1s a marked break 1n de11very ot the hystrichos phaerids between the Devonian and the Carbon1ferous. Whereas a wealth of torms occurs in the older rormations the Carbon1ferous is nearly devoid ot hystrichosphaerids. This 1s of course due to a local lack and therefore is or lesser value than a positive but may be used with some caution ~or cor-occurrence or tossils, : , relation; 3) that real indu tossils which are restricted to one · single formation (as ror instance Leiofusa ror the Silurian) are rare; 4) that we, theretore, have a faunal assemblage that varies in time more quantitatively than qua11tatively in forms. A'prac tical application for correlat10n must, therefore, be done besi des taking in account the index fossils, largely by means or a quantitative analysis. - The sporomorphae have not yet been included in :::hart 1, be.cause trix to sporomorphae mostly about 2 : 1); 2) display a smaller variation ot ditferent torms w.hicb mostly belong to very s1mple, uncharacterist1c types, at 1east in the Si1urian and to some extent also in the Devonian, whereas the Carboniferous contains more differentiated forms. The hystrichosphaerids, therefore, otter tor the present a better and more rapidly accessable base for correlation. The sporomorphae, however, are stil1 in study and wi1l be later add ed to chart 1. - A more detailed zonation of the Silur1an, Devonian and Cal: boniterous as chart 1 shows at present, is not possible on the base or the present1y knOldl forms and the smal1 number of samples which must be considered too sma11 ror sucb a purpose. It is, however, probable, that a zonation may result from a quantitati ve analysis ot one set or samples taken from õne we1l in not too long 1ntervals. Sucb a wel1 cou1d then serve as a standard se-Hecommendations As this study had to be based on relative1y few core SUl p1es w.h1ch, moreover, are dlstributed over several dirferent wells, the basis for rurther correlatlon work must be necessarily spotty and unsure. These shortcomings are especially true for the Carbo niferous, of w.hich only 4 samples could. be~included in this study. In order to get a sounder base ror future work we would prefer to have one we11 sampled thorough1y 1n the sma11est poss1b1e inter vals (cores and di tch samples) and then to use this wel1 . section as our standard for correlation work.
KFK!ibs
Respect1ful1y submitted,
