Mr. Wal ter K. Link: Exploration Department Manager Petrobrás-Depex Rio de Janeiro,Df.
Enclosed you will find 4 copies of a report b,y geologist Guntram Kremer of the structural geology in the Sao Mateus do Sul area, southern Paraná.
TG-ll was assigned the task of doing structural mapping in this area by utilizing the many shallow holes drilled by Xisto. The purpose of this project was to locate possible drillable structqres for petroleum exploration.
Stratigraphical1y, only the Permian Irati and Serra Alta formations were studied in detail. The Irati formation contains two bituminous shale zones; one is 5 to 6 meters thick and the other is 2 to 3 meters thick. Although the upper, Serra Alta shale formation is capped by the Potinga sandstones, no evidence of oil migration from the shales into the sandstones has been found. The formations maintain uniform thicknesses throughout the area and, therefore, no isopach map was made.
The only possible struct~al closure is in the area about 20 kilometers northwest of Sao Mateus. In this area, a long, north-south trending, diabase-filled, normal fault develops a stratigraphic throw of 110 to 135 meters, with the up-thrown side being baeinward. A transversal fault creates closure on the north. The great amount of diabase in the area suggests that the strati graphic displacement was caused by vertical uplift of intruding dia base.
Since the map and report may serve, as a drilling guide for Xisto, we request that the additional copies be sent to Tremembé. The distriot does not recommend additional work in the area, nor do we believe that the fault structure indicated on the map warrants drilling.
EJB/os
DEBSP-367/59 , Ponta Grossa, Paraná 11 November,
"GEOLOGIO REPORT ON, THE TRATI-SERRA ALTA OUICROE ABRA LE Dtstr1to de Exp10raqão da Bacia SediJl8D tar do Paraná Ponta Grossa, Paran' Ootober 16, Th1s report is intended to serve_as a drilling guide for "srx" operations in the vicinit,y of Sao Mateus do Sul, Southern Paraná, where an area of 360 squara kilometera waa mapped b.Y TG-ll. Working conditiona are good during the whole year,living conditions are adequate in the mapped area.
The flat topography is only interrupted by escarpment forming diabase dikes in the northern and northweatern part of the report area.
The survey W8a started at the contact Palermo-Irati fm and carried westward to the eontact Serra Alta-Teresina "fm. The Irati fm shows a consistent th1ckness throughout the report area and contains two bituminous sha1e bodies in its upper parte The upper bituminoua abale or 1& bitum1nous Irati shale has a th1akness of 6 metera and forma the top of Irati fm. The lower or 2& bitum1nous Irati shale of 3 metera thicknass is separated from the ·· first ona by a non-bitum1nous to part1y bitum1nous interval of 8 metera. - The Serra Alta f.m revealad a cõnaiatent th1cknas8 of 110-120 metera al1 over the report area. It ia overlain by the Patinga sand faoies, wh10h representa the basia of Teresina tm in the report area and adjacent regions in Southern Paraná and Northern Santa Catarina. All Lower Permian sedimenta mapped with1n the report area stayed submerged after the basinw1de Irati transgression and are of marine origine During late Triassic and early Jurasaic time dia base intruded along rejuvenated and ~ewly created faults.
The regional dip of sediments in SOuthérn Paraná and in the report area points WSW and SW, exceeding nowhere 1 l/2Q degree of inclination. The fault "pattern shows NNE, NE and NW pointing trends of strike. The western, upthrown f1ank of a NNE striking fault of major magnitude "in the northwestern part of the report area merits a cloaer invéstigation for oi1 by shallow drilling down to the Rio Bonito aands, wh1ch might aho~ here an updip accummulation of " Itarar' generated oi1. An intensiva aearch in thia region and over the who1e report area -ahowed however no 011 or gas indicationa. A10ng the who1e 1ength of the above mentioned fault diabase has 1ntruded.
The contour structttre map 1:25,000 of the mapped area with contours baaed on the top of the 1Q bituminous Irati shale ia expected to fUrnish new information for auy further drilling operat10ns by "BIX" with1n the mapped area.
ABSTRACT bE
Page 
The oorrelation o~ surfao. and subeurfaoe data within the mapped area resulted in the oompilation of the Geologio and Struoture Oontour lIap of the · são 14ateus do Sul Irati-Serra Alta outorop area 1:25,000, wh1ch oovers the whole area mapped and aooompenies tbis reporte As this map is regarded to turnish sufficient stratigraph10al end stnotural .. informatioD to serve as a drill1ng guide for "SIX" and no th1ckness ohanges of the :tall Irati seotion were obserVed Within the mapped area, no further cross sectioDS or Isopaoh maps of Irati formation are presented with tais reporte The top of the upper or tirst bitum1nous Irati shale, wh10h is regarded by the writer to present the top of Irati formation, represents the contour datwa in the acooapanylng map.
D. Previous Invest1gations: ot previou8 investigatlons within parts _of the report are a the tollowing report of L. de LOOZ7 was available to the writer: DE LOOZY, L. - 1954 - OONTRIlIUTIOH TO TBE PETROLEUK GEOLOGY 01' TBE SOUTHERN PART 01' THE SUTE 01' PA1W'J1. SDI-DETAILED GEOLOGICAL SURVEY o:r THE AREA BEHEEB UBIlo DA VITORIA. - M. M'ALET - sIo JlADUS. DO SUL. O.B.P. - Ootober,1954 - .Petrobrás-Depex report n l 51 Until tod.q 58 strat holes "ere drilled by ".sn" w1 tMn the surveyed area. The dri1ling logs of these strat holes were available to the writer and their subsurtaoe data .ere correlate! with the surfaoe data obtained in the field.
E. ACknowledgeaents:
!he writer w1shes to expres8 bis thanks for a11 the help of:tered to hiJl &Dd bis :tield erew by Engl Gui40 Pisoni, engineer in charge o~ ·SIX" operatioDs in são Rateus do Sul.
!he ~OWD ot são Kateus do Sul. ani the report area are 8itua~ed about 140 kilo.meters South of Ponta Grossa and are eaai17 aooesaib1e by road trom the ~strict headquarters. Às "SIX" operates a .Radio . Station~ radio commUDication with District headqü&rters oan be used at 1iberty ..
Cltaa~e and Vegetation:
. !here are no distlnet dr,y and ralny seaSODS in Southern Paraná. Pield .ork oan· be carried OD throughout the year. Within most of the surve7ed area grow woods of Paraná pine and Mate bushes.
Living Condi tions:
"arx" regional headquarters and .a amall hotel in the town of são Kateuã dO -Sul offer adequate liv1ng conditioDs tor a tie14 orew.
Relie! and !opographl
Generally the report area ShOW8 a tlat to slight17 rolling topograph1. More or 1ess pronounced escarpments are foraed b7 ~abase dikes in the Dorthern and .estem parta of the surveyed area.
General Stateaents
CODcording with the worklng prograa issued b7 DEESP tor .the são )(ateus do Sul area, onl7 the Lower Peraian lrati &nd Serra Alta outorop zones were 010se17 surve7ed. Genera1ly the surve7 .as carr1ed trom .0 the Palerao-Irati contact to the Serra Alta-feresina oontact. stratigraph10 anoma1ies were observed within the Irati and Serra Alta sediments ot the surve7ed area.
GEOGRÀPHY
S~RA~IGRAPHY
The stratigraphic sequence and tbicknesses of Irati and Serra Alta sediments in the sio Mateus do Sul area are demonstrated in tbe following generalized stratigraphic summary.
Sbale, dark blue gray, light gray and light blue weathering colours, masaively bedded, blocky, soft, occasional limestone nodules.
Guatá Group UPPER PENNSYLV ANIAN
General: The Palermo fm. W8a named in 1908 by 'Ih1 te after i ta type locality, the village of Palermo in Santa Catarina. Only the uppermost part of the Palermo tm ia outcropping in the report area.
Lithology : The upper Palermo beda, outcropping in the report area, conaiat of pink, reddiah and yellow silty abale with lenticularly interbedded micaceous ailtstone or fine-grained, argillaceou8, light brown sandstone •
. Th1ckness and Areal Extent: The uppermost part of the Palermo tm, with a th1ckneaa of 10-15 meters, representa the eastem margin of the report area. Palermo beds of a lower stratigraphic position, composed of fine-grained, argillaceous sandstone and silty abales, are outcropping in the northeastern part of the report area on the downthrown flank of a NNE striking fault.
Th10kness in metera
IPac1es: The s1lty ahales and fine-gra1ned, argillaceous sandstones of the Palermo f.m 1nd1cate a depos1t1on 1n a brackish to mar1n. environment.
Age and PaleontologY:The Palermo fm 18 of Upper Pennsylvan1an age. No foss1ls were found 1n the Palermo beds of the report area. Orig1n: See Jac1es. 011 and Gas Poss1b1l1t1es: The very t1ght sandstones and s1lty shales of the Palermo beds, outcropp1ng 1n tbe report area, can I not be regarded as potent1al souree or reservo1r rocks.
Clast1c and Sand/Shale Batios: The Palermo sed1ments w1 th1n th. mapped area sbow a clast~c rat10 of 50 and a sand/shale rat10 of 1.5.
LOWER PERMIAN - Estrada Nova Group Irat1 tm General: The Irati fm was named by Wh1te 1n 1908 after 1ts type loca11ty, the town of Irat1 1n Paraná. The Irat1 fm representa the lowest part of the Lower Perm1an Estrada Nova group. Lithology : The Irat1 f.m ean be d1v1ded 1nto two d1fferent l1tholog1cal un1ts, the lower and the upper parte The lower part cons1sts of blu1sh gray to dark gray, poorly bedded and lam1nated, blocky ~o mass1ve clay sbale w1th occa81onal, often s1l1c1f1ed l1mestone lenses. Iron oxide concret1ons are common. Weather1ng colours are l1ght gray to l1ght blue gray and p1nk.
The lower part of Irat1 fm has a th1ckness of 21 meters. The upper part of Irati fm is made up of alternating lime stone, bituminous abales and clay shales, starting with a med1um to thick bedded, gray to dark gray limestone of 6 metera tbick-ness at the basia. This limestone ~s o~ten a strong bituminous smell, is rather dense, hard and sp intery. Small pyrite concretions are eommon. Tbe limestone is overl 1n by 3 meters of b1tuminous shales (2 Q bituminous Sh~le). The Irat1 b1tum1nous shales are dark brown to blaek, well laminated to fissile, hard and br1ttle, with thin (5 mm-l em) interbeds of gray and dark gray limestone. The 2Q b1tuminous sbale shows generally tbe h1ghest teor of b1tumen and represents the best source for any art1ficial extraction of 011.
The 2Q b1tuminous Irati shale is overlain by about 8-9 meters of alternat1ng thin beds of blue gray and dark gray clay shale, similar to the basal part of Irati fm, th1n 11mestone beds (partlY s1l1eified) and th1n beds of f1ssile dark brown to black, slightly bitum1nous sbale. On top of this only partly bituminoua interval follow 6 metera of dark brown to blaek b1tum1nous, fisaile, well laminated, 1ndurated, brittle ahales which repreaent the lQ b1tuminous Irati sbale and the top of the formation.
Thickness a·nd Areal Extent: Tbe Irati fm and i ta bi tuminous and caleareous párts show alI over the mapped area a consistent thiek neSSe The who1e Irati seetion measures 43-45 metera. The lQ bituminous shale has a th1ckness of 6 metera and the 2Q b1tuminoua shale a th1ckness of 3 metera.
In ·:tb.e eastem part of the report area the Irati :tm strftes NNE within a relatively tbin outcrop belt. Irati beds, striking 1n the asme d1rection were a1so encountered on the downthrown flank of a major NNE strik1ng fault in the northwestern part of the report area.
Strat1graphic Relationah1ps: The Irat1 f.m over11es the Palermo tm without any sign of a recogn1zable unconform1ty. The 1 Q bituminoua sbale, representing tbe top of Irati fm, is eonformab1y "overlain by the Lower Per.m1an Serra Alta fm.
!Seles: The basal clay shales of the lower part and the alternatlng llmestones and clay sbales with lts two bltumlnous shale bod1ea of the upper part of Irat1 tm are cone1stent throughout the report area and 1n adjaeent parta oi Southern Paraná and Northern Santa Catarina.
Age and PaleontologY: After von Huehnes descript10n and def1n1tlon of Mesosaurus rema1ns the Iratl fm belongs to the Lower Permian, representing the lowest Permian beds depos1ted 1n the Paraná Bas1n. The Paleontology of the Irat1 fauna 1s perhaps the most well known of all sedimente deposited in · the Paraná Baein and has been desc%ibed 1n deta1l by many authors.
Origin: The begin of Irat1 t1me W8S marked by a bas1nw1de Lower Permian transgression, after wh1ch Irati sedimente were depoa1ted 1n a shal10w sea of probably high sa11nity. The limestone. and b1tuminous ahales of the upper part of the Irat1 format1on indicat. a mar1ne environment w1 th 11 ttle fresh water eupply.
General: The Serra Alta fm represents the middle part of the Lower Per.m1an Estrada Nova Group marine c1'cle.
Ldthology: 'or 1ts greater part the Serra Alta ~m consists of the same dark blu1sh gr&.,. to dark gra.,., massi vel.,. bedded and blocky' sbales as the lower part of Irati fm. .Many th1n, mostl.,. lenticular and partl.,. s1l1c1fied 1nterbeds of l1mestone are found in the lower and middle part of Serra Alta fm. Iron oxy-de concretions are common. In 1ts upper part the Serra Alta beds become gradually more silt.,.. Lenses of very fine grained to fine grained, highl.,. argillaceous, yellow, pink and brick red sand are found near the top of Serra Alta fm, marking the gradual change from Serra Alta to Teresina sediments.
Thickneaa and Areal Extent: With1n the . mapped area the Serra Alta fm shows a consistent thickness of about 110 meters. The Serra Alta t.m covera the greater part of the report area, striking NNE SSW.
Stratlgraph1c Relatlonshlpa: The Serra Alta fm overlies conformably the Irati tm and ls overlain conformabl'1' b.,. the Lower Permian Teresina tm. As there la no sedimentar" type break between Irat1 and Serra Alta fm, the Serra Alta and Irati fm represent after the writers oplnion the same sedimentary cycle and. should be regarded as one stratigraph1c uni t.
Jacies: The h1ghly argillaceous Serra Alta sbale facies with irregularl.,. diatributed aand lenses ~t the top ls conslstent throughout Southern Paraná and Northern Santa Catarina. Age and Paleontolo&y: The Serra Alta ~m belongs to the Lower Per.mian. Or1gin: The Serra Alta sediments were deposited in a shallow, gradually deepening sea. Oil and Gas Possibilities: The Serra Alta shales might be regarded as possible source beds for oil or gas generation in deeper parta of the Paraná Basin.
Mineralog;r: No minerals of commercial value bave been found until today in Serra Alta sediments of Southern Paraná.
General: The Teresina tm, represent1ng the uppermoet part of the 'Lower Per.m1an sedimentar,y cyc1e, was named after its type locality the town of Teresa -Cristina in Paraná. Only the basal part of the Teresina tia is out'cropping r i thin the report area.
Li tho10Q: 1f1 thin the report area, the basa! part of Teresina ta consists of a bighly argi11aceous, tight, varyco10ured, very fine to fine grained sandstone. Coloura are, ye110w, brown, brick red and piDk. Lent1cul.ar~ interbedded, arg111aceous, Serra Alta type sbales are common. The baaa1 Teresina sandetone, named Potinga sandstone by De Loczy after ita type loca1ity the Rio Potinga va1ley in Southern Paraná, has a th1ckness of 15-18 metere. It ia overlain by the si1ty, wel1 bedded and laminated shales and eherta which make up the bulk of Teresina ta.
Th1ckneas &nd Areal Extent: The outcrop zone of the Potinga sand- , atone of Teresiaa t.m representa the westem margin of the mapped area. The survey .as only carried westw8rd to the contact Serra Alta-Teresina. The basa! Potinga sandstone sho~ with1n the report area a th1ckness of 15-18 metera.
Stratigraph1c Re1ationsh1pa: The Teresina ~ over11es conformab17 Serra Alta fm. lacies: The basal aandy Poti.nga facies of Teresina faeies seema to be cODsistent in Southern Paraná &nd Northern Santa Catarina.
Age and Paleontologz: The Teresina fm belongs to the Lower Permian. Orig1n: The basal Teresina sands are coastal shallow sea deposita. Oil and Gas Possibilities: The basal sandy Potinga ~acies of Teresina fm is too tight, to offer any reservoir possibilit1es ~or oil or gaa.
Correlation: The basal sandy facies o~ Teresina tm aeems to correlate only wi th e qui valents in Southern Paraná and Northenl Santa Catarina. It la not known in more Northern and Southern parta of the Paraná Baain. Cla.tio and Sand/Shale Ratio: The clastic ratio of the baaal Teresina General: The Triassio Jurassic Diabase intrusives and Lava liows of the Paraná Basin are named Serra Geral tm.. Only Diabase intruaions, cutting into older sediments and for.m1ng dikes or 8il18 were encountered within the report area.
General: Alluvial gravels and sands bave been deposited in the river bed8 of the Rio 19uaçú and other major r1vers, cross1ng the report area.
- 11 -
Regional Structure: The regional dip of 8ediments pointa WSW to SW, within th. report area. The dip ia very gentle and exc.ed. nowhere 1 1/2Q inclination; normally it ranges from 1/2Q to IA inolination. The atrik. of alI fault., ob8erved With1n the mapped area, ahows NNE, NE, and mr trends. Th1.s trend conforms wi th the normal fault pattern of the Southern half of the Paraná Basin. M08t of the faults obaerved within the report are a are conneoted with diabase intrusion ••
Stratigraphic Overlapa and Pinchouta:
There are no atratigraphic overlapa or pinchouts of sedimenta within the report area.
Looal atruoture of maj or magnitude was observed in the .north _estem pB:rt of the report area, .here one ~NE atrik1ng fault could be followed for 16 kilometera. Th1a fault aho •• a thro. of about 110-135 • with Irati or Palermo beda on th. upthrown .estem f1ank and Teresina or Serra Alta beda on the downthrown eaatem flank. Th1s fault explains the repetition of seetion of Palermo, Irati and Serra Alta sedimente in the northweatern part of the report area. Â 8carp forming diabaae dike marks the whole length of this fault. Theoretioally there ex1st possibi11ties for an up-d1p hydroearbon acoumulation in sandy Rio Bonito or Palermo rooka trom marine Itarar4 souree beds OD the upthrown tlank of th1a fault. An intensive aearch for any oil indioatioDs in the Palermo outcrop area on the upthrown flank of the fault was however negative.
All other structures observed and mapped within the report area, are minor faults with a throw vary1ng trom 5 to 30 meters. Most of them ahow diabase intrus10ns along the fault planes and no indication of 011 or gas acoumulat1on.
- 12 -
Yollowing the deepening of the baain and deposition of brackiah to partly ahallow marine aedimenta during Upper Pennsylvanian time (Palermo ta) there W8S a general Lower Permian transgreasion which caused the deposition of shallow marine Irati sediments all over the Paraná baain. During the time of deposttion of Serra Alta and Teresina aedimenta the Southern halt of the Paraná Easin atayed submerged. Serra Alta and Teresina formationa were depoaited in a true marine environment. In late Tria8aic to early Jurassie time basio magma intruded along rejuvenated older faults or newly oreated faults and formed numerous diabase dikea and sills all over the Paraná Eaain.
No petroleum indications like Gil or ga. eeeps bave been enoountered within the mapped area.
The Irati tm contains two bitum1noua abale bodiea in ita upper part, which might merit an artificial extraction of hydrocarbona on an industrial basia.
Generally the petroleum possibilitiea of the report area must be regarded aa poor.
Souree Rocks:
a. Lower Pennsylvanian, Itarar' Group
Marine Itararé shales are developed in adjacent eastem parta of the report area. It can be aS8umed that these marine abales, which are regarded as possible aource beda, are developed with considerable thickneaa in the subsarfaoe of the report area.
GEOLOGIC HISTORY
PETROLEUM INDICATIONS
PETROLEUM POSSIBILITIES
b. Lower Permian, Irati fm.
The bituminous shales of Irati f.m are basinwide regarded as potential eouroe beds in deeper parte of the basin, west ward of the report area. ward of the report area. tm, The two bitum1noua sbale bodies at the top of Irati highest espeoially the 2Q bitum1noue Irati sbale wh10h showa the teor of bitumen, might merit an artifioial extraotion of hydrooarbons on an industrial basia.
c. Lower Permian, Serra Alta tm..
The marine Serra Alta abales, oovering the greater part of the report area, might be regarded as potential source beda farther westward, in deeper parta of the basin.
Reservoir Rook.: No potential reservoir rooks are outcropping with1n the report area. The Palermo aandstones at the top of Palermo fm are highly lentioular and too tight for offering good reservoir possibilities. The same is true for the highly argillaoeou., silty to fine arenaoeoue Potinga aandstone, whioh representa the basia of Teresina fm.
Mean. of Aooumulation:
.Â DE striking, 16 kilometer long faul t of maj or magnitude oftera some possibilitiea for an up dip aooumulation of hydrooarbons r i th1n the Upper Pennaylvanian Rio Bonito sands, which should be present in the relative1y uear eubsurface ou the upthrown f1ank of the fau1t in the northwestern part of the report area. Any oil accumulated there should come trom marine Itararé sources. A thorough search for oi1 indicatione in the outcrop area of sandy Palermo sedimenta on the western, upthrown flank of this fault was without poaitive resulta.
- 14 -
CONCLUSIOBS AND RECOMMENDATIONS
Th1e report and especially its accompanying Geologie and Struoture Contour Map 1:25,000 of the lrati-Serra Alta outcrop area in the vicinity of são Mateus do Sul 18 lntended to serve as a drl111ng guide for "SIX" operatlona in the above mentioned area. The contours based on the top of the IA bituminous I rati sha1e,which showa a oonslstent th1ekness of about 6 meter. and L . conslstent th1Ckness of about 6 metera and ~ . cons1stent interVa1 between la and 2a Iratl bituminou8 sbale of 8 meters should taci11tate the ' location of fUture dri11 holes with1n the mapped area.
The eastem margin of the up1ifted fault block in the north westem part of the report area merlts a sha110w dri11ing prograa down to Rio :SOni to fm. by ~he tranaport&ble Pranks rig at the disposition of DEBSP.
Ponta Grossa, October 16, 1959
-
1. DE LOCzr - 1954 - Contribut1on to the Petroleua Geology oi the Southern part oi the state oi Paraná-Sem1-deta11ed Geolog1oal Survey oi the area between União da V1tor1a K.Kalet - são Mateus do Sul.- C.N.P.- Oot. 1954. Petrobrás report nA 51.
2. R.M.SAN~ORD & P.W.LARGE - 1957 - Paraná Eas1n Speo1al Study - DEBSP, Sept, 1957 - Report nA 107.
BI:BLIOGRAPHY
- 16 -
