1. Since the southern area of Pojuca-Central oil field ia directly related to the Mata-Catu structuràl trend, and primarily of first interest for the structural drilling, we may say that enough strat holes have been drilled in the surveyed area.
2. As indicated by Água Grande, pojuca and Mata oil field structural maps, the area surveyed is probably highly faulted. On the other hand, the sand facies of the Ilhas formation in which most of the wells were drilled gives no correlatable markers on the e-Ioga. The assumption that "structllral contours were drawn on a distinctive , ca!careous, silty sandstone approximately 55 meters above the CatU-Sao Paulo sandstone sequence" is possibly a mis leading.
3. As a consequence of what was mentioned in the above Item 2, interpretation based here only on the shallow· strat holes is unreliable.
4. The drillsite resulting from the structural drilling program, in my opinion, is of questionable value. However, as a regional inference from Pojuca-Central oil field maps and residual gravity interpretation of the area, testi~g of the prospect i8 re quired.
5. In order .to make possible the use of a palinologic para meter control in such difficult surveyed area it i8 suggested that alI wells of the structural drilling program, always that is possible, terminate in a sbale bed. After care circulation, a representative sample of it should be collected for future pollen analyses. outhem are. 0'1 P03110 -OelJ.trai oil f1e14 Q ~. r1Mr1l7 dlrectly r.elate" to ~h. Mate.-OaW struotural trenl, 8I1d rof ZJ.ra' 1nterest t r the etructural 4r.l111tig .. 1aÇ s&:f that .noup. trat holes .bave be&Jl dr1ll.ed bl. the SlUTelea area.
Gl'ái1Ie, ojuca ua. lIata 011 ti_ 8 in410a'e4 b;y _ '2. 'traotural I18.pe, tu area survelecl ta probably ldghlt f te4_ 00 -the .-l~. lhe ssu,ptlon 1bate "81:ru.Q~ contours"re n_ o. the oth.r ~aD4, the aand ~acles of tbe Ilhas toraatlon la Vb1 IBOSt of the QUa ... r8 ü!Ued «1V8S ao anela: bl. iIàl'kera . . e. dúiinotive c%oareoua. sUi)r sandstone aIProx.ju.te17 5~ .. ra oas1b~ a JIi ... aboY" the OatU-Sao ~o san48tone sequeno. la 1.ad~.
3. AS a oonse<1U4lnoe of ldlat y ••• n1;10n a in th. ab v. Ite. 2, 1hterpret 1:10n 'baaed are onl:7 011 'u ahallow atrat hol •• 18 '9'&111e. ~.X'... . \UlI"ellable.
'9'&111e. ~.X'... . 4. Thê 4r1lls1te resultlDa ~rom ~he st.Not1U'âl Ul11lq Pro":i 1i11V opimon" la 'Ót questionab'! taference t~ Po~o~O.ntral oil 11.14 aps aaa reala..l ~e110 ~V1tr ~nt.~retatlonot \he area; test~ bf th »roe,eot 18 re qu1re4.
5. In order o iIlake poa 1b1.8 tlle use of a pâ1ino10 C,&I"&- a.t r oontrol. in 8l1Ch di1'tlcult 8urv.;y. are 11; 18 elilCBee 1hat al1 wells of t~ tl'UOw.ral. 4r111ut ograa. that 18 wrq p08s1'ble, teratltáte in a abale 'b.a. After are o roulat1oa, a pr.a.n~at1v. sample of lt hould e collectta for fU~ o~n . ~~~..
GP/ is. 
Pile: Report nº 251,RPBA-Depex , D1I=5, PETROBRÁS IPE-4-A PETRÓLEO BRASILEIRO Enc10se p1ease find a copy of Mr . Conrads report on the Pojuca Area Structure Drilling. This was done during a 9 day period is a good example of the results tha t can be obtained by this party in suitab1e area .
I agree wi th 11r . Conrads conclusions in this area and a location has already been re c ommended and approved 2620 meters south and 1660 meters east of PC-lI . There is some risk as a structura1 rise in the Ilhas does not necessarily indicate a corresponding rise in the Sergi , however it is fe1t that the area is well worth a wildcat we11 .
During th period Deee b r 10. through D ember 18, 1958. conduat d in an area 80uth shallow structural drUling progr w of the Pojuea Central 1e14 with the co pl tion and 10gg1ng of s v n toen shallow sub-surlaee holea.
Interes in th Prospeet was d riTed through an interpre tat10D of th pojuca Fi ld strueture by Mr. W.M. Joung in Rio whieh to th aouth of PC-ll • indieated th prob bility of ri ing structur In addition. urfac mapping by Grabert (Reterene. No. ~) showed a blo k of Ilhas upthrown againe 8·0 Sebastião.
All locationa w re made with rer rene. to "C-ll which WD.8 th n tiad to Astrolab Station A-5 in CatÚ. In dd1t1on. a traveI' aa eompleted betw en A-5 and A-lO in Mata de são João.
Sh llow structural drilling south of the ojuc Fi ld - h d tin d a tilted íault bloCk approxim tely 200 m tera higher than the PC-ll dry hole. This interpr tation is qUali!! by noting the dia aney b tween shallow and deep t~cture in that indicat 4 high in th Ilha. y reflect an It parie. 10 •• Nevor th los8. in tbe aba~nco of a method which will predict thiB oceurr nce. a location ia a t of PC-li. Dp th to reco end d 2620 met r south nd 1660 th Sergi w111 pproximat 12 O m t 1'0.
6.000 - 9 - PETRÓLEO BRASILEIRO S. A. tn th Pojuca - Catú. Acoord1n to Gr rt'. ur! ce ppin Are ,th fOrIllations expos.d in the pro pect in 1uele th. Barr ir . . , são Seb ti·o, anel I1haa. uat.rnary alluviuu ar d posited in th. valley of the P juc • Structural 4r1lling confirms, in aner , / , the stratigraphy at the urface.
Thia mo t r cent of th Rec$ncavo s dim nte pen trated in hallo. hole nQ 10 .here the formation con i teci of fiu -grane' to conglo eratie ae d tones, the ub-ronnd d. poorly sorted t anel ar c men ted 'ri. iron ondes.
This tormation ia diff1cult to id ntity in th pojuca South 9 and lQ drill d es. Cor hol equenee of silty. oon ahales, and li ht greanish grrq, very fine grained aandston a which ar prob bly sXo S basti·o in ag • Ostracoi fSr en-çay to bl Qk shaJ.ea, and light gray, ver'J fin. grain d mioae oue sandaton s of the Ilh pr do in te in the a dr1~ed. Intercalated thin. .hite y anel black limeston with miea ceou • calcar ou 1lt are a180 pre ent. To th south. as sh on th map enclosure. a rapid facieB chang ia interpreted with the d velope. ment of a massiva Ilh &and. Th sand ia .hit varying to ros in co lori very fine to fin gr in d. aubrounded. well sort d. c bon ceous with very poor poroo1ty. Structural int rpretations und r Buch cond1-tioJ1a are doubtful.
STRATIGRAPRY TERTIARY B RRElMS s O SEBASTll0
6 .00 0 - 9 - Btru tural contoure • re drawn on a. diati11ctiv calcareoua. - pproximately 55 motel' above th CATO - 510 PAULO a11t7 andeton - aandston aequ nee. ~hia otnt _as cho •• n b c ua8 1\ appe a to • str ti r phical17 conatan both the atructure holes and in the P juca Field w 11 • Structure in the int r diate bet_ee P u and Mata de são João ia amUar to he contiguration of the ntire M! -- eouth aIIt trendin normal. faul t - CATO' trend. A minor northwes f. t p ra1.1 18 th. major MA~Â ... CATO - with the upthrOWll blo k t th Fault. SUbsidiar, faults radi t. to th. north. t formin amall hor ta nd tilt d f ult block situated ap oXimat 17 three ~omet.re 209 eter higher than the dr.1 bole. Cor elation to th outh o~ thia area ia unr 11abl.' although lU1 T n high r stru tur 1 loc t10n U ind1cat.4, th. d ta do not warrant •• rlou. con 1derat10n.
~ pr vioua g ologiat. hav note th d cr.pan~ b tw D eh d de p structure in th Agua Grande r g1on. ~is ltuat10n can be r adily demon trated at Pojuca throu a co p iso of th ahallo. p included with his r po~t . and the fiel m ~ ontours b7 Mr. Young on the top of the It pica. The ituat10n simpl,. at te 18 that a •• ~1 h~gh on shal10w Qtructure ~s oft n ~ow on th. e p r b d • In an att pt to pr ict dee» tructure frem shal10w data. AD i opaeh was constructed between the contour trueture dr1l1 hor1zo and th top of th li parica CEnel aure I1C 2). 13uming a time lhe ai the upper hor1zon. th. isopach indic t 8 th intluence of faultin cont mporaneoua w1th d pos1tioD upon the 1sopach thickB. Untortunat 117 th patt rn cannot be prcdicted becnuse hallow taulting doe8 not r pe deoper faulting in thia are • s. A. PETRÓLEO BRASILEIRO
2. Ilhaa lQarkeJ" to top Itçarica. Iaopach Map, m1.ddl REFEREHCES
