Apresentamos à sua apreoiação o Relatório em epígra fe, de autoria de E. J. Bauer, Geólogo-Chefe da Divisão de Geologia da RoP.Ba.
Refere-se o presente relatórlo à área ~ue ~irounda o Qe~l, onde 3 poços j~ foram perfurados numa tentativa de ver a desooberta do prlmeiroo O autor justifioa o insuces . de duas perfurações por terem atravessado planos de falha, e 'de outra por ter enoontrado o intervalo produtor estruturalmente mais baixo, is to basêado 'em oorrelações detalhadas de perfis elétrioos, horizonte a horizonte, onde pràtioamente não foi oogitada a hipótese de inoon formidades.
Eo J. Bauer mostra-nos umq falha oom 200m de rejeito senSe interseotaâa por outra fâlha (mais ~ova), oom 600m d~ rejeito e direção NE, esta oom uma inOlina9ão de apenas '42 0 0 No oruzamento a destas falhas teria sido furado o Qe-I-BA, oortando assim ambos os 'planos, interpretação a nosso ver um tanto ousada, se bem que geome . ' trioamente razo~vel o ", .
--_ ... - .....
Encaninhamos a V.S. um relatório sébre a geologia da Grea do Qua rerá, copocifidatenento da área dos poqoo Q-l, 2, 3 o 4, O relatório tam weou-se nos dados adicionais dos poços de Qo-3 é 4 os quais ainda não tinhan sido perfurados quando fei feito o princire relatório preliminar do autoria do geólogo Manoel Medeiros. Foram utilizadas também as novas interpretações síguicas do Setex.
Nossas interpretações indicam que o arenito produtor do Qe-1 foi falhado em Qo-2 @ 3, sendo perfurado om Qo-% porem enbaixo do contasto do óleo o água, O próximo pôgo (400 m WU do Qu-l) deve encontrar © arenito uu-ma posição estrutural favevivci. --=- Nos achamos que as asomolias geolegicais como, a falta de grandes seoções nos poços Qe-l, 2 e 5 poderiam ser explicadas mais simplesmente pelas falhas que cortam os poços @ não pelas discordâncias brascas. | Usando dessa hipstese ds falhas, tenes rasão para aevéditer que outros blocos de falhas adjasentes tonha possibilidades de conter o arenito produtor do Ge-l.
No relatório, duas lotações de "outpost” são propostas, Devido / que existem duas hipóteses pare explicar as anomalias geológicas na áreaçeu gerimos que o Setex considere estas locações antes que sejam liberadas para perfurar pela Diviges.
No fim do relatório foi incluído uma discursão do novo “high density" perfil do “Digmeter". Intarprotanos ôsces perfis do Qe-3 e 4 e chg games a conclusão que êsse novo perfil pode nos dar informação muito valio-sa para ser usada no programa de desenvolvimento. Recomendamos que éste per £42 soja foitó em todos pogos do “outetep”.
BINISEO 
.' ....... . •• u ••• " ............. . :ft==-= ..... ••• ... ' ............................. . ,. ..... ' .....• ..... . . J . . . . ~ e, 1.1~ • • ,. . . . . A ..... io4t; . . . . . • i_ t • • • • • ' • •• ' . . . . . . . . . . ~~' •• , .' •• ~.1~ • • . . ~ « ....... ~.i., .. . .... ..... ........•. ..
~. ' . & \ • Three outstep wells, located approximately 500 meters south, cast and north of qu=l failed to extend the productive arca of the Tlhas sand of the discovery well in these directions, Qu=2 and Qu=3 enoccountered a major fault which was responsible for the absense of the ofl sand in these wells, Qe-4 Grilled the correlative of the Quel of] sand at a depth 120 metera lower than predicted, and dencnstrated that the s.sdnd-“ás * well developed but water saturated in the immediate well area.
PURPOSE OF REPORT: ‘The report was proparcá in order to illustrate the detailed geological conditions which exist in the general Qe-) discovery area. The interpretations were based upon newer well data and Setex seisnic revisicas.
The accompanying map and cross-sections show the trend of future development in as far as outetep drilling is concerned. In afdition, tuo outpest locations have been recommended to test possible extensions of the Qe-h of] sand om adjacent fault block structures.
AGENQULEDGSMENTS: The writer wishes to express his gratitude to Setex seis mologists Waldener Assis and Carlos Fernandes for their enlightening dis cussion of the fault systems which are evident on the seismic sections of the area. Palcontologist Rolf Weber has contributed much time and effort toward the resolution of the geological problems which were encountered. Finally, duo epedit is given to Diviges geologist Mancel Nedeires, as his preliminary interpretations of the faults form the basis of the structural analysis of the present report.
INZRODUSTION site geological coluna (aee Perfil Compósto or Nester Log). The Sorual sedimentary covtion in the Quererá arca consiste of approximately 3000 meters of coarse and fine elastics of Jurassic ané Cre-taseous ages. Limestones occur in minor quantities. In comparison «ith / thick shale sections im the Reconcavo Basin, the formations in the querer’ wells contain a high percentage of coarse elastics or sandstones. ctresigraphio Sejationship: ‘the formation uncontormabiy overlies the basement complex. The upper contact, although shown as en abrupt change from maroon Shales of the Aliança to sandstones of the Sergi, appears to be com formable. comresasios she Aliança is readily correlateabic on the c-logs and = ly the predominance of maroon sediments. Correlation between Qe-3 and Qez-2 is some what difficult because of apparent faulting and lithological changes of the Aliença in the latéer well. 1 ad Geen DPenethhieistens Abbas She Micas actual cu attendee 4
< • BEiilnlos The Sergi formation consists primarily of white te Might gray, fine to coarse-grained sandstones. Thin, interbeds of gray-green and marom shales occur throughout the section, as do very minor amounts of yellowish limestone. . Qi Do Semel peewee 100 actos o bicha te tha Geesosk vma SA E WED DD ED E O E E aes es OE eS ee ee Oe ea shales occur throughout the section, as do very minor amounts of yellouish limestone. . Thickness: ‘the Sergl averages 150 meters in thickness in the Quererá area. This thickness is similar to that of surface outerops measured by Carles ta «cai a uma ca oO tira Geese Biased | Thickness: ‘The Sergi averages 150 meters in thickness in the Quererá area. This thickness is similar to that of surface outerops measured by Carles Walter along the southwestern sargin of the Tucano Basin.
SERATIGRAPREI 
ARENITO. CINZA CLARO, FINO A MEDlO. CAL CI FERO, ARGILOSO, POROSIDADE REGULAR , f OLHELHO , CINZA ESVERDEADO ESCURO, MA RROM, CARB ., SILTICO FISSIL, SILTITO, vERl.E OLIVA, CALCIF E RO; CALCA REO, CINZA AC AS TANHAUO , DURO
-_., ..... a., .• ... r __ . . . . . . . . . . u. .. ... ca fonsils were identified in the lover Candeias type shales fumediataly above the Sergi. Gerrelation: ‘The Sergi is correlateable on the e-logs of Qe-3, Qex-l and er E we ND eee ee O eee ee EN E NE Oe O42 and Gus Possibilities: The Sergi is a major petrolewn reservoir in the Recôncavo Basin. Although a number of wells have penetrated the Sergi sandstones in the Tucano Basin, the results have not been significant. No petroleum shows were observed in the Sergi sandstones in Qe-3 or Qex-l. Re sidual oil staining was reported in probable Sergi sandstones in Qex-2: Im the Recôncavo Basin, the key to the cussess of Sergi cil dis-coveries is related to the age of faulting. Studies of prolific Sergl il fields as Dom João and Agua Grande indicate that the structures were fornd. at em early date, probably during the time of Candeias deposition. ITAPARICA FORMATION:
. ...
The distinctive changes in the e-log resistivity curve which ser ve to differentiate the formation into three menbors in many wells in the Reconcavo Basin appear also on the e-logs of Qe-3 and Qex-l, but the break at the top of the afiddle Candeias is not as sharp in these wells due to the
: I . t " ; t _ ; . . ' l _ 1· I r " _ · i ' ; I 1 J . i . 11 t t , . . f ~ 1·1 . t , f :
1·1 t f : . ê ! I ! l , .
1·1 f : . ê ! I ! l , . . r ! ! . r . ' I '
: I " ! ~ I f J . . . I ! r ~ - I 1 r ' 1 , I da Ena Mithelogr: is formation ic composed of interbedded, fine to medium - grained, light gray to brown sandstones, greenish-gray and maroon shales, and olive-gray siltstones. Thin-bedded, gray-brom Limestones cocur at / random throughout the formation, but are more prominent im the basal part ef the esetion. y The formation in the Querera welle contains on umucusiiy high percentage of coarse clastios compared vith the tine equivalent in many areas in the Reconcave Basin. Shigkmeae: 4 composite thickness of 1050 meteoro was estimated for the Ilhas formation, based on correlations between the Querera wells and the determination of faulted sections in thea, Stretigraphio Relationships ‘The Ilhas is conformable with the overlying São Sebastiiic.
POToentago OF COGPSES GLABTISS COMpaTOS GAs WAS VANS SquiTALSHT Em aay areas in the Recôncavo Basin. Shigkmeae: 4 composite thickness of 1050 meteoro was estimated for the Ilhas formation, based on correlations between the Querera wells and the determination of faulted sections in then. Stretigraphio Relationships ‘The Ilhas is conformable with the overlying São Sebestião.
Ostracod studies by Weber and Staff reveal that the Ilhas can be divided inte an upper and lower member. In the Querera wells, the lower / and upper mesbers are separated by a hiatus or palco gap because fossils pertaining to the time equivalent of the São Paulo-Catu section sre absent. According to Weber, the lower Ilhas (basal part) in Querera is equivalent to the basal Ilhas of euch wolle as Se~k, ete., tut younger than the lover part of the Tihes in walle which have a thick lover has, such as in Nom peão and Jenuipe, ete. | Sorrelationt The interbedded ehales in the Ilhas formation produco ex cellent e-log markers which are consistent throughout the Querera area. The enclesed e-logo show the numerical assignment given to the markers by Divi, gee im order to facklitate correlations ané to Geteruine the asount of / miesing section in wells cut by faulte.
O42 and Gas Possibilities: The Ge-l oil discovery has shown that the Ilhas formation in the Tucano Basia has the same potential as a petroleum gene-rator as does the time equivalent in the Recôncavo Basin. However, the high Glastic ratio of the formation 4m the Tucano Basia Andicates, that . the thicker sandstone reservoirs will likely be flushed, and saturated with / salt water. .
- • ed that the sand extends at least as far north as this well, and being better developed (11.5 meters of porosity) in qe-* than in Go-l, one can assume that the sand will ex$end some Gintonço north and weet of both wells.
Correlations between Qe-1 and Q-4 show that an unconfornity exists about 40 to 80 meters stratigraphically above the producing sone (see E-logs and erose-scotion BS" of Féiha nº 2). thie unconferaity may have cut down to the producing horizon in areas south and southuest & Qe-1 (ses map), and thus lisit the of] possibilities. Consideration should also be given to the possibility that the @e-k oil eané às lenticular, as pointed cut by DMirceu Leite in thie repust of the area, and may not have great areal extent for this reason. etn araasvTrãa Porm avTou
· ............. - Stratigraphic Relationship: The formation conformably overlies the Ilhas im all wells drilled in the Querera area, Gopreletion: ‘the formation is easily correlated from one well to another en the bacia of L4thetacs. fanned) contonê ond eveottant o.tae aeckoees. on the basis of lithology, fossil content and excellent e-log markers. 042 end Gee Ponsiniisticas Because of the extrencly high clustio ratio and lack of adequate cap rock, little importance is given to the formation as am economic petroleum horizon. “aDrraAT Weber avTrns
/ E" TO TEFTEES TUNG SESS Cw WO 27% DOT TE eee EH WAS querera area. Stratigraphic Helationship: The formation unconformably overlies the São Sebastião, aná effectively masks underlying structures. It also,;forms the cana eee ma thee asma she formation unconiormadiy Overiies tae dao Sebastião, aná effectively maske underlying structures. It also,forss the surface cover in the area. Correlation: ‘he unit is correlated in the wells on a lithological basis. 942 end Ges Possibilitioss The Marizal has no apparent petroleum possibi-GENERAL: The Querera structure has been defined by geophysical studios as being a narrow but long, northeast-southwest trending horst block. A major mormal fault with a relatively large throw is the principal structural / feature along the western edge of the horet. This fault probably conneste with the surface fault west of Pataiba, shown on Disbrow's gualogical map ef the Tucano Basin.
The eastern edge of the horet às not as clearly delineated as the sestern margin, in that, instead of being bordered by a single major fault, the eastern edge may be displaced by a series of irregular trending faults, some of which cut the structue obliquely.
Divigeo's interpretations indicate that the major fault aleng/ the western edge of the Querera structure crosses Qe-l, Qe-2 and Qe-3. Its extension inte the Qen-i and Qua? well às cleo iuplied. In all 8 probabi~ lity, the fault trace forms the ncar-horizontal anomaly on the seiesic 8 / eroas-section of line 7-RL-175, which has been interpreted as being an um conformity by some authore of geological reports of the Querera arca. For the purpose of this report, the structural discussion is li máted to the fault systems and unconformities in Qu=] and afjacent 8 deve~ lepment welle.
EANES “As Good e-log correlations between qo), 2 and & chow thet apprg mimately 180 motors of upper Tlhas are nicuing in Qu=l at a depth of 1390 moterea. A etudy of the dip-metor Jog of thie well and the overall etructe-ral anaiguis of the area rovecis that the aiscing section was caused by a fault which eute the well. the section which contains c-log narker noi is absent.
..
STRUCTURE
..... ., ...... a I ee es ANN eee PP E ee eee The fault cute Ge-3 ab basement depth and Gisplases the lower Tihes against the erystaliine rock at that point. Although the final report of Qe~l shows a thin section of lower Candeias to be present at the bottom of the well, paleontologiat Weber*s re-exanination of the fossils ‘inéiieg tes that the presence of the lower Candeias is very questionable. (Verbal coast anti ams Ta qu=2, the faukt has Giepleced the upper Tiheas against Cams Geies sediments, and has faulteé cut the Ge-2 of) sandstone. The encunt of stratigraphic throw is approximately 590 meters, similar to that in @-1. a Qe-3, the fault crosses the eek at 1945 meteoro, and has rg duced the thickness of the upper Ilhas to 240 meters in this well compared to a normal composite thickness of approximately 900 meters for the area. The amount of stratigraphic throw 4s essentially the sane as the throw in Qe-l and Qe-2, considering that the thros in the iatter wells can be adjust ed samewhat by varying the basement depth in the dowsthrows Uleck of the feult.
Ry using depth control pointe in qe-l, 2 and 3, the resolution of a three-point protien of an inchined plane in apace indicates 8 that / Fault "8" strikes E 45° E and digo 45° mu, Interpretations of the Gipnoter log of Qe~3 (sce appendix) indicates that the fault plane strikes E 50° B and dips 42° Nu. The writer chose the latter attitude as being more repre contativo of the attitude of the fault plane at the level of the quel off cand as 4% conforas more closciy to the general direction of the fault = / trase shown on Scheidt's contour map (720-3-h) of a Ilhas horisen. ‘fhe interpretations in this report imply that Fault "B"ie younge: than Fault “4”, There is no apparent evidense of an initial sovenent ecour
.. .... ... ua. I.'l.,..,, ~ -_ ............. , .. te1~.~-.J~ ".alt.! • . . . . . . f' ..... . . . . . ., .. _ .. ---I.
.. _ .. ---I. '\1 : : . ' J.
A Biatus or paleo gap separates the lower and upper Ilhas. Whether this unconfermity represents a period of non-deposítion or erosion cannot be ascertained with the limited amount of control available at the present time.
Am erosional unconfornity exists 40 to 60 meters stratigraphical ly above the Qe=) ofl sand. Ite regional significance has not been deter-mined. Locally, the unconformity may cut-down deep enough to completely erode the producing horison.
The shallew water type of deposition that coscurreá in the area, coupicá with periods of minor uplift probably created auall unconfornítios àm other parte of the section, but they may bear no significaemse as far as the petroleum possibilities are concerned. The São Sebastião was gently beveled by crosion before the deposition of Marisal sedinents.
....... u._ ...........
RESONENDATIONS
,ia ............... "J»I.~ • • f I _ ...... _ ......... aa tlPIU_
... im proposing these locations, the writer considers that oil / migrated inte and was trapped within the Qu-1 oil sand before large scale faulting tock place. Therefore, the fault block on which location 53-L-
... ~_.
... ~_.
EJN/msu. 
REFERENCES 
ESCLOSURES
G24 seale in feet 121.000 
.• _. I) . . . . . . . . . --111 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .. __ ._ ............. ~. - - - . :I
._ ............. ~.
.. ..... .. - .. ...
.. ... ..... · l / ., . . . . . __ tI. - " .
. . . . IA . . ~_IIIId •.. ..-lt.alllã ... ... -I . . 1Iw1 . . 0 •• 1_. h. ' .. , _11._- .. _ • •. · . . . . . . . 1 . . . . -_ ... ~_ .. , ......... L • •
-_ ... ~_ .. , ......... L • • The upper (7) Candeias unit shows excellent strustural dip. The dárection of this @ip varios alághtiy from that of the 5 dip arrows below 1800 meters. This may be due to a amall uncsonforsity of simply te daposi-tional conditions.
The Ilhas formation is composed mostly of interbedded sandstones and shales. The shale beds produce good structural dips which, in general, ere oriented in the same direction. Crose-bedding, channeling and fore-set bedding are also recorded. ;
..... - ... -. te
............. --_ ....... . . . 11. la _,la " a __
" Divâgeo*s interpretation of the new, high density dipucter log shows that the geologist has available a highly useful and important teel. The log will not only be help ful to determine faulte and uncor-formities, but it will tell us auch about the depositional history of the formations. Intérpretations of the leg, coupled with sedimentation studies, will help to resolve many of the stratigraphic problems in the basin. We recommend that the leg be rum at least in all of the develep-ment outstep wells.
CONCLUSIONS 
€,9,8,6,5,3.8,1,0,7.
WEST 
WEST 
wESí
AG (Baur TEMPO - PRE-SÃO SEBASTIÃO
