The Cedro area lies approximately 3.5 kilemstera cast of the igua Grande field. Interest in the ares was generated by soisnic studies which delineated a dome-like structure ef reaseg able size.
' ....... • , ..... aJl1I
' .......
After the sbandonencat of Cé-2, the decision was nado to drill a repetition well 80 meters SE of Cd-2. This well drilled te a total depth of 2261 meters, and entered directly inte the Seg ef from the lover Candeias. Ne significant oil shows were encounter cê. and the wilh ems chandeneé cc a Orr hele. SC A JI typical ef the formations in thie part of the basin. The São Sebastião is cempesed of predominantly sediua to coerse-grained sendstenes, ané thin interbeds of «halo and ldmeetene. The average thiekness is 300 acters.
.......
The Candeias formation io composed of a dominant abalo section whieh can be divided inte lover, uíddio and upper menbero em the basis of calcareous content, paleontology and distinetive Changes in the resistivity curve ef the e-leg. There is a conside rable variation in thickness of the formation ia the Gedre welle.
In Câ-l and Cá-2 the Candeias is approximately 45 meters thick. Over 600 acters of Candeias sediments were Grilled in Cd-2R. The anomalous thiekening ef the Candeias im this well can be explained by contemporanceus deposition and fault asevezent. Aw illustrated in the geolegical section of Folha nº 1, the Candee is thicker en the domthromm side of Fault “A”, The reduced Canácias section in Cd-2 was caused by eblique-slip mevenent along Fault “BD”, The interpretations of Folha nº 2 present a simpler pig ture. In either ease, however, the dewn-thrown block contadas a thicker section of Candeias compared te the same rock unit on the hágh block ef Cé-1. The goslogical section of Folha nº 5 shows the
...
The basal part ef the Candeias formation is nermally marked by the eceurrence of the “A” Zone sandstones. This wait is approximately 22 metere thick in Cd-l, and exhibits exeellent re-~ servoir charecteristioso The Itaparica ané Sergi formatãoas were drilled in Cdci, and are typically developed, The Itaparica, the "A" Zone, and the upper part of the Sergi are missing by faulting in C6-2B.
The Cedro structure bas bees depictod by <ceienic af being a sual] deme, separated fron the Água Grande trend by dewa-faulted blocks. The results ef Cé-2R2 show that this strusture is cut by a normal fault whieh created a stratigraphie displasenest of approximately 250 acters along the fault plane. Am interpreta-tiem of the dip-mcter of Gé-2R ândicates that the strike ef this fault (Fault “ar) as B 50º E, with a dip of approximately 60º 55, | A southwest extension ef this strike across seismic line 6-R1-145 euts between shot points 3437 and 3438 where fault disturbance is indicated on the seismie 42 section.
The difficulty in presenting only one interpretation of the structural conditions between Cd-l, Cd-28 and Gde2 às due te the fact that mo directional control is available fren Cd=-2, the blew-eut well. For this reasca, two structural interpretations are prescatedo
......... .,..
.........
The small index map em Fólha nº 3 shows that the princi pal fault aligument in the Codro area parallele the major fault features along the sast side of the Agua Grande ficld, This is a significant relatienship because in both arcas movenent along the faults ocourved at an early date-during or shortly after Candeias dspesition. Enclosed structure aleng the up-threwn side of such fault systeas offer eptiaum trapping conditions for hydrocarbons that have migrated from the Canácias qhales into adjacent sand bodies. im the event thet Cd=-5 enconbters oil in the "4" Jone er the Sergi, consideration should be given te wake a directional well of Cd-2R for the purpose of completing it às à producer 4a either reserveir om the up-throm side of Fault "A".
L BCC 14 EM ” DATIC iS a.. .. fate relatório mestra duao interpretações para explicar a coorrência de hidrecarbenctos no Cd-2, Uma supõe que éste poço pa paço, Sade rp Na minado im dica que o desviou mais ds que estã indicado na leitera do Teteo, e encontrou a Zona "A" no bloco alte da falha, Asreditamos ser nais razoável a segunda hipstese muito embora não concordo com as leituras de Totce. JÊ tenes evidências em outros poços nes quais o Tetes parece não ter funcionado satisfa toriamento, inclusivo no último póço de Santana (2a-1) onde o dog vio indicado pele Tetee não ultrapassou 5º enquanto o perfil dire-cional da Sohlunborgor montra desvios até 13°.
No case do o Cd~5 dar Slee ma Zona “A”, provenes que pg le menos 8 poços adicionais drenarão a cotrutura,
00/1 vávigoo a/0. 
In th18 report the autbor Mr ~ . Da_r • et tbat the .18ain, "AlI aand in drJ' bole Od-2R-:BA oan be explainec.t b7 a nonaal raul t cuttina the .el1 in the upper 8erl1 thua plao1ns the lower Candeia. In tbe .el1 in tault oont.ot witb the trun-cated Serp. ata that 4r7 hole Cd-2-BA The author turtber a out when the clr111 blt penetrated the -Ali sone OI' wh1ch bl nearí lt.,aotual1y 4eYlated .eyeral hundred _tera, oroa8ed the 11M tault plane lnto the "A" aon ot the 04-1-tault b1ook. Seta ceoloaiat M. Lane who a180 4etal1ed the po1ogy ot th1a area ap-ee. witb th authora tlr.t o no1ualon as 1 t 18 obyloualy a IIOre.1 1. 10&10&1 ex.p1anatlon. Setu now haa an up to date 8Ub8urtao. po10&1oa1 _p t the C c.tro area.
MVI/dl
