Ref.: Geology of the Lucindo Area, Sta Catarina (continued) 
Please find herain the report "Geology of the Lucindo Area, Santa Catarina, (continued)", prepared by the geolog1st Guntram Kremer.
The Lucindo area was first investigated by Mr. !remar in 1957, when he wrote the "Geological report of the Canoinhas-Valões Porto União Area" (DEBP n 96); l.ter, in August 1959, Mr. Swan completed a detailed work in the surrounded Lucindo area and presented the report "Geology of the Luc1ndo Area, Sta Catarina", DEBP n 154). The enclosed Mr. Kremer report, was delivered to the Distric~ in December 1959, and represents a more detailed work of the Lucindo area than that he first made; yet it is extended to the north and northeast of the area mapped by Swan.
The objectives of Mr. Kremer assignments were to map the faults of the Lucindo area to obtain structural condition for Gil entrapment. The investigations revealed that the regional dip of the Permian strata is to SW and many faults exist in the area with a predominant. atrike to NW, NNW and NNE. The Swanta "Lueindo Fault" pointa more northeastward and representa the eastern f1ank of the down-throW-n Lucindo Faulted Block, which is of limited dimensions and it is ti1ted southwardly. The area shows intrusive activities with increaaed development to the weat, toward Serra dos Borgea.
Conoerning to the petroleum possibilities, smal1 aocumulation might be expected on the southern f1anks of the NW striking faults and on the dow.n-thrown LucindoBlock. But, Lucindo Block is of o such a sma11 size that considerab1e migration toward it ia unlikely. More favourable condition$ for oil accumu1ation are expected, in Mr. Kremer's opinion, to the east, on the upl~ft Rio do Liso area, where a detailed investigation ia sugges,ted. - Comparing Mr. Kremer's and Mr. Swan's mapa, it was observed that many difference in e1evations and different stratigraphics topa ex1st in the neighbouring areas of 'both surveys, showing Mr. Kremer'a map higher values than those. of Swan's. It is the oase to wonder whether Mr. Swan has made m stake s toward the edges of his survey or Mr. Kremer , starting with higher figures, has not carried them into the Swan's mapped. ares. When one: match such different maps, faults precede any structural interpretation, as occurs with Mr. Kremer's fauli, limiting to the wes t of hia mapped Lucindo Block. This fau1t, if really exist, it ia however emphasized by two different readings for the top of Teresina in the same spot, the Kremer's station L-30 - Swan's G-15. Station L-30, reads 721 m and station G-15, resds 704m, both readings corresponding to the top of Teresina, at the same spot.
Distrito de Exploração da Bacia Sedimentar do Paraná Page INTRODUCTION • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • 1 Purpose of Report 1 • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • Loca tion of Area 1 • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • Object and Me thod of Survey 1 • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • Previous Investigations • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • 1 Acknowledgements • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • 2 GEOGRAPHY 2 • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • 4 • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • STRATIGRAPHY 2 • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . STRUCTURE 2 PETROLEUM INDICATIONS . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3 GEOLOGIC HISTORY . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3 PETROLEillil POSSIBILITIES • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • 4 CONCLUSIONS AND RECOM!I!3NDATIONS • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • 4 REFERENCES • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • 5 APPENDIX • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • Purpose of Report: At the end of November 1959, TG-ll was assigned to continue the structural survey of the Lucindo Area, northern Santa Catarina, especial1y of the adjacent parts to the west and north of the area previously mapped by A.G. Swan. The assignment was carried out during the month of November, 1959. This report presents the results of the continued survey in the Lucindo Area.
Location of Area: The working area contains about 130 square kilometers and ia centered approximate1y by Longitude 50º 30 ' W and Latitude 26º 30 ' S.
Object and Method of Survey :
The main object was to map the fau1ts of the area . Tbe survey was carried out in detail, using the plane table method. The whole month of November was spent in the field. Seven working days in the fie1d were lost, because of continuous, heavy rain .
The fo11owing previous investigations were made in the report area : Swan made a detai1ed stratigraphical study of the eastern and southern parts of the Lucindo Area. Therefore , the writer refers to Swan ' s report , and presents no stratigraphical data herein.
The topographical work of this assignment was done by topo graphers Adolpho A. Dittrich and José A. Ogibowski .
In his report on the southern and eastern parts of the Lucindo Area A.G.Swan (2) gives detailed stra~igra.phical data. The writer refers here to this reporte
STRUCTURE •
The continuation of structural survey of the Lucindo Area pro duced the following facts, which are listed below:
1. The regional dip of Permian strata points SW. The dip shows generally less than one degree of inclination. 2. The structural pattern of the Lucindo Area is dominated by NW, WNW and NNE striking faults. 3. AlI northwestward striking faults show uplifted southern flanks, with the exception of two faults in the extreme northern part of the report area. The Monte Castelo Fault Area, to the east of the Lucindo Area shows similar structural features (1). As intrusive activity seems to have been most intensive in the southern part and t 'o the south of the Lucindo Area, the uplifted southern flanks of the NW striking faults might be explained by the intrusion of northward pointing diabase sills.
GEOGRAPHY
S T R A T I G R A P H Y
STRUCTURE
4. AlI fauIts in the southern and central part of the Lucindo Area are to a greater or lesser degree filled with diabase. 5. The so-called "Lucindo Fault" of A.G.Swan (2) points more north eastward and representa the eastern flank of the downthrown Lucindo Fault Block. The Lucindo Fault Block does not extend farther northward t~an to the latitude of 262 30 ' S t where it dies out. There is no connection with the Santa Leocadia Fault, mentioned by the \vriter in a previous report (1). Only parta of the eastern fault of the Lucindo Block seem not to be filled wi th dia base. The Lucindo Block is tilted southwestward and shows a downward displacement of about 60 meters in its southern part and about 40 meters in its northern parte The contours to the eaat and west of the Lucindo Blóck are practically connecting. The whole block shows a small areal extent. 6. The Serra Zézinho and Serra da Mula dikes connect with the Serra dos Borges intrusive aren. 7. The region to the west of the mapped area shoVls increasing intrusive activity.
No petroleum indications were encountered within the mapped area. An asphalt seep occurs in joints of·Morro Pelado fm in the Serra dos Borges, about 4 kilometers to t~e west of the mapped area.
The writer concurs with A.G.Swan ' s conception of the geologic history in the Lucindo Area (2).
PETROLEUM INDICATIONS GEOLOGIC HISTORY Small updip accumulations of oil might be expected on the southenl flanks of alI NW striking faults of major magnitude and within the area of the downthrown Lucindo Block. The Lucindo Block area is however of such a small size, that conaiderable migration of oil within thia block ia unlikely
CONCLUSIONS AND RECO~~~NDATIONS
The northemmost NW trending faults of the mapped area are not intruded by dia base. It ahould be interesting to aee if these faults connect eastward with the uplifted "Rio do Liso" area, where the writer expects more favourable conditions for an accumulation of oil. Therefore a detailed investigation of these fau1ts in eastern direction is advocated. (1) Kremer, G. - Geological Report on the Canoinhas-Valões Porto União Area, Northern Santa Catarina. DEBSP Report Nº 96 t February 1957.
REFERENCES
