Dear Sir,
Herein we submitted the geologic report of TG-13 which was done in the Lucindo area - South of Canoinhas, near tbe erosional edge of the lava scarp \rith the principal purpose to map any structural feature which could be projected south westwards under the lava covered areá in order to properly se1ecting the eastern Tangará 1ocation in an area of maximum sedimentation of sandstones (See Bauer Report).
The dominant NNW trending ridges of diabase, most of which correspondent to fau1ts with throw of about 100 m were mapped. The only important fault trends approximately N-S is Lucindo fault. As a result the main objective of the survey was not be reached. However, further field work it is necessary, in the north side of tbe map-area, to investigate the structura1 relationship between Lucindo and Santa Leocadia faults. In the area a strat test was se1ected for the 1960 exploratory program using the field information obtained by TG-13.
GF/os file
DEBSP-327/
Respectfully
GEOLOGY OF THE LUCINDO AREA SANTA CATARINA ============================~================
Distrito de Exploração da Bacia Sedimentar do Paraná
By: Arthur G. Swan
Ponta Grossa-Paraná August, Recent subsurface correlations by Bauer(l) in central Santa Catarina suggested the presence of a submarine high during upper Pennsylvanian time along which maximum sedimentation of sandstones in the Guatá group could be expected~ The axis of this sandstone development trends SSW from the area of the town of Canoinhas, through Serra dos Borges and under the lavas of tbe Serra Geral fm (ref. Index Map). It was therefore proposed to make a geological survey close to the erosional edge of the lavas with the purpose of finding structurea which could be projected southwest wards into the area of interest. This report presents the results of this suvey. It is accompanied by the map "Geology of the Lucindo Area" (Plste 1) and by a structursl cross-section (Plate 2).
Location of Area The area of work contains about 120 square km, lies 30 km south of Canoinhas and ia centered approximately by Longitude 502 25 t W and Latitude 26Q 35' S.
Object and Nature of Survey The principal object of the survey was to map "the faults of the area that may be encountered near the lava scarp and which may be related possibly to the aims of the proposed locations of Bauer's report(l)tt. To this end the survey was carried out, in-so-far as possible, in detail. Special attention was paid to the contacts in the Rio do Rasto group and to the finding of marker horizons in the upper part of the Teresina fm.
Numerous picadas were cut, especially in tbe ravines that were thought likely to expose the lower part of the Morro Pelado fm and its contact with the Serrinha fm. These, although often occurring in relatively clean cultivated aress, are usually choked witb debria from the cleared fields and are covered with dense underbrush. Picada work along their courses was slow and often geologically un-rewarding.
No aereal photo-coverage is available. Topographic control was acheived by plane-tabling on scales of 1:12,500 and 1:25,000. Altimeters were used to determine elevations in a few places where horizontal control was not important, e.g. on near-vertical scarps, and for establishing an elevation reference point based on a bench mark in Canoinhas (Railroad Station El. 765.47m). Approximately 1 month was spent in the field.
Previous Investigations Kremer(2), in 1956, made a semi-detailed and reconnaissance survey of the regional between Porto União and Canoinhas. The erosional edge of the lavas falls near the southern limit of his work, and except in the Serra dos Borges area, does not form part of the map-area proper. This is mentioned because Serra dos Borges lies only 12 km N of the Serra L~indo Area and it is the writer's opinion that the two areas together form part of a larger inter connected zone of intrusive activity.
Acknowledgements The writer was capably assisted in the field by geologist Alaor Altafin. The plane-table and altimeter work was done by topographer José Ogibowski who was later joined by topographer Afonso Chukewiski.
The eastern part of the Serra Lucindo Area is well served by unimproved r oads. Some of these follow the projected bed of an un completed pr vate railroad. Large ranges of hills, not known locally by any one name, trend N-S through its western part and are not easilyacessible. Theyare covered by forest with dense bamboo and taquaral undergrowth. Relief ia high and reaches a maximum of about 300 m, with numerous scarps and deep ravines.
GEOGRAPHY
- 2 -
Diurnal temperature variation during the months of June and July is high, often ranging from -5 Q to 25 Q C. Morning ground mists are heavy but these are usually dispersed b,y 9.30 ame Three consecutive days of work were lost on aecount of steady rain. The nearest hotel accomodation for the party was in the town of Canoinhas; this involved about 2 hours of driving per day to and from work when roads were in good condition.
Strata of the Botucatú, Morro Pelado, Serrinha and Teresina fms outcrop in the area. They are all intruded by diabase. Basaltie rocks of the Serra Geral fm overlie the Botucatu. The section is as follows:
Thiekness 210 - 240 m (after Kremer(2». Teresina fm
Only the upper part of this fm was mapped. This sequenee, about 110 m thick, is comprised of a uniform greenish-grey shalfey siltstone, with thin limestone and chert bede whieh form two local markers near the upper contact of the !m. The shaley siltstone is made up of gently cross-laminated irregular interbeds, generally lesa than 1 em thick, of dark grey shale and light grey siltstone. In unaltered outcrops it is hard and massive; where weathered, it parts readily into th1n plates. The lower 25 m of the section is predominantly shale and weathers conspicuously into small flakes. One marker bed forms the upper contact of the fm. It consists of a 10 - 20 cm thick bed of fossiliferous oolitic chert, ledge-forming, whieh overlies a 4 m section of silty shale with about 50 cms of massive, dense, cherty limestone at its base. Between the two, smaller discontinuous chert beds occar.
The second marker bed occurs about 20 m below the top of the fm and consists of a 50 cm thick dense, oolitic lime stone bed. The siltstone section immediately above and below th1s bed contains large elongate eilty limestone eoneretions.
STRATIGRAPHY Other cherts occur below these two markers but insuf ficient control does not allow their correlation. The upper contact of the Teresina fm is placed at the top of the uppermost chert and limestone bed. It marks a distinct lithological break: the basal Serrinha strata occurring above it are more homogeneous than the Teresina, are devoid of co~spicuous cross-laminations, and in road aections they acquire a pale green, sometimes maroon, weathering colour.
Serrinha fm Thickness : about 126 m
The Serrinha conformably overlies the Teresina fm. It comprises a sequence of greenish-grey, well-laminated silt atone and silty ahale, with intercalated beds of ailt,y sand atone which are generally less than 3 m thick. In unaltered outcrop the colour is darker and the siltstones and ahales are hard and often calcareous; in ravines they form numerous small waterfalls.
Its lower contact in this area has been described above and is placed at the top of the uppermost Teresina chert. Its upper contact has hitherto been based on colour phanges only. In this area, at Stations G 15, G 119, G 121, G 46, and G 87, a possible marker bed which separates the lithological sequences of the Serrinha and Morro Pelado, consista of a 1 1/2 m zone of chert nodules and siliceous (cherty) sandstones which occur in well-laminated grey Serrinha siltstone with fine green shale interealations. This is overlain by maroon, massive, conchoidal-breaking shales of the Morro Pelado with large ailty limestone concretions at its base. In weathered outcrop, as at G 15, the nodules are not present but thin ledges of siliceous and cherty sandstone, up to 15 cma thick, occur in pale green shaley siltstones. This latter section at G 15, is incomplete.
Morro Pelado fm Thickness: about 195 m
Thia fm lies conformably on the Serrinha. It comprises maroon, green and yellow ahales and shaley siltstones with lenticular interbeds of argillaceous sandstone which are predominant in its upper parte The latter are usually fine- "grained, often rounded and frosted, generally well-bedded and sometimes croas-bedded. One of them forms a line of scarps 8 m high on the west side of the valley of the Rio Vermelho. The ailtatone and shale sequence is predominantly massive and is characterized by a conchoidal fracture. It contains occasional hard discontinuous calcareous layers. The lower contact is placed at the siliceous sandstone and chert zone, already described, which marks the upper limit of typical Serrinha. Its upper contact is not well expoaed. It is usually coincident with the appearance of a vertical Botucatu scarp, below which a small swampy bench of Morro Pelado forma the headwaters of small streams that are fed from springs at the base of the Botucatu. The contact is unconformable and there exists a re-worked zone in which sediments of [orro Pelado origin are mixed with Botucatu sanda. No basal Botucatu conglomerates are presente
Thickness: 45 - 80 m (after Kremer(2». Botucatu fm
The Botucatu unconformably overlies the Morro Pelado. Its thickness was not measured but in places it forms scarps which attain heights of over 45 m. It comprises brown, fine to medium-grained, well-stratified, thin-bedded sandstone which is silty and argíllaceous in its lower parte The larger grains are sub-rounded and frosted and they are sorted into fine regular stratifications. This, together with the presence of regular bedding and occasional truncated torrential cross-beds, indicates a predominantly aqueous sedimentary environment.
The lower conta ct of the Botucatu has been described in the discussion of the Morro Pelado fm. Its upper contact with the Serra Geral was no~ seen.
Serra Geral lavas in central Santa Catarina when the regional dip of Palaeozoic strata is to the order of 12 m per Km (0 240') WSW. A series of closely spaced rugged NNW-trending ridges pass through the western part of the area and are made up of diabase dikes which in places are over 250 m thick. These dikes para~lel the erosional edge of the lava and are believed to extend 12 Kms to the northwest to connect with the Serra dos Borges area of intrusive activity. The youthful topography of the ridges that they form denotes only relatively recent remova1 of the lava cover and implies that they were true feeder dikes.
Three such diabase ridges are mapped. The eastemmost two are involved in faulting, which is probably quite complex. The . northernpart of the Serra da Mula diabase ridge forms a reveree fault with displacement of about 102 m. It is cut by the transverse normal Lucindo fault, trending N15ºE, with displacement of about 90 m. Together they bound a downthrown wedge, here referred to as the Serra da Mula fault block, which is tilted to the· SW. No evidence of a limiting structure on its northern side was seen. On its southern side, a narrow block of sediments is enclosed by the continuation of the Serra da Mula diabase ridge and the Serra do Toldo d1ke whioh parallels it about 2 1/2 Kms to the east. Normal faulting with displacement of about 25 m is present at the northern end of this dike and it apparently involves an up-thrust wedge formed by its intersection with the small SE~trending dike at Station G 17.
Further to the South, control based on the upper Serrinha contact at Stations G 115 and G 114, although widely-separated, suggests the possibility of the presence of other NE-trending faults similar to the Lucindo fault.
A small diabase dike, trending NE occurs at Station. G 96, 2 km south of the village of são Sebastião, aÍ;ld coincides approximately with the northern fault of the Rio do Liso Block as mapped by Kremer(2).
.
The accompanying map (Plate 1) shows contours on the top of the Teresina fm. Because of the lack of marker beds in the Serrinha fm it is poorly con~rolled. It reflects upward displacement on the east side of the Serra do Toldo dike but suggests that this may be due to a structure imposed by the intrusion of dia base. The displacement of the Serra da Mula fault block apparently decreases northward.
No indications of petroleum were found in the map-area. An asphaltic seep occurs in joints of the Morro Pelado fm in the area of Serra dos Borges, 11 kms to the NNE.
The upper beds of the Teresina fm repres~nt the last marine phases of the Permian period when a shallow fresh-water environment prevailed. Bottom currents and wave~action caused the irregular bedding and cross-lamination of the fine clastics whichare characteristic of tbe fm and provided the agitation that is thought necessary for the growth of oolitic beds.
With Serrinha time a transition to a deeper fresh or brackish water environment ensued: the fine clastics becoming more regularly laminated ' ali.d e the sandier beds lacking sorting and stratification. This condition continue on into Morro Pelado time when rapid changes in source material occurred, causing the abrupt succession of varicoloured sediments of that fm. Lenticularity of these beds and occasional cross-bedding suggests rapid deposition under near-delta conditions where numerous brief intervals of emergence occurred locally.
A pre-Botucatu hiatus caused erosion of the Morro Pelado whiCh is reflected in this area by a thin re-worked zone at its upper contact. Botucatu sedimentation commenced with a fresh-water PETROLEUM INDICATIONS GEOLOGIC HISTORY prevailed for a longer period than in other parts of the bas1n. No typ1cally aeolian condit10ns occurred but sand with definite wind-blown characteristics formed part of the source-material. Towards the end of Botucatu time, dia~ase dikes intruded the whole sedimentary section and, reaching the surface, caused the effusion of basalts of the Serra Geral fm. Faulting occurs along the outcrop traces of these dikes but there is no evidence to indicate their age. They are generally supposed to be concomitant with the intrusion.
None of the fms which outcrop in the map-area are considered capable of generating hydrocarbons. The porous' Botucatu sandstones could provide good reservoirs.
The Lucindo fault, with normal displacement of about 90 m, and the down-thrown block that exists on its western side offers favourable conditions for the entrapment of hydrocarbons. Tbis fault trends Nl5 2E and appears to reach northwards into the area of the village of são Sebastião to intersect with the southern extremity of the larfe SSE-trend1ng normal St~ Leocadia fault which was mapped by Kremer 2) • Three possibilities are suggested for the migrat i on and entrapment of hydrocarbons, assuming, in (a) and (b) helow, th~ presence in porous and permeable beds of the Carboniferous system before the period of faulting: (a) If the faults are intruded by diabase.Up-dip migration and accumulation against the diabase seal. (b) If the faults are free of diabase. Up-dip migration with accumulation controlled by the displacement of the reservoir bed against an impermeable bed. E.g. Rio Bonito down-faulted agàinst the Itararé sbales.
PETROLEUM POSSIBILITIES (c) If the faults are free of diabase. Up-dip migration from potential source beds into porous reservoirs against-- which they may have been faulted, with accumulation dependent in structures on the up-dip side of the fault. E.g. Irati displaced against Rio Bonito.
The magnitude of such migration would be limited by the proximity of the diabase dikes on the western side of the Lucindo fault. Since these trend NN the drainage area increases nortbward.
The dominant geological features of the Lucindo area are a series of large NNW-trending diabase dikes which intrude the Serrinha, Morro Pelado and Botucatu fms. They are believed to forro part of a larger dike system, which paralleling the Serra Geral scarp, connects with the Serra dos Borges area of intrusives. A down-thrown fault blook, with about 100 m displaoement and open on its northern side, ia bounded by two faults: The Serra da Mula fault, trending NNW, and the Lucindo fault which strikes N15ºE. There is evidence that other NNE faults also exist. This down-thrown fault block and its relationship with the Lucindo fault is considered to offer favourable condition for the migration and accumulation of hydrocarbons, and should be considered for a possible drilling locat1on.
It is recommended that further field work should be done in the north side of the map-area to : (a) Trace the northern extension of the Lucindo fault and to determine if it intersects with the inferred Santa Leocadia fault (which . trends SSW írom the village oí Santa Leocadia for ,40 Kms and reaches within 8 Kms of the map-area). - (b) Obtain further structural control on the western side of the Lucindo faul t, and to determine wl:ether diabase intrusiom are present in the area.
CONCLUSIONS AND RECOl~NDA TIONS
(2) Kremer, G. - Geological report on the Canoinhas - Valões - Porto União area, ~orthern Santa Catarina; DEBSP report NQ 96, February 1957
Plate 1 Geology of the Lucindo Area, showing structure contours on top of the Ter~sina fm. Scale 1: 25,000 Projected structural cross-section along line A-A+-A2 Plate 2 (ref. Plate 1). Scales Horizontal 1: 25,000 and vertical 1 2,000 REFERENCES
