A-OI Attached please find a letter written by Dr. J.C. Troelaen, acknowledging receipt of Dr. Lange's excellent paleontologio report.
Such reporta in conjunction with your Depex Report 722 have been instrumental in inatructing the Paleontologioal people what ia expected of them. I had noticed a general lethargy and 1ack of enthusiasm in some members. I believe this attitude stemmed Trom a lack of appreciation of the relation of the laboratory to the Qverall operation.
Along thése sarne lines, the Paraná Basin Study will demonstrate the significance af a carefUl compilatian and interpretation af paleontolagical data.
Mot. EPE - sit + Boo bla. 3/ nog47-Inicaríoca-Pará I wish to acknowledge with my best thanks the receipt of DEBP-PAL.57!15 containing the results of Dr. Frederico W. Langels study of Silurian and Devo nian microfoesils írom the Amazon Basin. Our labora tory in Belém has a1ready ~or some time been using some o~ these micro~ossils for correlation purposes, but Dr. Lange's beautiful r~port, written as it is by an expert, confirms our previous results and opens possibilities xor making more detailed correlations in the future.
Through the good offices of the Petrobrás headquarters in Rio we have received a supnly of hydr.ofluoric acid, necessary for the preparation of the unweathered shales from the wells, and wi~h the addition of some simple but essential labor atory equipment we çan now hope to be able to subdivide our Lower Paleozoic cores with greater précision.
The Belém laboratory has for some time been collecting foraminif~ra from the Silurian and Devonian strata and eonodonts a~d other microfpssils from the Carboniferous deposits of the Amazon Basin, and it is intended to pre-para reports on their vertical and horizontal distribu tion in the formations. Sue h investigations should prove helpful, both in stratigraphical correlations and in biofaci€s studies.
Mod. IPB • 80S· Boo blo. S/ râ1 :tUe and !nfoftla;t;loD. 1[8 traDS.ut • 01' lJO\U" ~ con of a Yery excellellt pale,nto1ogiC study Mã.e "'1 b. Jlre4,er1co 11. J.ange oi tlle Par&na ;aq,lor&tlon lJiatrlot.
!lUa at.r1a1 ... glveB to " thó;r'" Dr. !rOelaeil :tNIi ~ . n... ph8eated á.. &D4 a se n-in tll. t 'Dl 8 oi eU".t.... sapl ••• e'ftlua" o:t tU •• Jl1e~088Ua el!1d.1ted" Q . . . . . ia .,. U'at aIId .'alo __ ~. ___ 1_ t .. :ro-atlO11 .. ..u .. Ia .eaeral, ld.4dle a1aD. tUlU trOII t nac-vve ao.tq q .'1t1l1.d 0'1 Ma. lftatl'i-th. _ pUer1 tu ol.eco4oJ1ta. Sporomorphae tJraptol1 tas eto eve tÍ1&t th1s aa'l.r1à1 1'Ul p Te .xtrea~ Ve .~ in cerrel.a11oD8 an4 ~ in soa0 1:t1sta1lGee give Tallid ftf'enB.C8 po1nt. tO, ;rour paleol1tolos1ats. Ia h alAo, 'fihat 7' v t1atr1ct vUl beg1n -to contr:1but. w1.th tlda tne oi . . U 4irerie4 reaearoh aater1al.
Ptn'ROBRÁS I P E ·4 · A Enclosed is the paleontologic study made by Dr. F.N. Lange of this district based on a set of micro-fossil slides and surfélce samples received from Dr. J.C. Troelsen of the Belem laboratory a few months ago .
Dr. ~ange has attempted to set out the results of this study in the form - of a prilSctical guide for lab work and well geologists in the Amazon district in identification of micro fossils from Devonian and Silurian age rocks.
The identification of the specimans together with the photomicrographs represents a complete cmd well done study. Two copies of this report are being enclosed, one of which should be forwarded up to Dr. Troelsen together with any comments by DEPEX.
Re: Report Amazon Paleontology
AGE üD DISTRIBUTION OF\iJOxJ AMÃZONIAN PALEOZOIC MICROFOSSILS. ===-=============
, , During a visit to the Belem laboratory of Petrobras, at the end of May 1957, the writer received from Dr. J. C. Troelsen several s11des with microfossils as vell as a series of surface samples with the request for any obtainable stratigraphic informat1on relating to this material. Due to other more pressing vork (Paraná Bas1n Special Study) the writer only at the end ot July vas able to prepare and study this material. Â part of each one of the received 13 samples was submitted to acid treatment and the res1due checked for microtossil contente The thus obtained microfossils vere mounted on glass slides and then atudied and photomicrographed. In order to evaluate the systematic poa1tion and the geologic age of the apecimena, the foaaila vere com pared wtth S1lurian assemblages from the Trombetas formation, and with Devonian forma from the Âmazon bas1n. Some time ago the writer received several samples from the Divisão de Geologia e Mineralogia, D.N.P.M., collected at the Cachoeira Vira Mundo, type locality of the Silurian Trombetas format1on. These samples yielded a great nuaber of micro fosails (Chitinozoa, Hystr1chospbaeridae, Scolecodonts, Sporomorphae, Graptolites, Fish remaina), which already bave been mounted on slides and also been studied and identified. This assemblage enabled a compa rison with the above-mentioned Troelsen samples. Many of the herein discussed microfossils repreaent nev forms; since their systematic description has not yet been published, the ne. specific names assigned to the several forms have no offic1al status and are mentioned only for general reference and to help in the evaluation of the age of the samples and to show the geographical and vertical distribution of the species.
The accompanying table of distribution allovs a comparison of the different localitiea of occurrence. The two tables with photomicrographs illustrate all the herein mentioned Chitinozoan species •
INTRODUCTION
Frederico Waldemar Lenge
P!L.57/l5.
The folloving samples vere received for analysis: -Nine glass slides AGS. 352.A containing: CyathoChitina cf. C. campanu laeformis, ConoChitina cf. C. simplex, Scolecodonts, Foraminifera.
AGS. 251: Cupar1= Shale, grey, clayey, micaceous, vell laminated. Microfossils: AngoChitina aff. A. filosa, Conochitina fila mentosa, C. hadrocephala, C. cf. C. proboscifera, Cyathochitina cf. C. calix, C. rhabdomorpha, Illichitina cuspidata, Ancyrochitina svani, Sphaerochitina annulata, Sph. setosa, Rbabdochitina cf. R. magna, Desmochitina balanomorpha, D. cf. D. cingulata, D. cf. D. erratica, Leiofusa fusiformis, Veryhachium trispinosum, Hystrichosphaeridium sp., Sporomorphae. AGE: Silurian Trombetas Fm. ,
, AGS. 352.A: Apuau= Shale, light grey, clayey. Microfossila: ConoChitina cf. C. simplex, CyathoChitina cf. C. campanulaeformis, Desmochitina sp., Leiofusa fusiformis, Scolecodonts, Sporomorphae. AGE: Silurian Trombetas Fm.
DÃA. 219 (250) Urupad1: Sandstone, very fine, silty, micáceous, and Siltstone, clayey, micaceous, laminated. Acid treatment yielded no microfossils, only heavy mineral residue. , . AGE: Probably Lover Devonian Maecuru.
CÂÂ. 249: Urupad1= Shale, clayey, light grey, soft, laminated, very finely mieaceous. Microfoasils: Lagenochitina exigua, Cyatho chitina rhabdomorpha, 4ncyrochitina cf. A. diabolo, Desmochitina cf. D. cingulata, D. cf. D. aommeri, Leiofusa fusiformis, Veryhachium tri spinosum, Hystrichospaheridium spp., SporomorphaB. AGE: Silur. Trombetas.
CÂA. 246: Urupad1= Shale, as above. Microfoasils: Lagenoeh1t1na exigua, Ancyrochit1na cf. A. d1abolo, Desmoch1tina cf. D. c1ngulata, Desmochitina cf. D. sommeri, Leiofusa fusiformis, Veryhachium trispi nosum, Hystr1chosphaeridium app., Scolecodonta, Sporomorphae. AGE: Silurian Trombetas formation.
CÂA. 245: Urupad1= Shale, grey, clayey, silty, micaceoua, laminated. Microfossils: Conochitina hadrocepbala, Ancyrochitina cf. A. diabolo, Deamochitina andrei, Desmochit1na cf. D. aommeri, Scolec odonta, Sporomorphae. AGE: Silurian Trombetas formation.
CAi. 243: Urupad1= Shale, grey, clayey-silty, laminated, vith thin light-grey silty laminae; and Siltstone, coarse, arenaceous, micaceoua. Microfossils from ahale: Conochitina caudata, Conochitina cf. C. dactylua, Conochitina inflata, Cyathoch1t1na cf. C. ca11x, Oyathochit1na cf. C. campanulaeformis, Cyathochit1na rbabdomorpha, Ancyrochitina cf. A. diabolo, Desmochit1na balanomorpha, Desmochit1na cf. D. cingulata, Desmochitina cf. D. erratica, Desmochitina cf. D. sommeri, Pteroch1tina symmetrica, Leiofusa fusiformis, Veryhachium tr1sp1nosum, Hystriehosphaeridium spp., Sporomorphae, Graptolites.' AGE: Silurian Trombetas formation.
CAi. 243.B: Sbale, light yellovish, silty, micaceoua. Microfossila: Cyathochitina rh~bdomo~pha, Veryhachium trispinosum, Hystrichoaphaeridium sp., Sporomorphae. AGE: Silurian Trombetas Fm.
CAA. 239: Urupadl= Shale, light grey, clayey, very finely micaceous, soft, laminated. Microfossils: Lagenomorpha exigua, Cono chitina inflata, Cyathochitina cf. C. campanulaeformis, Cyathochitina rhabdomorpha, Ancyrochitina cf. A. diabolo, Sphaerochitina cf. Sph. sphaerocephala, Desmochitina cf. D. cingulata, Desmochitina cf. D. sommeri, Leiofusa fusiformis, Veryhachium trispinosum, Hystrichos sphaeridium spp., Scolecodonta, Sporomorphae. AGE: Silurian Trombetas Fm.
The accompanying table shows the distribution of the obtained microfossils. The Silurian assemblage from the Cachoeira Vira Mundo, Trombetas River, and the species described from the Middle Devonian Barreirinha shale of the Tapajós River, vere listed in this table for comparison. The numerals on the species/locality coordenates indicate the number of specimens obtained from the residue of individual 5 to 10 gram samples treated with acids, and thus illustrate the average frequency. Representative specimens of each species vere mounted on glass slides for future reference and comparison.
This preliminary report concentrates especially on the analysis of the Chitinozoa vhich, due to their relatively large size, may be identified even under a common binocular microscope. The Hystricho sphaeridae generally are very small and need an .amplifieation of about 500 times for systematic classification, and therefore only the relatively large Leiofusa fusiformis, vhich so far only has been found in the Silurian, and the easily identifiable Veryhaààum, vere included in the distribution table. The other microfossils, i.e., scolecodonts, spores, fish remains, graptolites, need further detailed study, and vere included in the table only to call attention to their occurrence in the respective samples. The identification of these microfossils vill be given in a subsequent final reporte The geologic age of the samples vas established by comparing the microfossil assemblage with the forms previously described from the Middle Devonian Barreirinha shale of the curuá formation, and vith Middle Devonian Barreirinha shale of the curuá formation, and vith the Silurian assemblage obtained from the Trombetas samples. An analysis oi the fossil assemblages shovs that the Arixl-Tracoá AGS. 221 sample yielded 2 of the three previously described Barreirinha (curuá) Chitinozoan species, and in addition contained scolecodonts, fish remains, and spores similar to those from the curuá formation • TABLE OF DISTRIBUTION AGE OF SAMPLES AlI the other microfossi1-bearing samples vere assigned to the Silurian Trombetas formation, based on the fol10ving percentage eva1-uation 01' Silurian forms: Oli. 249 = alI 5 Chitinozoan apecies are lmown from the Trombetas assemblage (=100%). OU. = alI Chitinozoan speciea are known from the Trombetas assemblage (=100%). OAA. 246 = alI 4 Chitinozoan species are known from the Trombetas assemblage (=100%). Cli. = Tvo 01' the Chitinozoan species are known from the Trombetas assemblage (=50%). Cli. 243 = Ten 01' the 12 Chitinozoan species are lmown from the Trombetas assemblage (= 83%). Cli. 243B = The only Chitinozoan species from this sample is lmown trom the Trombetas assemblage (= 100%); in addition, the sample contalns Silurian Hystrichosphaerida. CAA. 239 = S1% 01' the 8 Chitinozoan species are known from the Trombetas assemblage (= 75%). AGS. 251 = Five 01' the 9 Chitinozoan species are known from the Trombetas assemblage (= 35%). In addition, this sample contains typical Silurian Hystrichosphaerids. AGS. 352Ã = From the 2 Chitinozoan speciea identiticated from thia sample, one can be correlated vith a species found in samples Cli. 239 and Cli. 243, both showing a high Silurian percentage. In addition, this sample contains the typical Silurian Leiofusa fusiformis.
Since the Ponta Grossa laboratory ia vell equipped to handle the preparation 01' theae PaIeozoic microfoseils, and since the writer has alI the pertinent literature, in addition to a large series 01' samples, thus enabling a direct eomparison and identification, it is hereby sug gested that additional samples from the Silurian and Devonian 01' Ama zonas be sent to this laboratory in order to prepare a type collection. After preparison and analysis, full reports about stratigraphic range and geographic distribution, photomicrographs, and slides with dupli cates, viII be returned to the Belém laboratory and to the DEPEX office in Rio. Ponta Grossa, August 5, 1957.
- 5 -
FINAL BEMABKS
Explanation of Plate I (AlI magnifications X 132 unless otherwise indicated).
Explanation of Plate FWL/8.57.
