CENTRO DE PESQUISAS E DESENVOLVIMENTO LEOPOLDO A. MIGUEZ DE MELLO PESQUISA E DESENVOLVIMENTO E ENGENHARIA DE EXPLORAÇÃO E PRODUÇÃO
[lj PETROBRAS 
BALANCING OF A REGIONAL GEOLOGIC SECTION IN SANTOS BASIN, BRAZIL 
INTRODUCTION the interpretation of a composite seismic line crossing BM-S-8 (figure 1). The great amount of salt present in the Santos Basin is the main responsible for the structural framework of this basin. Salt flew basinwards due to basin subsidence and differential overburden resulting in a thin skinned tectonics that led to the development of an extensional domain in the proximal part of basin and a compressional domain in the distal part. The extensional domain is characterized by the presence of synthetic and antithetic listric normal faults detaching on the salt layer and the compressional domain is characterized by growth folds, similar folds and reverse faults (figure 2). Salt occurs as pillows and diapirs along fault planes and in the cores of anticlines comprising an area of approximately 203km”, Synthetic and antithetic planar normal faults predominate bellow the salt layer.
BM-S-
[li] PETROBRAS 
METHODOLOGY 
The restoration was performed using the software Locace (IFP-Beicip Franlab) and the deformation mechanisms used were basically simple shear, flexural slip, rotation and translation. Salt was restored by filling in the area between restored upper section and the base of salt.
After each step of restoration the section was decompacted using the porosity data provided by the interpreters. The position of the shelf break was obtained through the analysis of the seismic line and the slope anele was calculated using paleobathymetric data.
The restoration was done over eight horizons, which are: Top of Middle Eocene, Top of Maastrichtian, Top of Campanian, Base of Campanian, Top of Turonian, Top of Albian, Top of Sag and Rift.
TOP OF MIDDLE EOCENE 
Deformation was subtle at this time and restoration was achieved taking into account the displacements along minor faults. The shelf break was positioned approximately 65km basinward the shoreline and it was used an slope angle of 1.3 degrees for the restoration of Middle Eocene time horizon.
Main observations (figure 3): 
[El PETROBRAS 
TOP OF MAASTRICHTIAN 
The position of the shelf break was kept constant and the slope angle used for the Maatrichtian was 0.9 degrees. Restoration was performed along faults and through unfolding.
The base of the salt layer was rotated 0.1 degree, counterclockwise, to compensate the basin subsidence effect.
Main observations (figure 4): e Depocenters are controlled mainly by faults F2, F3 and F4. e Extension dominates until the 170km position. To the east of D3 compression dominates and smaller depocenters are concentrated on “mini basins’ adjancent to salt domes. e In the vicinities of domes D2 and D6 erosion was taken into account in the restoration. e Salt occupies an area of approximately 215 km’.
TOP OF CAMPANIAN 
The shelf break was placed between positions 40km and 50km and the slope angle used was 0.9 degrees.
Restoration was done along faults and through unfolding. The base of salt was rotated of 0.1 degree counterclockwise.
[lil PETROBRAS 
Main observations (figure 5): e The major depocenter was controlled by Fl. e 2 and F3 were not active during the Campanian. e During the restoration process some normal faults were converted into reverse faults. e A normal fault around the 170km position was defined, along which D4 has evolved. e Compression migrated to the east of D4 and in the distal part of the section the depocenters were concentrated adjacent to salt domes. e Salt occupies an area of approximately 300 km’.
BASE OF CAMPANIAN 
The shelf break was placed between the positions 40km and 50km and it was considered for this time an slope angle of 0.9 degrees. Restoration was done along faults and through unfolding. The base of salt was rotated of 0.1 degree, counterclockwise.
Main observations (figure 6): 
El PE TROBRAS e During the restoration process some normal faults were converted into reverse faults. e A loss of mass was identified close to position 200km in the Turonian layer. e The salt layer occupies an area of approximately 415 km”.
TOP OF TURONIAN 
The shelf break and the slope angle (0.9 degrees) were kept constant.
Below the salt layer the faults with bigger throw (F7, F8, F9, F10, F12 and F13) were restored by fault shear and above the salt layer restoration was done along faults and through unfolding. The base of the salt was rotated by 0.5 degree, counterclockwise.
Main observations (figure 7): e Depocenters are controlled mainly by normal faults, especially FO, Fl and Fo. e The region between FO and Fl, which in the previous scenario was representing a structural low, now represents a structural high (see figure 6). e A loss of mass in the Albian layer was identified close to position 190 km. e Compression is very subtle at this time. e Salt occupies an area of approximately 545 km”.
Eli] PETROBRAS 
TOP OF ALBIAN 
The Albian surface was considered nearly horizontal (0,1 degree) and the base of the salt was rotated by 0.2 degree, counterclockwise. Restoration was done mainly by simple shear.
Main observations (figure 8): e The thickest portions of Albian are concentrated between positions 100km and 180km. e Some gaps formed due to intense shear along the faults through time and also there might have been a salt flow to out of the section and part of the sediments may have been carried along with the salt. e Salt occupies an area of approximately 650 km’. SAG
Main observations (figure 8): 
SAG 
Restoration was done mainly by fault shear due to the great amount of erosion.
Main observations (figure 9): 
e A structural high was defined between positions 150km and 190km, separating two ‘mini basins’. 
Ei PETROBRAS 
TOP OF RIFT 
Restoration was done by simple shear. Main observations (figure 10): e The main depocenter was located between positions 10km and 80 km. ° Structural highs were observed around 120km, 170km and 260km. e There was an adjustment problem along faults F9 e F11 where a large gap was created. CONCLUSIONS Two structural domains were identified in the geologic section: an extensional domain and a compressional domain. BM-S-8 is located on the compressional domain; The main active faults at each period of time were identified. Fl was active from the Top of Albian to the end of the Campanian, being the major controller of the depocenters. From that time on, until the end of the Maastrichtian, F2, F3 and F4 were the most active and important faults.
[ld PETROBRAS 
In the BM-S-8 area (to the east of the 160km position) there was a structural high in the pre-salt sequence. Extension was dominant until the end of the Turonian, when the depocenters were controlled by normal faults. From the Campanian on compression started to dominate and depocenters were concentrated in the vicinities of salt domes Its advisable to check the interpretation of some horizons in some parts of the section, especially in the places where normal faults were converted to reverse faults after restoration in order to verify if an inversion could have occurred. Also, where gaps were big the trace of the horizons should be confirmed, especially on the pre-salt sequence.
The loss of mass of the Turonian and the Albian layers around the 200km position after the restoration of the Base of Campanian and of the Top of Turonian suggest that a check over these horizons should be performed.
