No relatório em referencia (3 volumes) a Prakla apresentou os mapas de intensidade magnética, resultantes do levantamento da Plataforma Continental Sul, trecho de Porto-Alegre a Cabo F'rio, executado no período novembro/1969 a março/1970, O sistema de trabalho, desde as operações de campo a compilação e apresentação dos resultados, é o mesmo em-pregado no litoral do Para, E, Santo e R, G. do Sul e dispensa novos. comentarios. f sem dúvida, um trabalho de ótima qualidade, não obs tante as restrições aos mapas reduzidos (1:500. 000), cujos contórnos e inscrições não são bem nítidos. A Prakla insistiu em usar tinta sépia ao inves de preta, como recomendamos, a qual daria melhores copias ozalides, Providenciamos uma reduçao do mapa de is sogamas para a escala 1:1000000, incorporando o mapa da area de Pe-lotas, anteriormente executado, o que permite melhor yisualizacao das anomalias regionais: uma faixa perturbada se:desenvolve ao largo e a | proximadamente paralela à linha da costa, acusando a presença de ro-chas fortemente magnetizadas, talvez a prefundidades relativamente . menores; a leste deste espigao, o campo -magnetico é suave, O que po de indicar grande espessura de sedimentos; a oeste, aparecem areas relativamente calmas, como ao largo de Santa Catarina e no litoral de Sao Paulo (Iguape), podendo isto significar a presença de bacias costei ras com pacote sedimentar espesso, ou simplesmente areas de emba - samento fracamente magnetizado, 7 ag Pedimos autorizar a remessa de uma copia do relatorio ao Arquivo Tecnicbd e outra à DIREX/RPBA, para futura © Ref.: Relatório '!Aeromagnetometrical Surveys - Plataforma Continental Sult? - nº 069126/
e ~ E ae À Ed De acordo com o-contrato, a Prakla devera 
Ao: reinterpretacao pelo técnico G. Selch. Uma terceira cópia foi entregue pela Prakla à Diretoria do Serviço Geografico do Exercito, em cumpri-mento à recomendação do Conselho de Segurança Nacional, 7530-000-
"PRAKLA GESELLSCHAFT FUR PRAKTISCHE LAGERSTATTENFORSCHUNG GMBH
on Aeromagnetometrical Surveys 
in Brazil, Plataforma Continental Sul 
Client: 
Petróleo Brasileiro S.A.” Petrobras Dexpro Rio de Janeiro
Report 069 126/ Appendix I: ANA, Aircraft Navigation and Positioning System with Atomic Frequency Standards for Offshore Surveys Appendix II: Fixpoints ANA 12 - 18 (protocols and sketches)
069 126/
069 126/
Mapa 24 SH-22-K-III 25 SH-22-K-IV 26 SH-22-L-1III 27 SH-22-L-IV 28 SH~22-K~-I 29 SH-22-~K-II 30 SH-22-1-1 31 SH-22-1L-IT 52 SH-22-E-IV 33 SH-22-F-III 34 SH-22-F-IV 35 SH-23-A-III 36 SH-23-A-IV 37 SH-22-F-T 38 SH-22-P-II 39 SH-23-A-T 40 SH-23-A-II 41 SH-23-B-1 42 SG-22-X-III 43 SG-22-X-IV 44 SG-23-S-III 45 9G-23-8-IV 46 SG-23-T-III 47 SG-22-X-1 48 SG-22-X-II 49 SG=-23-8-I 50 $G-23-5-IT 51 SG~22-R-IIL 52 SG-22-R-IV 53 SG-23-M-III 54 SG-23-M-IV 55 S6-23-N-III Rio Grande do Sul a Rio Grande do Sul ”. Rio Grande do Sul Z Rio Grande do Sul” Rio Grande do Sul” Rio Grande do Sul ~ Rio Grande do Sul “ Rio Grande do Sul | Santa Catarina “ Santa Catarina oil Santa Catarina Santa Catarina “ Santa Catarina Santa Catarina — Santa Catarina - Santa Catarina * Santa Catarina — Santa Catarina Z Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Santa Catarina” _ santa Catarina dá Santa Catarina ~ Santa Catarina “ Santa Catarina © Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Santa Catarina
069 126/ rapa 56 SG~22-R-1 BY SG-22-R-IT 58 SG-23-M-T 59 SG-23-M-II 60 SG-23-N-I 61 SG-23-N-IT 62 SG-22-L-TIT 65 SG-22-L-IV 64 SG-23-G-III 65 SG-23-G-IV 66 SG—-23~H-III 67 SG-23-H-IV 68 9G-23-1-III 69 SG-23-1-IV 70 SG-22-L-IT 71 SG-23-G-I 72 9G-23-G-IT 73 SG=23-H-T 74 SG-23-H-II 75 SG-23-1-1I 76 9G-23-I-II ti 9G-23-J-I 78 9G-23-A-TII 79 SG-23-A-IV 80 SG-23-B-III 81 9G-23-B-IV 82 3G-23-C-TII 83 9G-23-0-IV 84 9G-23-D-III 85 9G-23-D-IV 86 SG-23-A-II 87 9G-23-B-I 88 SG-23-B-II Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Santa Catarina Paraná Paraná Paraná Paraná Parana Paraná Paraná Paraná Paraná Paraná Paraná Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo
+ Area 
069 126/
6 - Área Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Sao Paulo Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Sao Paulo Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Guanabara Guanabara Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Guanabara Guanabara Rio de Janeiro Rio de Janeiro Paraná, Santa Cats Paraná, Santa Cats
069 126/
In the agreement of August 21, 1968 and in the Têrmo aditivo no. 1 of July 9, 1969, Petróleo Brasileiro S.A. - Petrobras, Rio de Janeiro, commissioned PRAKLA, Gesellschaft fiir praktische Lagerstáttenforschung GmbH, Hannover, with the execution of aeromagnetic surveys in Brazil on the Continental Shelf of Rio Grande do Sul, Santa Catarina, Parana, Sao Paulo and Rio de Janeiro, and with the interpretation of the results of these surveys.
The present report deals with the execution of this survey called Plataforma Continental Sul, the compilation and processing of its data and the presentation of the geophysical results.
Corresponding to the mentioned agreement the interpretation of the results will be given in a separate report (069 126/2).
Fete LOCALLOMN OL DUrVey Area The survey area comprises the continental platform of the Atlantic Ocean located between Pôrto Alegre in the south and Cabo Frio in the north. It extends from the shore to the 200 m water depth line. Furthermore, one group of 4 profiles was flown from the town of Peruibe seawards extending the normal length of the flight lines by 230 km. Principal flight line direction is NW-SE.
The location of the survey area is represented in the index map (encl. 1, scale 1:1 000 000), 069 126/
| els Aim of Survey Tne aeromagnetic survey was intended to provide first geological ideas about sedimentary basins which are situated in the continental platform, enabling Petrobrás to select favourable regions for marine seismic work. In detail the aim was: - to determine the dimensions of such basins; - to separate areas of poor occurrence of magnetic material from those strongly magnetically disturbed; - to investigate,as far as possible, faults within the sediments.
Se pn ie a e ai a À The aeromagnetic survey was intended to provide first geological ideas about sedimentary basins which are situated in the continental platform, enabling Petrobrás to select favourable regions for marine seismic work.
Tede Previous Geophysical Surveys Geophysical investigations have not been executed pre- + viously in the survey area. Cy
1.4. Topographical Reference Navigation and positioning of the survey aircraft was done by means of PRAKLA's ANA two range electromagnetic digital navigation and positioning system, a description of which is attached as Appendix I of this report.
1.4.1. Positioning of ANA Transmitter Locations 
In the survey area close to the coast line triangulation points of the following institutes were available:
069 126/
CNG, DHN, SGE, IBGE. The coordinates of these points are calculated on the international ellipsoid and referring to Petrobrás! ARATU datum.
The coordinates of the seven needed ANA transmitter locations (ANA 12-18) were determined either by short tellurometer traverses or by triangulation work tied to the above mentioned triangulation points.
ANA 12 Palmares do Sul was tied to the SGE points. Joao Morais and Casa da Ponte by a tellurometer tra- - verse.
ANA 15 Pontal do Sul was tied to the CNG point Barranco and the DHN point Conchas by a tellurometer traverse.
ANA 16 Guarujá was tied by special agreement of Petrobrás to CNG preliminary point Tegereba and to IBGE point Farol Moela by triangulation work. The preliminary point Tegereha had to be used as no other definitive points of sufficient accuracy exist in this rough coastal strip between Itanhaem and Angra dos Reis.
ANA 17 Angra dos Reis was tied to DEN points Ponta da Cidade and Algodao by triangulation work.
ANA 18 Conselho is almost identical with the DHN point Conselho.
in de 
069 126/
1.4.2. Topographical Maps 
Very few topographical maps of the scale 1:50 000 of the coastal strip were available: Palmares, Rancho Velho, Florianópolis, Itajai, Joinville, Araquari, Santa Cruz, Vila Militar, Baia de Guanabara, Araruama, Cabo Frio and Farol do Cabo.
In all other cases the Carta do Brasil 1:500 000 or 1:1 000 000 maps had to be used for topographical details, but always adjusted by the flight path films to the final profile positions.
2.1. Time Schedule and Performance 
069 126/
Nov. 22, 1960 Nov. 23, Nov. 24, Nov. 25, Nov. 26, Nov. 27, Nov. 28, Nov. 29, Nov. 30, Dec. 1, Dec. 2, Dec. 3, Dec. 4, Dec. 5, Dec. 6, Dee. Ts Dec. 8, Dec. 9, Dec. 10, Dec. 11, Det. 12, Dec. 13, Dec. 14, Dec. 15, Dec. 16, Dec. 17, Dec. 18, Dec. 19, Dec. 20, Dêts Bly Dec. 22, Dec. 23, Dec. DA.
794.5 1136.5 944.
Cc. 25, 1969 Break-down Magnetometer 0. 26, Productive 2. 27, Productive co. 28, Movement of ANA 14 to ANA 16 2. 29, Movement of ANA 14 to ANA 16 2. 30, Movement of ANA 14 to ANA 16 0. 51, Base-line flight P.S.IV 1. 1, 1970 Base-line flight P.S.IV Ne 2, Productive 1. Bs Productive a. 4, Productive 1. 5, Productive 1. 6, Productive 1. Ty Productive a. 8, Productive 1. 9, Aircraft 100 hours control a. 10, Aircraft 100 hours control 1. 11, Aircraft 100 hours control 1. 12, Productive 1. 13, Productive 1. 14, Break-down navigation computer 1. 15, Break-down navigation. computer 1. 16, Inclement weather 1. 17, Productive 1. 18, Inclement weather 1. 19, Productive 1. 20, Productive 1. 21, Productive 1. 22, Productive 1. 25, Productive 1. 24, Productive 1. 25, Productive 1. 26, Productive
- 12 - 
069 126/
796.3 
1091.2 439.6 855.1 806.7 971.1 998.1 582.1 696.7 Jan. 28, Jan. 29, Jan. 30, Jane 31, Feb. 1, Feb. 2, Feb. 3, Feb. 4, Feb. 5, Feb. 6, Feb. 7, Feb. 8, Feb. 9; Feb. 10, Feb. 11, Feb. 12, Feb. 13, Feb. 14, Feb. 15, Feb. 16, Feb. 17, Feb. 18, Feb. 19, Feb. 20, Feb. 21, Feb. 22, Feb. 23, Feb. 24, Feb. 25, Feb. 26, Feb. 27, i SO
746.4 
performance productive km/day = 413.5, 
ole Party Staff sc. s consertado! À Mw VOR md For the execution of the surveys PRAKLA provided the following personnel: supervisor (only temporarely present in Brazil): | party chief: | chief surveyor:
Dr. D.C. Boie | J.-P. Miller H.-D. Miersch surveyors:
operators: pilot: copilot/navigator: aircraft mechanic: local helpers for ANA-installation: The mentioned personnel with the exception of the local helvers is of German nationality.
The total flight hours in the survey area (excluding mobilisation) were 476:47 h. During this flight time the aircraft had to pass 4 routine controls after 100 h overation. No serious break-downs occurred.
Flying in Brazil was authorized by an order of Government of the United States of Brazil.
The observation of the national flight regulations was controlled by the local Brazilian DAC authorities.
2 - 5 temporarily hired 
069 126/
2. ANA-Aircraft Navigation and Positioning System For navigation and positioning of the flight-lines PRAKLA provided ANA, radio aircraft navigation and positioning system with atomic frequency standards for offshore surveys. A description of theory and application of this PRAKLA developed and manufactured system can be found in Appendix I of this report.
According to the permit licenced by the Brazilian telecommunication board CONTEL the two ANA transmitters were adjusted to the following frequencies: Transmitter I: (ANA-Stations 12,14,16,18): £ = 1874267 cps: Transmitter II: (ANA-Stations 13,15,17): £ = 1875793 cps.
The effective propagation velocity Vinge was determined by base-line measurement by ANA itself (phase-counting on the base-line), in comparison to the geodetic base-line length, resulting generally in: Using these effective propagation velocities, the corresponding wave lengths of the two ANA-transmitters applied were:
= 46 = 
069 126/ survey area VI: The coordinates of the ANA-transmitters are given in the protocols of the fixpoints ANA 12 - 18 (Appendix II).
The two distances determining the position of each fiducial being represented and numbered in the isanomaly maps were punched automatically in units of these 1/16 À in intervals of 14.2 sec (about 1 km profile-flight resp.) by the ANA-receiver aboard the aircraft on 5 channel paper tape in the National Elliot Code for direct input into PRAKLA'ts Control Data 30 computer.
Updating and closure errors of the positioning data were controlled by overflying check points at the beginning and end of each survey flight. They are entered in the daily flight-reports in octal units of 1/16 à.
These check points were determined during the phase counting flights of each ANA base line with an accuracy of + 1/16 A.
As the effective propagation velocity and final base-line extensions were determined using all survey flights, the corresponding parameters for aircraft navigation had to
069 126/ be determined provisionally prior to the flights, resulting in slightly uncertain navigation data for the pilot in the vicinity of the base line. But these provisional parameters were used only for aircraft navigation. Final coordinates computations were entirely carried out by introducing the final parameters.
Generally the ANA navigation and positioning system was running at a very high degree of reliability and performance. No greater troubles occurred even in 400 km distance from shore. ca
2.5.3. Doppler Navigator 
In the case of provisional system parameters ANA navigation information becomes weak in the vicinity of the transmitter base line including its crossing. This is due to a mathematical insufficiency of the Pythagorean proposition in the case of one of the small sides of a rectangular triangle approaching zero.
In order to provide navigation data for the pilot in such zones a Radan Doppler System, type GPK 1000 of General Precision Laboratories, Pleasantville, N.Y., was used in combination with a navigation data computer TNC 50.
Horizontal control in the case of Doppler navigation was provided by a high precision Gyro Sperry C 12.
In the case of the application of the Doppler navigation, Doppler data were introduced as an interpolation device between starting and finishing fiducials positioned by ANA.
o 78 = 
069 126/
Thus all positioning is done within the same coordinate system.
2.5.4. Altimeter 
A barometric altimeter (manufacturer PRAKLA) with analog continuous recording was used to measure the altitude of the aircraft above sea level.
The flight altitude is represented on the magnetometer analog record in a vertical scale of 250 mm & 1000 m (1:4 000) and in a horizontal scale of 25 mm = 1000 m (1:40 000).
Flight altitude control is important for correlation of measuring profiles and control profiles.
Deviations from the pre-selected altitude by 50 m which only rarely occurred during the surveys do not affect the magnetometer as the normal earth's field vertical gradient is only of the order of 3 y/100 m.
Thus no further consideration of the altitude as far as mapvine of data is concerned was necessary.
2.5.5. Flight Path Camera 
The flight path camera LK 21, manufactured by PRAKLA was used. This strip camera prepares continuous strips of the overflown terrain in the scale: focal length/flight altitude. The camera is mounted on a gyro-stabilized platform in order to guarantee a constantly sharp re-oresentation on the film.
069 126/
Tne fiducials of the synchronization of flight path and magnetometer measurements are represented by simul-taneous recording of the ANA-or Doppler-coordinates on the magnetometer tape and on the margin of the film. On the film, the first "1" indicates the exact position of the fiducial, then follow 4 figures indicating Say (see Appendix I, page 2) (or in the case of Doppler the flown profile length) and 3 more figures which give Spi (or with Doppler the actual deviation of the aircraft from the desired line of the profile) in 4/16 (or with Doppler in hundreds of nautical miles).
As the major portion of the survey area was offshore, the camera was only running when approaching or overflying the mainland or islands. The films may easily be orientated by means of the mentioned fiducials.
On board the aircraft and for ground monitoring, two of PRAKLA's digital free-proton precession magnetometers PM 24 were used.
The PM 24 consists, besides a visual control indicator, of two recording devices: digital output with 5-channel punched tape recording in the National Elliot Code as 5 digit figures, the unit being 1-7 3 digital output with 5-channel punched tape recording in the National Elliot Code as 5 digit figures, the unit being 1Y; analog output with ink recording on paper tapes with a vertical scale of 250 mm É 200 y and a horizontal scale of 1 value * 1.6 mm or 25 mm = 1000 m (1:40 000).
- 20 - 
069 126/
Integration time including recording for one measurement is 0.9 sec corresponding to about 65 m on the ground. Exactly 16 digital magnetometer values are related to 1 pair of ANA values (at about 1 km intervals) on the same punched tape record. Fiducials on the analog record are simultaneously set by the digital ANA recordings (at 25 mm é 1 km intervals).
The ground monitor magnetometer was designed only for analog ink recording on 100 mm paver tapes with a
vertical scale of 100 mm É 200 y anda horizontal scale of 1 cm é1min. 
Synchronisation to the flying magnetometer is recorded by exact time comparison (+ 1 sec) on both records.
2e4, Disposition of survey According to the ANA-radio navigation and positioning the survey area had to be divided into six survey zones (P1.S. 1 to P1.S. 6), each being limited roughly by profiles cutting the transmitter locations (see encl. 1). ote wie pees Vs LA A According to the ANA-radio navigation and positioning the survey area had to be divided into six survey zones (P1.S. 1 to P1.S. 6), each being limited roughly by profiles cutting the transmitter locations (see encl. 1). The division into the six survey zones was used for flying and positioning purposes only. In the geophysical processing by CDC 30 in Hannover, a difference had to be made between the zones I-III, IV, V-VI, but all zones could easily be tied to each other.
Spacing between consecutive measuring profiles was 5 km. At the limits of the survey zones the limiting profile was flown twice (on PRAKLA!'s expense) in order to get
DT a 
069 126/ sufficient control of zone connections. The spacing between control profiles was about 25 km. According to this spacing the survey has to be classified as re-connaissance survey.
Flight altitude was strictly 700 m above sea level controlled by the aircraft's barometric altimeter, adjusted twice every day to local pressure.
Em Compilation and Processing of Data, Presentation of Results 3.1. Profile Positioning Basis for the entire profile positioning are the locations 49 - 48 of the ANA trensmitters (compare 1.4 and 2.3.2).
The descriptions and the coordinates of the ANA-stations are represented in Appendix II. The coordinates applied to profile positioning are the coordinates of the trans-mitting antennae.
The coordinates were computed and map layouts represented in the UTM-systems 22, 23, 24 respectively.
The layout of all maps is strictly based on the corresponding Petrobrás instructions.
Computation of flight path coordinates as well as their plotting was done entirely by means of PRAKIA's CDC 30 computer and by a punch tape led automatic plotter.
- 22 - 
069 126/
The profile positioning work carried out by the local crew was rather simple. The crew had to prepare the flight programs and continually control the ANA equipment. This control was mainly to localize, in 22 cases, a lane loss which was simply possible by the lane chain records of both transmitters on the analog magnetometer record. Furthermore the crew had to control and distribute the closure errors between two consecutive updatings of the ANA distances at check points (see 2.3.2).
The mean closure error of profile positioning derived from a total of 276 overflights of check points resulted in a horizontal closure error = + 7.0 A/16=+ 70m within a mean flight time of 1:40 h and within a mean profile leneth of 400 km. or = 3.5 /S km in m.
As this figure includes twice updating errors during overflights of check points in the order of 21/16 = + 20 m the accuracy of ANA is still higher.
In Hannover 211 positioning data prior to final coordinate computations ran through a general program to check all recorded data by means of a second derivative method.
Final positioning of profiles was programmed by using the triangle of transmitter A, transmitter B and aircraít, all sides of which being known, and by transformation into the UTM-system by means of the UTM-coordinates of the two transmitters.
- 33 = 
069 126/
Del. Processing of Magnetic Data 
3.2.1. Elimination of Diurnal Variation of the Magnetic Field wv Fe o 1. nl cias malas doloso mal eh Seção Nh ia Sel do nd ws eet te A te te "O Neale ote WW NO oe or ia ad O alo fal eee GEE mr (o Pnet wae oe Sra org aa tonal It is well known that records of the diurnal variation at a ground station are not always representative for a survey area which is up to 430 km away from the recording station.
Nevertheless during all survey flights, the variation of the total intensity was measured by a second magnetometer of the type PM 24 in order to eliminate at least the short-periodical parts of the variation. Normally, this ground station should be located approximately in the center of the survey area; but due to the almost complete offshore survey the ground station could only be placed close to the coast line.
The variations of the ground station were determined at one gamma intervals by precise time comparisons of ground station and aircraft records. Then they were digitized and finally subtracted by the computer from the survey data.
Still existing long-periodical parts of the variation were eliminated in the course of the digital evaluation of data. Experience had proved that the long-periodical parts of the variation are of a linear character within the short time of the survey of one profile and may be represented by a + bx (x = length on profile).
If an adjustment by the method of least squares is carried out with the total misties of the magnetometer data ty appearing is profile intersections, the minimum condition Ew;. + minimum with
o om 
069 126/ yields the coefficients a,b; for survey profiles resp. Csd; for control profiles, the parameters of the long-periodical terms of the variation.
Having corrected the total of the values correspondingly, the residual mistie (medium = + 1.4 y) at profile intersections were about in the order of the noise level of the magnetometer. Thus, the application of the mentioned method eliminated the influence of the long-periodical variation completely. Simultaneously the smallness of the residual mistie proves the correctness of the profile positioning, of keeping the flight altitude and of the precision of the magnetometer. The residual misties finally were distributed in the vicinity of the profile intersections as their amounts can be assumed to be produced by local errors in position and/or altitude. dec. Computation of Regional Field The regional magnetic field contrary to the gravity normal field cannot be determined world-wide. Thus, it had to be derived from the total of the measured magnetometer data. The computer determines, from the magnetometer data, coefficients of a general square surface adjusted to minimize the mean square sum of the residual anomalies.
o PS o 
069 126/
Tne formula for the applied regional field reads: 
Xo» Yo? coordinates of the origin of the regional field in the UTM-system in m.
a 96 = 
VeCllLiaL WorlLariali wm Dit i x) = 7 161 758 Yo = 22 762 501 | B99 = 23 786 B49 = 70,000 686 922 Ag, = -0,000 449 135 244 = -0,000 000 003 33 Central meridian -51º Ky = 7161 758 Yo = ™ 762 501 aoo = 23 775 2410 = 0,003 961 000 201 = 0,001 013 300 aq = -0,000 000 019
069 126/
3.2.3. Computation of Isanomalies of the Magnetic Total Intensity a “ Tne anomalies of the total intensity resulted finally from apvvlving the following equation to all magnetic data:
AT =T - short periodic variation measured _ jong periodic variation - Tas 
In practice, the electronic computer yields a list of the coordinates of the intersections of isanomalies and flight lines. Moreover, the drafting machine plotted a map of these intersections (contour interval 5 y). Finally these intersections were connected manually. A graphical representation of the program flow is given in figure 1 (page 28). rer Presentation of Results The survey area covers 107 maps in the scale 1:100 000 (encl. 13-119) and 12 maps in the scale 1:500 000 (enci. 2-12. 6a).
ELECTRONIC INTERPRETATION GF AIRBORNE-MAGNETIC MEASUREMENTS i The maps of the isanomalies of the magnetic total intensity were prepared as two-colour prints on transparent film Pokalon (0.15 mm) of invariant size.
They contain: - the automatically drawn lattices of the maps, grey colour; - a simplified representation of the topography, grey colour, controlled precisely at intersections with flight lines; | - the automatically drawn locations of the flight lines ; with fiducial marks, each fifth numbered, grey colour; - the isanomalies of the magnetic total intensity with | contour interval of 5 y, brown colour, each fifth stron- . ger, extreme values being drawn additionally; - the subtracted regional field in parameter representation on the legend.
According to the contract, geophysical description and interpretation of results will be given in a separate report.
August Aug 12,
«= BO = 
069 126/
Two Transmitters, 70 W output each, to be installed as ground stations at known locations. The lightweight and small size transmitters including spare parts and power supply can easily be brought to any desired place, also into rough terrain. Even small aircraft or boat can be used for transportation: Aircraft Equipment for each aircraft operating in the survey area. This equipment is especially designed for installation and operation in small aircrafts.
Two-Range Navigation and Positioning 
Applying ANA for aircraft navigation and positioning, the distances s', and s’, between the two ground stations A and B and the aircraft are measured by determining the traveltime of the electromagnetic waves. The frequency standard for measuring the traveltime is aboard the aircraft. The output of the traveltime measurement is digital, ready for input into the binary navigation computer. Besides the two distances measured electromagnetically, the The value vs characterizing a flight line, is set on the control indicator, the constants characterizing the geometry of the transmitters and flight angle O are put into the navigation computer.
The navigation computer has a fixed program, which first re-duces the oblique distances sa ands’, to horizontal distances sa und sg. These horizontal distances are then used for determining the quantities p and q. From p and q the position of the aircraft in the u-v-coordinate system, axes of which are parallel and rectangular respectively to the desired flight path, is determined by rotating the coordinate system. By sub-tracting vg from the cross-track coordinate v of the flight path, the deviation Av of the actual flight path from the desired one (Av = v — Vs) is computed. This information is given to the pilot and to the autopilot by the control indicator.
As only the modulus of p is determined, two aircraft positions are possible. However, for the solution of that ambiguity as to u and v, the aircraft position relative to the basis line is put in by a switch on the control indicator.
Ground Stations 
Iwo transmitters Operating in the 1.60 Wiriz-Dana are necessary. The transmitters radiate unmodulated energy. The operating frequencies of the two transmitters may be as close together as approx. 1.5 kHz. That means, a bandwidth of only + 750 Hz or a 2.5 - 10-4 frequency tolerance channel covers the frequencies of the two stations. The fully transistorized transmitters are sealed in cylindrical housings filled with inert liquid for protection against moisture and dust. The housinas are flanaed directly to the antenna
Aircraft Equipment 
For operation of the aircraft equipment 24 V to 28 V DC power supply with a maximum consumption of 12 A and the 1 MHz output of a frequency standard are necessary. Again a Varian R 20 Rubidium Frequency Standard equal to that of the ground stations is used. While control-indicator and navigation receiver shall be installed ready-at-hand to the navigator, the navigation computer and the frequency standard may be placed at the aircraft radio-rack. As receiving antenna a 2 to 3 m fixed aircraft antenna, as normally installed for HF-reception, can be used.
From the received energy, first the carrier-frequencies f and f + Af of the transmitters A and B are filtered-out with a 25 Hz bandwidth double crystal filter, the attenu-ation of which is more than 80 db when regarding the frequency of the other ground station. Due to the fact,
60-times per second the distances in the two phase accumulators are digitally transferred to the naviaation computer and transformed into the navigation coordinates u and v, which are digitally displayed on the control-indicator. On the navigation computer, digital thumbwheel-switches are provided for the parameters defining transmitter geometry and flight angle.
Range and Accuracy 
The ANA-positioning and navigation system is specially designed for offshore airborne geophysical prospecting. Thus, it may be assumed that the electromagnetic waves, used for the survey, are propagating mainly over water. By overflying and updating known locations in intervals of some hours, there is a possibillity of avoiding an accu-mulation of inaccuracies of the frequency standards of aircraft and transmitters.
Practising these conditions, the range is more than 400 km and the error of the measured distance is less than 25 m per flight hour since the last updating at a known position.
The lowest bit of the octal input and output corresponds always to 2/16 or 1/32, resp., that is approx. 10 m or 5 m, resp.
Aircraft Navigation System with Atomic-Frequency-Standards 
Application of the frequency standard aboard the aircraft avoids the operation with modulated electromagnetic waves, operation with more than two ground transmitters, the use of directional antennas or the installation of a transmitter aboard aircraft. The use of unmodulated waves of highest frequency-stability permits maximum filtering-out of atmospheric interference at the receiver; therefore over-sea range is up to 400 km at only 70 W transmitter power. Small dimensions and lightweight equipment of ground stations and their easy handling enable an all-terrain application. Ground stations and aircraft equipment are fully transistorized, using integrated circuits; this assures long life-time and low trouble-rate. The two ground stations may simultaneously be used by any number of aircrafts.
PRAKLA GMBH - 3000 HANNOVER 1 - P.O. BOX: 4767 - PHONE: 80721 - TELEX: 922847 - CABLE: PRAKLA Amsterdam - Ankara - Brisbane - Djakarta - Kuala-Belait - Madrid - Rio de Janeiro - Tripoli - Vienna Reprint, even partially, only with our permission
Aircraft Navigation System with Atomic-Frequency-Standards for Offshore Surveys 
Technical Data 
The complete navigation and positioning system consists of two ground-stations and one aircraft equipment per aircraft. The construction of the two ground-stations is identical, they only differ by the frequency of the radiated energy.
Amsterdam - Ankara - Brisbane - Djakarta - Kuala-Belait - Madrid - Rio de Janeiro - Tripoli - Vienn The ground-station operates at air temperatures between —10°C and + 50°C, and up to a 95% humidity (frequency standard 0° C — 50°C).
Aircraft Equipment 
The complete aircraft equipment is designed for a 24V — 28 V de power supply.
Praia 
Escala ~ 7: 193. ec: 10,2785" BB: 99, 1998?
Fscali ~ 1: Sd00¢0 
