HIGH-RESOLUTION SEQUENCE STRATIGRAPHY APPLIED FOR THE IMPROVEMENT OF HYDROCARBON PRODUCTION AND RESERVES: A CASE STUDY IN CRETACEOUS FLUVIAL DEPOSITS OF THE POTIGUAR BASIN, NORTHEAST BRAZIL Petróleo Brasileiro SA, PETROBRAS, Brazil Programa de Pós-Graduação em Geologia e Geodinâmica, PPGG-UFRN, Natal, RN, Brazil Instituto Dom Luiz (IDL), Faculdade de Ciências, Universidade de Lisboa, Campo Grande, 1749-016, Lisboa, Portugal Programa de Pós-Graduação em Geociências, PPGEO - UFRGS, Porto Alegre, RS, Brasil Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte, UFRN, Departamento de Geologia, Natal, RN, Brazil High-resolution sequence stratigraphy (HRSS) was applied to Cretaceous fluvial deposits of Açu Formation, the principal oil-bearing unit of the Potiguar Basin, aiming to help reservoir management. Facies associations and stratigraphic surfaces were interpreted from an integrated analysis based on rock cores, ichnological, well logs, and production data. Overbank strata envelop transgressive meandering fluvial complexes and promote vertical fluid-flow barriers between reservoirs, thus characterizing zone boundaries. Zones' top boundaries consist of high-frequency subaerial unconformities placed at the top of paleosol levels correlated throughout the study area. The correlation allowed identifying nine high-frequency sequences and established the reservoir zonation that replaced the former four lithostratigraphic zones. The chronostratigraphic framework supports a more detailed and predictive 3D numerical geological model that is much more representative of the meandering fluvial system and its heterogeneities. Furthermore, the high-resolution stratigraphic reservoir zonation helped revitalize production by identifying intervals with high water cut, which hinder oil production, and oil-saturated intervals that were never opened to production.
ABSTRACT
This case study demonstrates that the application of HRSS methodology is fundamental to improve oil reserves, production, and the final recovery factor in the Potiguar Basin oil fields and analogous situation worldwide.
Keywords: High-resolution sequence stratigraphy, fluvial systems, Oil production, Reservoir management
1. INTRODUCTION
The characterization of heterogeneities and the understanding of their influence on fluid-flow patterns in fluvial reservoirs remains a challenging task for reservoir geologists. Nevertheless, it is essential to reduce uncertainties associated with the 3D geological model and improve reservoir management. Such demands are appropriately addressed through HRSS because this methodology unravels high-frequency variations of base level and the resultant stratigraphic record through the identification of high-frequency stratigraphic surfaces, system tracts, and sequences (Magalhães et al., 2016; Catuneanu, 2019; Magalhães et al., 2020). The relevance of HRSS as a useful guide to reservoir zonation, characterization, and production has been assigned in several depositional settings (Wan Wagoner et al., 1990; Borba et al. 2009; Xuemei and Hogliang, 2016; Beavingnton-Penney et al., 2019; Mitchum and Van Wagoner, 1991; Flint et al., 1998; Labrecche et al., 2011; Zecchin and Catuneanu, 2015; Magalhães et al., 2016; Bi et al., 2017, Magalhães et. at., 2020).
Many studies correlate downstream-controlled fluvial systems architecture with base-level variations, focusing on regional scales and low-frequency responses to changes in accommodation, and using floodplain and paleosol levels to correlate stratigraphic surfaces or sequence boundaries (Shanley et al., 1992; Schumm, 1993; Whight and Marriot, 1993; Shanley and McCabe,1994; McCarthy and Plint, 1998; Kerr et al., 1999; Blum and Tornqvist, 2000; Fanti and Catuneanu, 2010; Hanneman and Wideman, 2010). The complexity of tectonic, climatic, and geomorphic elements that can affect fluvial systems are some factors that may hinder recognizing the register of high-frequency base-level fluctuations (Whight and Marriot, 1993). Nevertheless, some papers attempted to do so where fluvial systems are directly associated with marginal marine settings (Aitken and Flint, 1995; Burns et al.,1997; Plink-Bjorklund, 2005; Mack et al.,2010; Dalman et al., 2015). These examples show the effectiveness of HRSS methodology in reservoir scale fluvial system characterization. However, to our knowledge, sequence stratigraphy application for improving hydrocarbon production and reserves remains poorly documented in the literature (Magalhães et al., 2020).
Therefore, this paper proposes a high-resolution sequence stratigraphy framework for a producer oil field hosted in Açu Formation, an Albian to Turonian fluvial complex located in the Potiguar Basin, stratigraphically described in literature only in a regional scale (see Item 2). The study focuses on interpreting high-frequency stratigraphic units used to establish the reservoir zonation and characterize the critical barriers to the fluid-flow pattern. These factors are fundamental to support geological characterization and modeling, hence increasing production and reserves of mature oil fields.
2. GEOLOGICAL SETTING AND STUDY AREA
The Potiguar Basin is a Mesozoic basin located on the easternmost section of the Brazilian equatorial margin. It covers about 48.000 km² and extends from onshore to offshore (Bertani et al. 1990) (Figure 1). The basin originated from the Early Cretaceous South America-Africa rifting process. Its sedimentary filling represents the rift to drift tectonic-sedimentary evolution stages (Bertani et al. 1990; Matos, 1992; Pessoa Neto et al., 2007) (Figure 2). The study area is a mature heavy-oil field hosted over the Carnaubais Fault System, a structural trend located at the eastern onshore section of the Potiguar basin (Behar et al., 2006; Barros Penteado et al., 2007) (Figure 1). The field has an approximate area of 32 km², and its fluvial and tide-influenced fluvial reservoirs belong to the Açu Formation.
According to Melo et al. (2020), the entire sedimentary filling of the drift tectonic stage of the Potiguar Basin is a 1st-order depositional sequence subdivided into two 2nd-order depositional sequences: the Lower (from Early-Albian to mid-Campanian) and the Upper (from Late Campanian to recent), which are respectively equivalent to the Transgressive and the Regressive Supersequence proposed by Pessoa Neto et al., (2007) (Figure 2). Five 3rd-order depositional sequences (1 to 5) compose the Lower 2nd-order depositional sequence (Melo et al., 2020).
The Açu Formation was originally defined by Sampaio and Schaller (1968) as a succession of sandstones intercalated with claystone and siltstones deposited by fluvial and marginal marine systems from the Albian to Cenomanian. In the context of third-order depositional sequences 1, 2, and 3, these deposits were affected by lateral variations of facies and depositional systems (Melo et al., 2020) (Figure 3). Hence, the onshore section of the lowstand (LST 1), transgressive (TST 1), and highstand (HST 1) systems tracts from depositional sequence 1 are equivalent to the Albian interval of the Açu Formation. Alluvial fans and braided fluvial systems belong to LST 1, whereas meandering and low-energy fluvial systems compose the TST 1 and HST 1. The Albian interval is overlain by another fluvial cycle of Early to Mid-Cenomanian age inserted in Depositional Sequence 2. Braided fluvial systems constitute LST 2, and low-energy fluvial to marginal marine deposits represent TST 2. The depositional sequence 3 consists of low-energy fluvial, estuarine, and marginal marine strata from the Late Cenomanian portion of the Açu Formation. Melo et al. (2020) also argued that the Açu Formation has a part of the early Turonian age, representative of HST 3 (Figure 3). The Albian to Late Cenomanian interval shows a progressive finning-upward trend (depositional sequences 1 to 3). Such a tendency and the successive stacked fluvial cycles within an overall transgressive trend were also observed by Vasconcelos et al. (1990). They suggested a eustatic control in the deposition of the Açu Formation. Those authors defined four lithostratigraphic units of correlation for Açu Formation, named Açu 1 to 4, usually utilized in several studies (e. g. Becker, 1996; Menezes, 2004). In this research, the TST 2 is detailed following the high-resolution sequence stratigraphy approach (Figure 2).
Figure 3. Schematic chart showing the five third-order depositional systems interpreted in the Albian do Late Campanian interval of the Potiguar Basin. The Açu Formation comprises three depositional sequences, and the studied interval is on the onshore section of TST 2 and LST 2, as indicated by black arrows (Melo et al., 2020).
3. METHODS AND DATASET
The study is based on a database derived from 17 producer wells from a mature heavy-oil field of the Potiguar Basin. All the wells have the basic suite of well logs (gamma-ray, density, and neutron), and some of them also have micro-resistivity (MSFL), sonic (DT), or image logs, which were used as auxiliary data. The rock cores used in the lithological and stratigraphic analysis are present in wells 1 to 9 (Figure 1) (Table 1).
Facies description is based on lithology, grain size, and sedimentary structures, allowing facies association interpretation. However, sedimentary structures are not recognized in disaggregated and dark oil stained sandy intervals of the cores. Facies and architectural elements mnemonics follow Miall (2014). An ichnological analysis was employed to enhance paleo-environmental characterization based on ethnological interpretation of the trace fossils, the structures of the communities, overlapping of traces, and the association of this information with paleoecological conditions. The Bioturbation Index (BI) follows Taylor and Goldring (1993).
Integrated data from cored wells were then used to identify the changes in the stratal stacking pattern, and hence the interpretation of high-frequency stratigraphic surfaces, system tracts, and high-frequency sequences. Such units were then identified in the other wells through well log correlations, and the resulting high-resolution zonation was used to enhance reservoir characterization, 3D modeling, and production purposes. used to enhance reservoir characterization, 3D modeling, and production purposes. Melo et al. (2020) provided the regional sequence stratigraphic framework that supports this high-resolution study. Sequence stratigraphy nomenclature follows Catuneanu (2011, 2019), and the high-resolution sequence stratigraphy methodology follows Magalhães et al. (2020). The recognition of high-frequency depositional sequences was based on the following criteria proposed by (Magalhães et al., 2020): identification of a typical internal T-R pattern, the vertical recurrence of this pattern at the considered hierarchy, the evidence of trends internally to the third-order TST 2, and mappability of all sequences through the entire study area.
4. FACIES ASSOCIATIONS
Four facies associations were recognized in the studied area and attributed to braided channel-fill (BCH), meandering channel-fill (MCH), overbank (OB), and tide-influenced meandering channel-fill (TMCH). Table 2 presents a synthesis of these facies associations.
Table 1: Available data used in this study.
4.1. Braided channel-fill (BCH) facies association
Description
The BCH facies association (Figure 4) is composed of weakly developed finning-up trends of very poor to poorly sorted, conglomeratic, coarse-and medium-grained sandstones, with planar (Sp facies) and trough (St facies) crossbeds or massive (Sm facies) (Figure 5). Interbedding of silty and mud facies (Fl facies) are rare. Trace fossils are typically absent, or a depauperate ichnofabric composed of isolated simple horizontal burrows and root traces may be present on the top of medium-grained sandstones. In well logs, BHC is usually represented by blocky or serrated gamma-ray log profile and a sandstone crossover with a good separation density/neutron pair that reflects its good permo-porosity characteristics (Figure 4). High gamma-ray values occur when feldspar is present. This facies association occurs interbedded with OB facies association, where the contact is erosional at the base and conformable at the top. BHC was cored only in wells 6 and 7, but the excellent lateral continuity observed in well log correlation indicates its existence in the entire basal section of the study area. The thickness range from 7 to 20 meters.
Interpretation
The coarse-grained and conglomeratic dominance, the little mud content, the predominancy of sandy deposits, and the well logs pattern suggests that BHC facies association was deposited under high-energy conditions, typical of sand bars of a braided fluvial system setting (Hornung and Aidner, 1999; Miall, 2006, 2014). The coarse-sand and conglomerate grain size, and the weakly developed finning-up trends, suggest a predominance of channel (CHb) element (Miall, 1985; 2014). The excellent lateral connectivity observed in well log correlation indicates its occurrence as amalgamated-channel complexes, probably deposited under low-accommodation conditions. This interpretation matches with the absence of trace fossils, or the low bioturbation intensity and low ichnodiversity observed on the top of some cross-bedded sandstones. These characteristics can result from unappropriated conditions for the formation and preservation of trace fossils due to widespread erosion, high energy, and high sedimentation rate. The observed ichnofabric may represent short colonization windows, under suitable energetic conditions, on top of fluvial bars.
4.2. Meandering channel-fill (MCH) facies association
Description The MCH facies association (Figure 4) is composed of weakly to strongly finning-up trends composed of very poorly to moderately sorted, medium-to coarse-grained massive (Sm facies), horizontal laminated (Sh facies), planar (Sp facies), and trough (St facies) crossbedded sandstones grading to moderately to well-sorted fine-grained sandstones with horizontal stratification (Sh facies) and ripple lamination (Sr facies) (Figure 5). Mudstones drapes can occur along cross-strata, and mudstones intraclasts are common at the base of St and Sp facies. Thinny laminated silty layers (Fl facies) can occur interbedded with Sh facies.
The assemblages of trace fossils can be grouped into the Ichnofabric Taenidium and the Ichnofabric Skolithos. The Ichnofabric Taenidium comprises small specimens of Taenidium barretti that can occur in monospecific assemblages or associated with Planolites and other simple horizontal burrows and root traces filled with sediment similar to the host rock (Figure 6). This ichnofabric occurs on the top of the finning-up trends, associated with the upper part of cross-bedded or ripple cross-laminated sandstones strata, with BI between 2 and 4. The Ichnofabric Skolithos is composed of small Skolithos and Arenicolites, and subordinately Planolites and Palaeophycus, and occurs in low intensity (BI= 1-2) limited to the top of fine-grained sandstones with cross-stratification and ripple cross lamination. Besides, there is an isolated occurrence of a horizontal burrow system (well 9), similar to Ophiomorpha, associated with medium to coarse-grained sandstone with planar cross-stratification (Figure 6).
The upward increase in mud content is represented by a serrated bell-shaped gamma-ray (Figure 4) and sonic logs profiles. The crossover in density/neutron pair reflects the permo-porosity conditions, with good separation in the basal portions of finning-up intervals and close to shale crossover in high mud contents intervals.
This facies association occurs intercalated to the OB facies association (Figure 4), where the contact is erosional at the base and conformable at the top. In the basal section of TST 2, the MCH exhibits coarser-grained-size facies. Besides, MCH is intercalated with the sandy variation of OB facies association and shows fining-upward trends interbedded with the silty and muddy variations of OB facies association towards the top. The thickness range from 2 to 10 meters.
Interpretation The well-developed finning-up trends, the well logs patterns, and the intercalation with floodplain deposits led to the interpretation of channel-fill elements of a meandering fluvial system for this facies association (Hornung and Aidner, 1999; Miall, 2006, 2014). The identified ichnofabrics support the interpretation of channel deposits in this context. The low intensity, small size, and restriction of the Ichnofabric Skolithos to the top of the sandstone strata characterize short colonization windows of opportunistic organisms under relatively high sedimentation rates. In non-marine deposits, this ichnofabric is typical of Skolithos ichnofacies, usually associated with the top of fluvial bars (Melchor et al., 2012). The presence of Ichnofabric Taenidium, with moderate intensity also limited to the top strata, indicates subaerial exposure and colonization by insects. It is comparable to the pre-desiccation suite of the Scoyenia Ichnofacies (Buatois e Mángano (2002) developed on a soft substrate, very common on emergent channel-bar tops (Melchor et al., 2012).
The overall decrease in grain size suggests a gradual reduction in the system energy, reflecting the fluvial style's change into the meandering fluvial complex. In the basal section, the coarser granulometric dominance suggests deposition under relatively more energetic settings that can be representative of the "gravel-sand meandering" or the "low-sinuosity braided-meandering with alternate bars" fluvial styles proposed by Miall (2006). Upwards, the succession is more characteristic of a “sandy-meandering” fluvial style (Miall, 2006).
4.3. Overbank (OB) facies association Description The OB facies association (Figure 4) is composed of massive muddy medium-to fine-grained sandstones (Fsm facies), poorly to well-sorted medium-to fine-grained horizontally laminated sandstones (Sh facies), ripple-cross laminated sandstones and siltstones (Fl facies), and massive siltstones and mudstones (Fm facies). It is common the presence of intervals bioturbated by invertebrates and roots (Fr facies) and with nodular carbonate concretions (P facies) (Figure 5) (Table 2). Pyrite and punctual slickensides are also observed. The color typically ranges from gray to green, but dark-red horizons occur in the lower sections (Figure 4) of TST 2.
In general, this facies association presents the higher ichnodiversity and intensity of bioturbation. The trace fossils assemblages can be outlined in the following ichnofabrics: Taenidium, Taenidium-root traces, Scoyenia, and Skolithos (Table 2). The Ichnofabric Taenidium mainly consists of Taenidium barretti that can be associated with small root traces filled with sediment similar to the host rock (Figure 6 and Figure 7), occurring on the uppermost part of cross-bedded or ripple cross-laminated muddy sandstones and siltstones, moderately to intensely bioturbated (BI= 3-6). Similarly, muddy sandstones and siltstones with Scoyenia gracilis, T. barrette, and Planolites characterize the Ichnofabric Scoyenia (BI= 2), recorded only on Well 1. Larger T. barretti associated with more prolonged root traces, usually carbonate-filled (Figure 6), occurs in dark-red and gray to green intervals with no primary sedimentary fabric preserved, compounding the Ichnofabric Taenidum-root traces (Figure 6 and Figure 7). Fine-grained sandstones with cross-stratification and ripple cross-lamination show small Skolithos and Arenicolites, subordinately Planolites, and Palaeophycus cross-cut by Taenidium, characterizing the Ichnofabric Skolithos (BI= 1-2). cross-cut by Taenidium, characterizing the Ichnofabric Skolithos (BI= 1-2). High gamma-ray log values are typical of this facies association, and density/neutron pair usually reach the shale crossover characterizing its non-reservoir behavior. This facies association occurs intercalated to MCH and TMCH facies association with erosive contact at its top and conformable at its base (Figure 4). Sandy facies are more restricted to the bottom and medium section of the studied interval, whereas silty and muddy content increases upward. The thickness also increases upwards, ranging from 1 to 20 meters. The well log patterns also suggest the occurrence of OB interstratified with the BCH facies association. In this case, OB thickness ranges from 50 centimeters to 5 meters.
Interpretation
The well logs patterns and its association with MCH suggest that OB facies association represents fluvial overbank setting (Hornung and Aidner, 1999; Miall, 2006, 2014). OB comprises floodplain fines (FF), levee (LV), and crevasse splay (CS) architectural elements, which individualization was not necessary for this study because of their non-reservoir character.
The observed ichnofabrics Taenidium, Taenidium-root traces, and Scoyenia can be assigned to the Scoyenia Ichnofacies, whose typical environments include crevasse splays, floodplain ponds, and poorly developed paleosols (Buatois and Mángano, 2011; Melchor et al., 2012). The higher the assemblages' intensity, the longer the colonization windows (time between depositional events), typical of overbank deposits. The ichnofabrics Taenidium and Taenidium-root traces characterize subaerial exposure and colonization by insects and plants, being the root traces very informative in these cases. Simple and small root traces filled with sediment similar to the host rock may represent high water table conditions (Brockelie, 1994), whereas more extended root traces (taproots) can be associated with lower water table into moderate to well-drained paleosols (Cohen, 1982; Brockelie, 1994; Kraus and Hasiotis, 2006). The ichnofabric Scoyenia represents the desiccation suite of the Scoyenia Ichnofacies (Buatois and Mángano, 2002), suggesting the development of trace fossils with streaked walls in firmer substrates, maybe floodplain ponds or temporary submerged and exposed substrates associates with the crevasse-splay process (Melchor et al., 2012). Besides, the Ichnofabric Skolithos on top of fine-grained sandstones, sometimes with Taenidium cross-cutting simple vertical traces, are here interpreted as superposing assemblages of trace fossils colonizing sandy crevasse deposits.
In some intervals, the lack of primary sedimentary structures, the high mud content, the presence of carbonate nodule (calcrete), and pyrite in the greenish and gray intervals indicate pedogenetic processes actuation on OB deposits (Retallack, 1988; Whight, 1992; Marriot and Whight, 1993). Such intervals are interpreted as very weakly to weakly developed paleosols, and classified as entisoils to inceptsoils, according to Retallack (1988). The observed dark-red intervals, with calcrete levels and long root traces, are assigned to well-developed paleosols (Brown and Kraus, 1987) where oxidation took place after long residence time, usually in a location distant from channel belts. These intervals resemble the oxisoils (Retallack,1988). The occurrence of dark-red paleosol in the lower section of the studied interval and the dominance of grey-green paleosols upwards means an upward decrease in paleosols maturity, typical of transgressive trends.
4.4. Tide-influenced meandering channel-fill (TMCH) facies association Description
Description
TMCH facies association (Figure 4) comprises moderate to well-sorted, medium-to very fine-grained sandstones with planar (Sp facies) and trough (St facies) crossbeds, in finning-upward trends to fine-grained laminated sandstones, siltstones, and mudstones (Fl facies). Mudstones drapes and intraclasts can occur along the cross-strata of St and Sp facies. A monospecific assemblage of Cylindrichnus concentricus occurs throughout laminated fine-grained sandstones beds, with low bioturbation intensity (BI= 1-2), which characterize the Ichnofabric Cylindrichnus (Fr facies) (Figure 6). The gamma-ray log pattern shows a serrated profile, with low values in sandy and high values in muddy intervals. Density/neutron logs reach the shale and sandstone crossover in muddy and sandy facies, respectively. This facies association occurs in the top of the studied stratigraphic interval, interbedded with OB deposits, in a lower sand/mud ratio context compared with the intercalations between OB and MCH deposits.
Interpretation The sedimentological characterization and well logs patterns suggest that this facies association represents a point-bar deposit (Hornung and Aidner, 1999; Miall, 2006, 2014) intercalated to overbank strata. Cylindrichnus are interpreted as suspension-feeding structures produced by polychaetes, that preferably occurs in shelf settings and is common in marginal-marine and estuarine environments with a brackish condition (MacEachern and Gingras 2007; Buatois and Mángano 2011, Knaust, 2017). In this case, the monospecific occurrences Cylindrichnus is an indicator for stressed conditions, as previously noted by many authors (e.g., Ranger and Pemberton, 1992; MacEachern and Gingras 2007; Díez-Canseco et al., 2015), it is related to brackish settings. Additionally, the finer-grained size and lower sand/mud ratio in comparison with MCH deposits, as well the intercalation with OB deposits, which contains non-marine ichnofauna (Ichnofabric Taenidium), are indicative that TMCH deposits were deposited in the downstream reach of a fluvial system, in fluvial-tidal transition environment (Dalrymple, et al., 2015; Dashtgard and LaCroix, 2015; Díez-Canseco et al., 2015).
5. SEQUENCE STRATIGRAPHY FRAMEWORK
5.1. Low-resolution (third-order) scale
According to Melo et al. (2020), the lower 2nd-order depositional sequence (DS) of the Potiguar Basin drift stage consists of five 3rd-order depositional sequences, named DS 1 to 5. The DS 2 encompasses the studied interval and comprises continental, marginal-marine, and marine deposits of early-to mid-Cenomanian in age, subdivided into lowstand, transgressive, and highstand system tracts (LST 2, TST 2 and HST 2, respectively) (Figure 3). The LST 2 is represented by unconfined and amalgamated fluvial strata that occur onshore and low-density turbidites and muddy deposits at the offshore portion of the basin. Onshore, the TST 2 is characterized by intercalation of low-energy fluvial channels and floodplain deposits composing an overall transgressive trend to a marine-influenced interval that contains the Maximum Flooding Surface (MFS 2). HST 2 is limited at the top by SU 3, which represents the onset of DS 3. The HST 2 deposits downlap MFS 2 offshore and has a very restricted occurrence onshore, due to truncation by SU 3 or no deposition. From the lithostratigraphic point of view, all the onshore deposits of DS 2 are part of the Açu Formation. In contrast, the offshore deposits are part of the Açu and Quebradas formations (Figure 3).
The MRS 2 corresponds to the contact between braided fluvial systems (BCH facies association) and meandering fluvial systems (intercalation between MCH and OB facies association) observed in the basal portion of the analyzed section (Melo et al. 2020) (Figure 4, Figure 8 and Figure 9). The meandering fluvial complex presents a transgressive systems tract's typical characteristics, such as the upward decrease in fluvial system energy and paleosol maturity (Wright and Marriot, 1993; Catuneanu, 2011). The gradual decline of fluvial energy during transgression also favored the increment of bioturbation and preservation of bioturbated strata and muddy overbank deposits upwards.
The TMCH deposits with Cylindrichnus (Cy) ichnogenera (Figure 6) represent the marine-influenced interval in which Melo et al. (2020) interpreted the MFS 2 (Figure 8). Therefore, in the study area, DS 2 is composed of LST 2 and TST 2. The following item (Figure 10) presents the stratigraphic refinement of TST 2, through the description of fourth-order sequences.
5.2. High-resolution (fourth-order) scale
The TST 2 meandering fluvial complexes exhibit many vertically stacked cycles. This cyclic pattern within the third-order TST 2 characterizes the fourth-order hierarchy. Each fourth-order sequence is very well recognized in well log patterns (Figure 4 and Figure 11) and consists of MCH/TMCH bound by OB strata altered to paleosol at different maturity (Figure 4 and Figure 12).
Paleosols are usually related to relative falls of base level and, hence, the development of subaerial unconformity (McCarthy and Plint, 1998; McCarthy and Plint, 2003; Mack et al.,2010; Costantini, 2018). This study used paleosols and laterally related overbanks to identify and correlate subaerial unconformities in interfluve regions. Overbank and paleosol intervals topped by subaerial unconformities separate high-frequency fluvial cycles along the entire study area. Despite the absence of organic-rich layers, bioturbated floodplains deposits suggest the location of 4th-order MFS's, once the low sedimentation rate necessary to bioturbation proliferation is typical of flooding moments. However, such deposits are only preserved where the amount of subsequent erosion is lesser than the floodplain thicknesses, making SU's very close or superimposed to MFS's in most cases (Figure 12). In some locations of the study area, erosion removed the entire floodplain deposits, and hence, MCH channel-fill deposits from the overlying sequence are vertically stacked and in direct contact. The lack of typical braided fluvial deposits representing the fourth-order LST indicates MRS is superimposed to SU. Therefore, only transgressive MCH, TMCH, and OB deposits are preserved in fourth-order sequences.
The TST 2 is composed of nine fourth-order depositional sequences bounded by the SU at the top of overbank/paleosol levels (Figure 13 and Figure 14). An accurate subsurface mapping and correlation of fluvial strata are usually challenging due to lateral facies discontinuity and geometry complexities of this kind of deposits (Wainman and McCabe, 2020). However, the well logs patterns and high-frequency transgressive trends (Figure 11 and Figure 12) allowed the correlation of high-frequency SU’s and sequences along the entire study area (Figure 15). The overbank levels consist of zone boundaries and represent vertical barriers to fluid flow (Magalhães et al., 2016, 2020). They represent heterogeneities that control the reservoirs' fluid flow pattern (see the next item for further discussion). Each sequence also exhibits horizontal heterogeneities at the lateral contact between channel-fill and floodplain deposits (Figures 13 and 15). The LST 2 was not subdivided into higher-frequency sequences due to the high degree of channel amalgamation leading to a homogeneous response in well logs patterns.
6. DISCUSSION: APPLICATIONS OF HIGH-RESOLUTION SEQUENCE STRATIGRAPHY FOR THE IMPROVEMENT OF HYDROCARBON PRODUCTION AND RESERVES Reservoir geology plays an important role in reservoir characterization and management of oil fields, especially green fields. If the geological models do not represent the main heterogeneities and properties of producing zones, it is challenging to predict the wells' behavior and measure their useful producer life. In the mature heavy oil-field used here as a case study, the lithostratigraphic zonation used as a reference for production described the reservoir on a broad scale, ignoring significant reservoirs flow barriers. Consequently, despite the oil-field production at the commercial level as a whole, some wells presented a production response worse than initially predicted. Besides, conceptual and numerical geological models misrepresented geological features, and the steam injection process has not always performed as efficiently as expected. In this context, the high-resolution stratigraphic framework was proposed (i.e., reservoir zonation) to resolve or minimize geological uncertainties related to geological characterization and production management.
6.1. Reservoir zonation and characterization
Ten zones (i.e., high-frequency depositional sequences and the LST) replaced the former four lithostratigraphic zones adopted in the study area (Figure 14, Figure 15). The overbank muddy characteristic makes them zone boundaries and, thus, the principal vertical heterogeneities that prevent fluid flow between adjacent reservoirs. Although some reservoir from high-frequency zones is in vertical contact (hydraulic connection) due to erosion, each high-frequency depositional sequence behaves as a distinct producer zone in terms of fluid flow pattern. Hence they must be characterized and managed separately.
The high-resolution chronostratigraphic zonation led to an accurate characterization of zones boundaries and facies association representation in each zone, the last two steps of the high-frequency sequence stratigraphic workflow (Magalhães et al., 2020). The high-resolution chronostratigraphic framework here presented shows that: a) the lithostratigraphic zonation cut through high-frequency subaerial unconformities and hence, laterally correlated deposits that are not connected (Figure 16 and Figure 17), and b) anomalously tilted oil-water contacts that cut through high-frequency zones limits are, in reality, two distinct horizontal fluid contacts (Figure 16 and Figure 18).
The detailed observation scale highlighted the presence of heterogeneities not previously noticed, which improved the reservoir characterization. Paleoflow data, derived from image logs interpretations from well 16, showed specific depositional paleoflow directions for each high-resolution production zone compared to the regional paleoflow interpretation obtained from lithostratigraphic zonation (Figure 19). These data were used as input to build 3D numerical geological models more representative of the architectural elements of fluvial reservoirs (Figure 20). Compared to 3D geological models derived from lithostratigraphic zonation, the high-resolution numerical model exhibits more accurate vertical and horizontal heterogeneities representation: zone boundaries (i.e., paleosols levels) are represented in the entire modeled area, as well as external geometry of channel fill and floodplains facies associations. Such an advance supports a much more accurate prediction of fluid-flow patterns in numerical flow simulations (Figure 21).
6.2. Oil production and reservoir management
The primary production of heavy-oil fields is generally low due to high oil viscosity. Thus, steam injection is used to make oil production reach economic levels. Steam injection is usually performed in two different steps: cyclic steam stimulation and continuous steam stimulation (Farouq Ali, 1973; Alikhlalov, 2011). The cyclic steam injection, or steam soak process, is a well stimulation process that involves the transfer of heat to the reservoir near the wellbore by periodical steam injection. In this case, the same well acts both as injector and producer (Figure 16). After a soaking period, the transferred heat from steam reduces the oil viscosity and, consequently, increases its mobility and allows its production (Alikhlalov, 2011). The produced volume from this method depends on, among other factors, the energy drive of the reservoir. After successive steam cycles injecting the same amount of steam, oil production tends to decrease through time due to the reservoir energy depletion and build-up of water saturation around the well (Farouq Ali, 1973; Farouq Ali and Meldau, 1978). As a result, production falls below the economic cut-off, which leads to the abandonment of cyclic steam injection and the adoption of continuous steam injection. In this stage, also known as steamflooding, the steam is injected into the reservoir in a pattern basis, in which a single well is used to inject steam continually, and the surrounding wells are used for oil production (Farouq Ali, 1973; Farouq Ali and Meldau, 1978; Alikhlalov, 2011) (Figure 16). The injected steam reduces oil-viscosity and reestablishes the energy drive of the reservoir, pushing the mobile oil towards the producer wells, sweeping part of the bypassed oil in the area not reached by cyclic steam injection (Farouq Ali, 1973; Alikhlalov, 2011).
After two or three steam cycles, some wells of the study area were closed due to reservoir energy depletion and uneconomical production. However, the high-resolution reservoir zonation signalized the opportunity to improve these wells' productive lives before converting to steamflood patterns. The production strategy based on the former lithostratigraphic zonation considered that the production from top intervals would lead to water saturation at the bottom. The reason for that is the uprising of water due to pressure drawdown. Based on this assumption, the lower portion of any zone was considered as an uneconomical target.
However, the adoption of high-resolution sequence stratigraphy identified new zones and hence supported an alternative production strategy. As the fluid-flow pattern and the increase of water saturation around the wellbore after multiple cyclic steam injections are distributed among the reservoirs, there was a great chance to identify oil-saturated high-frequency zones that were never opened to production. These zones likely have fluid saturation close or equal to the original (Figure 22).
Following such guidelines, zones with original oil were identified and opened, reestablishing wells production. Additionally, each opened high-resolution zone had distinctive water saturation and behavior during production, giving different contributions to total production. Zones with high water cut, which hinders production, were closed to make cyclical production economical again (Figure 23). These results encouraged using the same approach in other wells in the field, aiming to open not drained oil intervals and reduce water cuts in cyclical steam production. The management of future steamflood patterns also improved with the use of high-resolution zonation. This zonation controls the pathway of injected steam, moving the mobile oil through the equivalent interval in producer well (Figure 24) with the advantage of rationalizing the steam injection coherently to the observed production.
With the help of additional production tools, it is also possible to estimate each zone's contribution to the total production and, if necessary, make wells operations (opening or closing intervals) to improve the pattern steamflood efficiency. The production of residual oil coupled with the decrease in water cut and increasing efficiency of steamflood are crucial factors to enhance reserves, production, and the ultimate recovery factor of mature oil fields.
7. FINAL REMARKS
The regional scale in which the fluvial deposits of Açu Formation are usually described does not properly address the reservoir purposes. The lithostratigraphic zonation used for reservoir management does not represent and correlate the main reservoir heterogeneities critical to the fluid flow, making it difficult to understand how geological aspects can influence the wells' production and efficiency of the steam injection process. Additionally, conceptual and numerical reservoir models do not always show the geological features useful for a proper reservoir representation.
In this context, the HRSS method application, though the integration of rock, well logs, and production data, was fundamental to solving such questions and renewing reservoir zonation and characterization. Facies interpretation, enhanced by ichnological analysis, led to the definition of facies association representative of fluvial systems stacked within 3rd-order lowstand and transgressive system tracts. The recurrence of meandering channel-fill interbedded with overbank deposits allowed TST subdivision into nine 4th-order depositional sequences bounded by the SU’s at paleosol tops. The distinct well logs patterns and the high-frequency trends were used for an accurate subsurface correlation of SU’s along the entire study area. The overbank levels are barriers that control the fluid-flow pattern into reservoirs. Therefore, each high-frequency depositional sequence, and the LST, can behave like an individual producer zone. This new stratigraphic framework replaced the four former lithostratigraphic zonation of the study area. Hence, each high-resolution sequence was characterized and managed separately.
The adoption of high-resolution chronostratigraphic zones significantly improved the reservoir characterization and representation in 3D numerical geological models. Oil production through cyclic steam injection was revitalized as new zones were opened, and water-saturated intervals were closed, increasing the lifetime of wells that otherwise would be closed until the implementation of steamflood projects. Understanding fluid-flow pathways through reservoirs within zones diminishes the uncertainties in reservoir management, helping to predict intervals that must be closed or opened to improve steamflood efficiency. These results encourage the broad application of the high-resolution methodology to reservoir zonation and characterization, thus enhancing production, reserves, and the ultimate reservoir recovery factor of mature oil fields.
8. ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
This study is part of a graduate project performed by the first author at the Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte (UFRN), entirely sponsored by Petrobras. The authors wish to thank all the colleagues that contributed to this paper: Ednilson Bento Freire, Ana Paula Araújo, Marcos Antônio Moura Filho, André de Gasperi, Carlos Lima Bruhn, Guilherme Raja Gabaglia, João Marculino Araújo Netto, José Alexandre Gonçalves Melo, Patrícia Carvalho Costa, Leonardo Meneses, Manuelle Meike and Ewerton Soares.
9. REFERENCES
AITKEN, J. F. and FLINT, S. S., 1995. The application of high-resolution sequence stratigraphy to fluvial systems: a case study from the Upper Carboniferous Breathitt, eastern Kentucky, USA. Sedimentology, 42 (2), 3 - 30. ALIKHLALOV, K., 2011. Conversion of cyclic steam injection to continuous steam injection. SPE Annual Technical Conference and Exhibition, Denver, Colorado, USA. BARROS PENTEADO, H. L., BEHAR, F., LORANT, F., OLIVEIRA, D. C., 2007. Study of biodegradation along the Carnaubais trend, Potiguar Basin (Brazil) - Part 2. Organic Geochemistry, 38, 1197 - 1211. BARRELL, J., 1917. Rhythms and the measurement of geological time. Geological Society American Bulletim,28, 745-904. BECKER, M. R., 1996. Sedimentologic architecture, permeability structure and fractal characteristics of braided fluvial deposits, cretaceous Açu Formation, Potiguar Basin, NE Brazil. Phd Thesis. University of Texas at Austin, 798 p. BEHAR, F., BARROS PENTEADO, H. L., LORANT, F., BUDZINSKI, H., 2006. Study of biodegradation along the Carnaubais trend, Potiguar Basin (Brazil) - Part 1. Organic Geochemistry, 37, 1042 - 1051. BEAVINGTON-PENNEY, S. J., WRIGHT, V. P., BARNETT, A., KENNEDY, S., COVILL, M., 2019. Integration of static and dynamic data and high-resolution sequence stratigraphy to define reservoir architecture and flow units within a ‘super giant’ gas condensate and oil field, Kazakstan. Marine and Petroleum Geology, 101, 486 - 501. BERTANI, R. T., COSTA, I. G., MATOS, R. M. D., 1990. Evolução tectono-sedimentar, estilo estrutural e habitat do petróleo da Bacia Potiguar. In: RAJA GABAGLIA, G.
P., MILANI, E. J. (eds). Origem e Evolução de Bacias Sedimentares. Rio de Janeiro, Petrobras, 291 – 310. BI, H., LI, Z., TANG, Z, LI, P., WANG, L., SHANG, X., 2017. High-resolution sequence stratigraphy, sedimentology and reservoir quality evaluation of the Yaojia Formation in the Longxi area of the Western Slope, Songliao Basin, China. Marine and Petroleum Geology, 88, 511 - 530. BLUM, M. D., TORNQVIST, T. E, 2000. Fluvial response to climate and sea-level change: a review and look forward. Sedimentology, 47, 2 - 48. BORBA, C., PAIM, P. S. G., GARCIA, A. J. V., 2009. Estratigrafia de alta resolução 3D em depósitos deltaicos do início do rifte da Bacia de Sergipe-Alagoas: impacto na compartimentação de reservatórios. Boletim de Geociências da Petrobras,17 (2), 291-309. BOWN, T. M., KRAUS, M. J., 1987. Integration of channel and floodplain suites, I. Development of sequence and lateral relations of alluvial paleosols. Journal of Sedimentary Petrology, 57, 587-601. BOCKELIE, J.F., 1994. Plant roots in core. In: DONOVAN, S.K. (Ed.), The Palaeobiology of Trace Fossils. Wiley, Chichester, 177–199. BRIDGE, J. S., TYE, R. S., 2000. Interpreting the dimensions of ancient fluvial channel bars, channels and channel belts from wireline-logs and cores. American Association of Petroleum Geologists Bulletin. 84 (8), 1205 - 1228. BUATOIS, L.A., MÁNGANO, M.G., 2002. Trace fossils from Carboniferous floodplain deposits in western Argentina: implications for ichnofacies models of continental environments. Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology, 183, 71–86. BUATOIS, L.A., MÁNGANO, M.G., 2004. Animal-substrate interactions in freshwater environments: applications of ichnology in facies and sequence stratigraphic analysis of fluvio-lacustrine successions. In: McIlroy, D. (Ed.), The Application of Ichnology to Palaeoenvironmental and Stratigraphic Analysis. Geological Society of London, Special Publication, 228, 311 – 333.
BUATOIS, L.A., MÁNGANO, M.G., 2011. Ichnology: organism-substrate interactions BURNS, B. A., HELLER, P. L., MARZO, M., PAOLA, C., 1997. Fluvial response in a sequence stratigraphy framework. Journal of Sedimentary Research, 67 (2), 311 - 321.
CATUNEANU, O.; GALLOWAY, W.E.; KENDALL, C.G.St.C.; MIALL, A.D., POSAMENTIER, H.W. & STRASSER, A. 2011. Sequence Stratigraphy: Methodology and Nomenclature. Newsletters on Stratigraphy, 44 (3), 173-245. CATUNEANU, O., 2019. Model-independent sequence stratigraphy. Earth-Science Reviews, 188, 312 - 388.
COHEN, A.S., 1982. Paleoenvironments of root casts from the Koobi Fora Formation, Kenya. Journal of Sedimentary Petrology, 52, 401–414. COSTANTINI, E. A. C., 2018. Paleosols and pedostratigraphy. Applied Soil Ecology. 123, 597 – 600. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.apsoil.2017.09. 021 DALMAN, R., WELTJE, G. J., KARAMITOPOULOS, P., 2015. High-resolution sequence stratigraphy of fluvio-deltaic systems: Prospects of system-wide chronostratigraphic correlation. Earth and Planetary Science Letters, 412, 10 – 17.
DALRYMPLE, R. W., KURCINKA, C. E., JABLONSKI, B. V. J., ICHASO, A. A., MACKAY, D. A. 2015. Deciphering the relative importance of fluvial and tidal processes in the fluvial-tidal transition. In: ASHWORTH, P., BEST, J., PARSONS, D., (eds). Fluvial-Tidal sedimentology, Developments in Sedimentology, 68, Elsevier, 3 – 45. DÍEZ-CANSECO, D., BUATOIS, L. A., MÁNGANO, M.G., RODRIGUEZ, W., SOLORZANO, E., 2015. The ichnology of the fluvial-tidal transition: interplay of ecologic and evolutionary controls. In: ASHWORTH, P., BEST, J., PARSONS, D., (eds). Fluvial-Tidal sedimentology, Developments in Sedimentology, 68, 283 – 321. FANTI, F., CATUNEANU, O., 2010. Fluvial sequence stratigraphy: the Wapiti Formation, West-Central Alberta, Canada. Journal of Sedimentary Research, Volume 80, 320 – 338. FAROUQ ALI, S. M., 1973. Current status of steam injection as a method as a heavy oil recovery method. 24TH annual technical meeting of the petroleum society of CIM, Edmonton, Canada. FAROUQ ALI, S. M., MELDAU, R. F., 1978. Current steamflood field experience. 53rd Annual Fall Technical Conference and Exhibition of the Society of Petroleum DALRYMPLE, R. W., KURCINKA, C. E., JABLONSKI, B. V. J., ICHASO, A. A., MACKAY, D. A. 2015. Deciphering the relative importance of fluvial and tidal processes in the fluvial-tidal transition. In: ASHWORTH, P., BEST, J., PARSONS, D., (eds). Fluvial-Tidal sedimentology, Developments in Sedimentology, 68, Elsevier, 3 – 45.
DÍEZ-CANSECO, D., BUATOIS, L. A., MÁNGANO, M.G., RODRIGUEZ, W., SOLORZANO, E., 2015. The ichnology of the fluvial-tidal transition: interplay of ecologic and evolutionary controls. In: ASHWORTH, P., BEST, J., PARSONS, D., (eds). Fluvial-Tidal sedimentology, Developments in Sedimentology, 68, 283 – 321.
FLINT, S., KNIGHT, S., TILBROOK, A., 1998. Application of high-resolution sequence stratigraphy to northwest North Sea: implications for management of a mature Brent Group Field. AAPG Bulletim, 82 (7), 1416 - 1436. HANNEMAN, D. L., WIDEMAN, C. J., 2010. Chapter 5: Continental sequence stratigraphy and continental carbonates. In: ALONSO-ZARZA, A. M., TANNER, L. H., (EdS.), Carbonates in Continental Settings: Geochemistry, Diagenesis and Applications, Developments in Sedimentology, 62, 215-273. HASIOTIS, S.T., 2002. Continental Trace Fossil Short Course Number 51. SEPM, Tulsa, Oklahoma, 132 p. HORNUNG, J., AIGNER, T., 1999. Reservoir and aquifer characterization of fluvial architectural elements: Stubens and stein, Upper Triassic, southwest Germany. Sedimentary Geology, 129, 215–280. KEEVIL, C. E., PARSONS, D. R., KEEVIL, G. M., AINSLEY, M., 2015. Three-dimensional meander bend flow within the tidally influenced fluvial zone. In: ASHWORTH, P., BEST, J., PARSONS, D., (eds). Fluvial-Tidal sedimentology, Developments in Sedimentology, 68, 127 – 148.
Applications, Developments in Sedimentology, 62, 215-273. HASIOTIS, S.T., 2002. Continental Trace Fossil Short Course Number 51. SEPM, Tulsa, Oklahoma, 132 p. HORNUNG, J., AIGNER, T., 1999. Reservoir and aquifer characterization of fluvial architectural elements: Stubens and stein, Upper Triassic, southwest Germany. Sedimentary Geology, 129, 215–280.
KEEVIL, C. E., PARSONS, D. R., KEEVIL, G. M., AINSLEY, M., 2015. Three-dimensional meander bend flow within the tidally influenced fluvial zone. In: ASHWORTH, P., BEST, J., PARSONS, D., (eds). Fluvial-Tidal sedimentology, Developments in Sedimentology, 68, 127 – 148. KERR, D., YE, L., BAHAR, A., KELKAR, B. G., MONTGOMERY, S., 1999. Glenn Pool Field, Oklahoma: a case of improved prediction from a mature reservoir. American Association of Petroleum Geologists Bulletin. 83 (1), 1 - 18. KNAUST, D., 2017. Atlas of Trace Fossils in Well Core: Appearance, Taxonomy and Interpretation. Springer, Suiça, 209 p. KRAUS, M. J.; HASIOTIS, S. T., 2006. Significance of different modes of rhizolith preservation to interpretation of paleoenvironmental and paleohydrologic settings: Examples from Paleogene paleosols, Bighorn Basin, Wyoming, USA. Journal of Sedimentary Research, 76, 633-646. LABRECQUE, P. A., JENSEN, J. L., HUBBARD, S. M., 2011. Cyclicity in lower Cretaceous point bar deposits with implications for reservoir characterization, Athabasca Oil Sands, Alberta, Canada. Sedimentary Geology, 242, 18 - 33. MACEACHERN, J. A., PEMBERTON, S. G., GINGRAS, M. K., BANN, K .L., 2010. Ichnololy and Facies Models. In: JAMES, N. P. and DALRYMPLE, R. W. (eds). Facies Models 4. Geological Association of Canada, St. John’s Newfoundland, 19-dimensional meander bend flow within the tidally influenced fluvial zone. In: ASHWORTH, P., BEST, J., PARSONS, D., (eds). Fluvial-Tidal sedimentology, Developments in Sedimentology, 68, 127 – 148. KERR, D., YE, L., BAHAR, A., KELKAR, B. G., MONTGOMERY, S., 1999. Glenn Pool Field, Oklahoma: a case of improved prediction from a mature reservoir. American Association of Petroleum Geologists Bulletin. 83 (1), 1 - 18.
KRAUS, M. J.; HASIOTIS, S. T., 2006. Significance of different modes of rhizolith preservation to interpretation of paleoenvironmental and paleohydrologic settings: Examples from Paleogene paleosols, Bighorn Basin, Wyoming, USA. Journal of Sedimentary Research, 76, 633-646. LABRECQUE, P. A., JENSEN, J. L., HUBBARD, S. M., 2011. Cyclicity in lower Cretaceous point bar deposits with implications for reservoir characterization, Athabasca Oil Sands, Alberta, Canada. Sedimentary Geology, 242, 18 - 33. MACEACHERN, J. A., PEMBERTON, S. G., GINGRAS, M. K., BANN, K .L., 2010. Ichnololy and Facies Models. In: JAMES, N. P. and DALRYMPLE, R. W. (eds).
MACK, G. H., TABOR, N. J., ZOLLINGER, H. J., 2010. Palaeosols and sequence stratigraphy of the Lower Permian Abo Member, south-central New Mexico, USA. Sedimentology, 57, 1566 – 1583. MAGALHÃES, A.J.C, RAJA GABAGLIA, G.P., SCHERER, C.M.S., BÁLLICO, M.B., GUADAGNIN, F., BENTO FREIRE, E., SILVA BORN, L.R. & CATUNEANU, O. 2016. Sequence hierarchy in a Mesoproterozoic interior sag basin: from basin fill to reservoir scale, the Tombador Formation, Chapada Diamantina Basin, Brazil. Basin Research, 28, 393-423. MAGALHÃES, A. J. C., RAJA GABAGLIA, G. P., FRAGOSO, D. G. C., BENTO FREIRE, E., LYKAWKA, R., ARREGUI, C. D., SILVEIRA, M. M. L., CARPIO, K. M. T., De GASPERI, A., PEDRINHA, S., ARTAGÃO, V. M., TERRA, G. J. S., BUNEVICH, R. B., ROEMERS-OLIVEIRA, E., GOMES, J. P., BRUHN, C. H. L., 2020. High-resolution sequence stratigraphy applied to reservoir zonation and characterization, and its impact on production performance – shallow marine, fluvial downstream and lacustrine carbonate settings. Earth-Science Reviews. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2020.103325 MARRIOT, S. B., WRIGHT, V. P., 1993. Paleosols as indicators of geomorphic stability in two Old Red Sandstone alluvial suites, South Wales. Journal of Geological Society of London, 150, 1109-1120. MATOS, R. M. D., 1992. The northeast Brazilian rift system. Tectonics, 11 (4), 766 – 791. McCARTHY, P. J., PLINT, A. G., 1998. Recognition of interfluve sequence boundaries: Integrating paleopedology and sequence stratigraphy. Geology, 26 (5), 387 - 390. McCARTHY, P. J., PLINT, A. G., 2003. Spatial variability of palaeosols across Cretaceous interfluves in the Dunvengan Formation, NE British Columbia, Canada: palaeohydrological, palaeogeomorphological and stratigraphic implications. Sedimentology, 50, 1187 - 1220. McEACHERN, J. A., BANN, K. L., GINGRAS, M. K., ZONNEVELD, J. P., DASHTGARD, S. E., PEMBERTON, S.G., 2012. Chapter 4 – The Ichnofacies paradigm. In: KNAUST, D. AND RICHARD, G. B. (Ed.), Trace fossils as indicators of Sedimentary Environments, Developments in Sedimentology, 64, 103-138. MENEZES, L., 2004. Mapeamento digital de análogos a reservatórios petrolíferos: exemplo para depósitos fluviais da unidade Açu-3 – Bacia Potiguar. Msc Thesis.
MELCHOR, R. N., GENISE, J. F., BUATOIS, L. A., UMAZANO, A. M., 2012. Chapter 12 - Fluvial Environments. In: KNAUST, D. AND RICHARD, G. B. (Ed.), Trace fossils as indicators of Sedimentary Environments, Developments in Sedimentology, 64, 329-378. MELO, A. H., ANDRADE, P. R. O., MAGALHÃES, A. J. C., FRAGOSO, D. G. C., LIMA-FILHO, F. P., 2020. Stratigraphic evolution of early Cenomanian to late Campanian of Potiguar Basin, northeast Brazil: an approach in seismic scale. Basin Research, 32, 1054 – 1080. https ://doi.org/10.1111/bre.12414 MIALL, A. D., 1985. Architectural-element analysis: a new method of facies analysis applied to fluvial deposits. Earth-Science Reviews, 22, 261 – 308. MIALL, A. D., 1991. Stratigraphic Sequences and their chronostratigraphic correlation. Journal of Sedimentary Petrology, 61 (4), 497 – 505. MIALL, A. D., 2006. The Geology of Fluvial Deposits: Sedimentary Facies, Basin Analysis and Petroleum Geology. 4th corrected printing. Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg, 589 p. MIALL, A. D., 2014. Fluvial Depositional Systems. Springer International Publishing, Switzerland, 322 p. MITCHUM Jr, R.M, VAN WAGONER, J.C., 1991. High-frequency sequences and their stacking patterns: sequence stratigraphic evidence of high-frequency eustatic cycles. Sedimentary Geology, 70, 131-160. PESSOA NETO, O. C., SOARES, U. M., SILVA, J. G. F., ROESNER, E. H., FLORENCIO, C. P., SOUZA, C. A. V., 2007. Bacia Potiguar. Boletim de Geociências da Petrobras, 15 (2), 357-369. PLINK-BJORKLUND, P., 2005. Stacked fluvial and tide-dominated estuarine deposits in high-frequency (fourth-order) sequences of the Eocene Central Basin, Spitsbergen. Sedimentology, 52, 391 – 428.
MITCHUM Jr, R.M, VAN WAGONER, J.C., 1991. High-frequency sequences and their stacking patterns: sequence stratigraphic evidence of high-frequency eustatic cycles. Sedimentary Geology, 70, 131-160. PESSOA NETO, O. C., SOARES, U. M., SILVA, J. G. F., ROESNER, E. H., FLORENCIO, C. P., SOUZA, C. A. V., 2007. Bacia Potiguar. Boletim de Geociências da Petrobras, 15 (2), 357-369.
PLINK-BJORKLUND, P., 2005. Stacked fluvial and tide-dominated estuarine deposits in high-frequency (fourth-order) sequences of the Eocene Central Basin, Spitsbergen. Sedimentology, 52, 391 – 428. RANGER, M. J., PEMBERTON, S. G., 1992. The sedimentology and ichnology of estuarine point bars in the Mc Murray Formation of the Athabasca oil sands deposits, north-eastern Alberta, Canada. In: PEMBERTON, S. G. (ed) Applications of ichnology to petroleum exploration: A core workshop. SEPM Society for Sedimentary Geology, 17, 401 – 421. RETALLACK, G. J., 1988. Field recognition of paleosols. In: REINHARDT, J., SIGLEO, SAMPAIO, A. V., SCHALLER, H., 1968. Introdução à estratigrafia cretácea da Bacia Potiguar. Boletim Técnico da Petrobras, 11 (1), 19-44. SCHUMM, S. A., 1993. River response to base level change: implications for sequence stratigraphy. Journal of Geology, 101, 279 – 294. SHANLEY, K. W., McCABE, P. J., HETTINGER, R. D., 1992. Tidal Influence in Cretaceous fluvial strata from Utah, USA: a key to sequence stratigraphic interpretation. Sedimentology, 39, 905 – 930. SHANLEY, K. W., McCABE, P. J.,1994. Perspectives on the sequence stratigraphy of continental strata. American Associtation of Petroleum Geologists Bulletin, 78 (4), 544-568. STRASSER, A., HILGEN, F. J., HECKEL, P. H., 2006. Cyclostratigraphy – concepts, definitions and applications. Newsletter on Stratigraphy, 42 (2), 75 – 114. VAN WAGONER, J.C., MITCHUM Jr, R.M., CAMPION, K. M., RAHMANIAN, V.D., 1990. Siliciclastic sequence stratigraphy in well logs, core, and outcrops: concepts for high-resolution correlation of time and facies. In: American Association of Petroleum Geologists Methods in Exploration Series,7, 1 – 55. VASCONCELOS, E.P; LIMA NETO, F. F. E ROOS, S. 1990. Unidades de correlação da Formação Açu - Bacia Potiguar. In: SBG, Congresso Brasileiro de Geologia, 36, Natal, Anais, 1, 227 – 240. WAINMAN, C.C., McCABE, P. J. 2020. Correlation of fluvial strata in subsurface – a review. Marine and Petroleum Geology, 122. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2020.104611 WRIGHT, V. P., 1992. Paleosol recognition: a guide do early diageneses in terrestrial settings. In: WOLF, K. H., CHILINGARIAN, G. V. (eds), Diagenesis III, Developments in Sedimentology 47, 591 – 619. WRIGHT, V. P., MARRIOT, S. B., 1993. The sequence stratigraphy of fluvial deposits systems: the role of floodplain sediment storage. Sedimentary Geology, 86, 203-210. XUEMEI, D., HONGLIANG, W., 2016. High-resolution sequence stratigraphy in layer correlation: a case study Shahejie formation in Huanghua Depression. Journal of Petroleum Science and Engineering, 147, 1 - 6. ZECCHIN, M., CATUNEANU, O., 2015. High-resolution sequence stratigraphy of clastic shelves III: Applications to reservoir geology. Marine and Petroleum Geology, 62, 161 - 175.
SAMPAIO, A. V., SCHALLER, H., 1968. Introdução à estratigrafia cretácea da Bacia Potiguar. Boletim Técnico da Petrobras, 11 (1), 19-44. SCHUMM, S. A., 1993. River response to base level change: implications for sequence stratigraphy. Journal of Geology, 101, 279 – 294.
SHANLEY, K. W., McCABE, P. J., HETTINGER, R. D., 1992. Tidal Influence in Cretaceous fluvial strata from Utah, USA: a key to sequence stratigraphic interpretation. Sedimentology, 39, 905 – 930.
SHANLEY, K. W., McCABE, P. J.,1994. Perspectives on the sequence stratigraphy of continental strata. American Associtation of Petroleum Geologists Bulletin, 78 (4), 544-568.
VASCONCELOS, E.P; LIMA NETO, F. F. E ROOS, S. 1990. Unidades de correlação da Formação Açu - Bacia Potiguar. In: SBG, Congresso Brasileiro de Geologia, 36, Natal, Anais, 1, 227 – 240. WAINMAN, C.C., McCABE, P. J. 2020. Correlation of fluvial strata in subsurface – a review. Marine and Petroleum Geology, 122. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2020.104611 settings. In: WOLF, K. H., CHILINGARIAN, G. V. (eds), Diagenesis III, Developments in Sedimentology 47, 591 – 619. WRIGHT, V. P., MARRIOT, S. B., 1993. The sequence stratigraphy of fluvial deposits systems: the role of floodplain sediment storage. Sedimentary Geology, 86, 203-210.
XUEMEI, D., HONGLIANG, W., 2016. High-resolution sequence stratigraphy in layer correlation: a case study Shahejie formation in Huanghua Depression. Journal of Petroleum Science and Engineering, 147, 1 - 6. ZECCHIN, M., CATUNEANU, O., 2015. High-resolution sequence stratigraphy of
