Eﬀective Q, velocity trend and their relation to gas-hydrate distribution at Joetsu Knoll (Japan Sea).
Luiz Alberto Santos and Ryo Matsumoto
Joetsu basin is a well known site of massive gas hydrate. They lay along the ﬁrst hundred meters of Neogene sediments and, together with gas chimneys, they play important role in absorption of seismic waves. Five single-channel seismic lines are processed, interpreted and integrated to evaluate subsurface compressional velocity and eﬀective quality factor Qef f along the Joetsu Knoll. Diﬀraction velocity analysis (DVA) is used to estimate a smooth velocity ﬁeld for time migration. Along the processed lines, bottom simulating reﬂectors (BSR) are mapped and Qef f is estimated along them at Haizume Formation, the youngest and shallowest unit. Both, gas hydrate and gas-saturated sediments at gas chimneys contribute to the reduction of quality factor that is below 100 and averages 50 along those domains. BSR and gas-hydrate are conﬁned to the anticline structure and it
ABSTRACT narrows toward northeast. Estimated compressional velocity ﬁeld from DVA is very smooth, it ranges from 1500 m/s to 1750 m/s, respectively at sea-bottom and 2.4 s, and shows a very low vertical gradient of 0.225 s−1, typical of subcompacted sediments. Under the geological context of Joetsu Knoll and similars, eﬀective Q section is a key tool to locate gas exudation and gas-hydrate. worldwide. Futterman (1962) states that attenuation due to absorption is always observed in seismic data. The author add that absorption causes important impact in recorded wave shapes and amplitudes, due to dispersive character of the phenomenon. Santos (1986) estimated Q factor from VSP data from Campos Basin (oﬀshore Brazil) using spectral ratio and frequency shift techniques. Dasgupta and Clark (1998) applied spectral ratio concept to conventional surface seismic common midpoint (CMP) gathers and successfuly estimate Q factors for three case studies: the validation against VSP data in a site at North Sea; the use of Q factor as lithology discrimination among sedimentary and crystalline basement, the last showing higher Q values and; the eﬀect og gas evaluation in saturated reservoirs in a ﬁeld at UK North Sea. Wang (2003) presents the use of a stabilized inverse Q ﬁlter to a land Vertical Seismic Proﬁle (VSP) data set. According to the author, the method promotes robust estimation of Q values, the subsequent processing ﬂow ﬂattens the amplitude spectrum, it strengthens the time-variant amplitude, it increases the spectral bandwidth, and it improves the signal-to-noise ratio (S/N). Hornbach et al. (2003) point three direct indicators of gas hydrate at Blake Ridge, oﬀ the eastern coast of United States: a paleo bottom-simulating reﬂector (BSR); stratigraphic intervals of high velocity and low amplitude (blanking) and; bright spots within the hydrate stability zone due to upward gas. Based on observations at Outer Blake Ridge (US coast), Malik (Canada), Nankai Trough (oﬀshore Japan)], at diﬀerent depositional environments and at diﬀerent frequency ranges, Dvorkin and Uden (2004) states that, despite hydrate bearing sediments are stiﬀer, and then presenting higher velocities, they always promote very high attenuation to seismic waves. ratio and frequency shift techniques. Dasgupta and Clark (1998) applied spectral ratio concept to conventional surface seismic common midpoint (CMP) gathers and successfuly estimate Q factors for three case studies: the validation against VSP data in a site at North Sea; the use of Q factor as lithology discrimination among sedimentary and crystalline basement, the last showing higher Q values and; the eﬀect og gas evaluation in saturated reservoirs in a ﬁeld at UK North Sea. Wang (2003) presents the use of a stabilized inverse
INTRODUCTION data but emphasize the need for high resolution in geophysical data. Cavalca et al. (2011) use the concept of attenuated traveltime tomography to estimate interval Q and sucessfully determine a known low Q zone along 3D survey oﬀshore Australia. Gamar et al. (2015) use high resolution Q-tomography technique to automatically detect shallow gas pockets at Brunei. Li et al. (2018) applied improved peak frequency shift to estimate Q factor using time migration gathers in a 2D seismic line in Sichuan Basin (China) and conclude quality factor can be used for hydrocarbon detection. Ramos et al. (2019) discuss stabilized inverse Q ﬁltering and apply this technique to improve 3D stacked seismic data at Blake Ridge. Joetsu Basin is a well known site of massive gas hydrate (GH). GH lay along the ﬁrst hundred meters of Neogene sediments that are mainly composed of clay and silt (Matsumoto et al., 2001). Ascendent gas locally cut the sediment pile through chimneys reaching the sea-ﬂoor and continue upward along the water column. Such geologically active environment causes diﬀerences in physical properties of sediments and rocks and their ﬁllings (gas, water or solid GH) that are sensitive to seismic signal. Despite the avaialability of seismic data and the geological characteristics, Joetsu Basin has very few dedicated research to understand Q distribution, its relation to gas hydrate and its relation to compressional velocity. Santos et al. (2009) estimate eﬀective Q (Qef f ) in a seismic line along the hinge zone of Joetsu anticline. They ﬁnd low Qef f values, ranging from 50 to 60, agreeing with the GH zone and higher eﬀective Q, above 100, out of the gas hydrate domain. Freire et al. (2011) report average velocity between 1618 and 1659 m/s for Haizume Formation based on two wells drilled at Umitaka Spur, a structure southward Joetsu anticline. Correlating the heat ﬂow information, the gas-hydrate stability pressure-temperature curve and two-way seismic time of BSR, Matsumoto et al. (2011) estimate velocity of host sediments ranging from 1000 to 1150 m/s along the knoll and from 1170 and 1230 m/s in the troughs. Santos et al. (2020) use diﬀractions to estimate the Normal Moveout (NMO) velocity that range from 1500 to 1580 m/s along Haizume formation.
The present work contributes to the characterization of eﬀective Q and dominant frequency pattern at Joetsu Knoll. Also, due to the employed processing ﬂow on single-channel seismic lines - based on diﬀraction velocity analysis - a smooth interval velocity ﬁeld is estimated. We employ those properties to map and process seismic data and to enhance Bottom Simulating Reﬂector (BSR). To address the proposed objectives we divide this work in ﬁve topics: Methodology, Description of geophysical data, Processing ﬂow and properties estimation, Discussion and Conclusions. In Methodology we revisit theoretical aspects of spectral characterization, explain a pragmatic routine to enhance high amplitude events. After describing the characteristics of geophysical data in the second session, we follow to Processing ﬂow and properties estimation session. There, we detail the estimation of interval velocity, we apply the enhancement of high amplitudes to highlight BSR and we detail the estimation of eﬀective Q in Haizume Formation along Joetsu anticline. To illustrate the methodology we make use of the strike line JK153. The following topic, discussion of the results, we make use of dip lines. Finally, in the last session we present the conclusions.
Theoretical aspects of spectral characterization
Stairing a seismic section in time domain, an observer often notices resolution losses with increasing time. There is a time-dependent frequency variation. Considering u(xsrc, xrec, t) as the recorded waveﬁeld at the surface (the seismogram) for a shot given at position xsrc, and receiver at position xrec, the Fourier transform of each trace is given by equation 1.
METHODOLOGY where t is time, xsrc is seismic source location in horizontal, xrec is the receiver location in horizontal, ω is angular frequency, i is √ 1 and U (xsrc, xrec, ω) is the recorded wave-−
ﬁeld in frequency domain. Amplitude spectrum of seismic data can be calculated from U (xsrc, xrec, ω). It shows the general behavior of each trace and it is often used to estimate dominant frequency and lateral energy variation. However, time-dependent variation of spectrum can not be located and evaluated with equation 1. Castagna and Sun (2006) present a variety of spectral decompositon methods. Among them: windowed dis-crete Fourier Transform (DFT), maximum entropy method (MEM), continuous wavelet transform (CWT), matching pursuit decomposition (MPD) and exponential pursuit decomposition (EPD). Eventhough the authors state there is no right or wrong method for time-frequency analysis, they enhance the advantages of EPD. in horizontal, ω is angular frequency, i is √ 1 and U (xsrc, xrec, ω) is the recorded wave-− ﬁeld in frequency domain. Amplitude spectrum of seismic data can be calculated from In this work we employ the windowed DFT as it directly relates amplitude sprectrum to a speciﬁc time window. Thus, the local spectrum is evaluated by multiplying u(xsrc, xrec, t) to a Gaussian function g(t), equation 2, that performs windowing around a given time τ . (1) U (xsrc, xrec, τ, ω) is the windowed Fourier transform of recorded waveﬁeld. g(t, τ ) is a gaussian function centered at τ .
Equations 1, 2 and 3 are described for general 2D seismic survey. For 2D zero-oﬀset or migrated data we may consider, for short, u(xrec, t), U (xrec, ω), U (xrec, τ, ω) instead of tion and remaining text we refer the terms dominant and peak frequency as synonymous. From the amplitude spectrum of U (xrec, τ, ω) we extract the dominant frequency at each time, through the operation
Enhancement of high amplitude events
Consider the amplitude seismic data, u(xrec, t), is composed by two classes of events: high amplitude and another class with lower amplitudes, below a certain value. After normal-ization of the amplitudes, consider the mean values of high and low amplitude classes are respectively uhigh(xrec, t) and ulow(xrec, t). When powering the entire seismic data a value
F (xrec, τ ) = argωmax U (xrec, τ, ω) . { }
Thus, with suitable high p, the resulting section with enhanced high amplitudes (EHA) uenhance(xrec, t) is calculated by
Geology of Joetsu Basin
The Japan Sea is a back-arc basin formed behind the Japanese island-arc system initiated by the rifting of the eastern margin of the Eurasian Continent at approximately 25 My (Tamaki and Isezaki, 1996). During the Middle Pliocene, the tectonic style changed from extensional to compressive (Tamaki, 1988), and a series of north-northeastsouth-southwest-trending folds, such as the Joetsu Knoll, were formed along the eastern margin of the Japan Sea. During the Miocene, anoxic conditions favored the high production of organic matter deposited in the Nanatani and Teradomari Formations (Okui et al., 2008). From the Late Miocene to the Late Pliocene, the Japan Sea was tectonically stable, and coarse-grained sediments of the Shiiya Formation were transported and deposited (Okui et al., 2008). Mudstone, sandstones, and also volcanics of the Nishiyama Formation overlie the Shiiya Formation. Over the Nishiyama layer, clay-bearing sediments of the Haizume Formation have been deposited since the Late Pleistocene (Son et al., 2001).
Joetsu Basin is a very active geological system. Machiyama et al. (2009) report present day average heat ﬂow in a muddy sea-ﬂoor at Joetsu Basin equal to 98 +/- 13 mW/m2. And it overcomes 150 mW/m2 at methane venting and mounds along the hinge line of Joetsu Knoll. Matsumoto et al. (2011) report those mounds and pockmarks are 50 to 500 m wide and 10 to 50 m deep and they are sea-ﬂoor expression of gas chimneys below. The existence of source rock of Miocene units (Nanatani and Teradomari Formations), the thermal history of the Joetsu Basin, and the vertical fault system at the apex of the Joetsu anticline provide the necessary means for the precipitation of hydrates at the Haizume Formation. According to Matsumoto et al. (2011), bottom simulating reﬂectors (BSR) are often paralell to layering and; based on stability conditions of gas hydrates and heat ﬂow information, they estimate BSR lie 115m below sea-ﬂoor (bsf) at the crest of Joetsu Knoll and 135 m in the trough.
DESCRIPTION OF GEOPHYSICAL DATA
Technology (JAMSTEC). The source, an air-gun cluster, is towed 30m far from the ship and the depths range from 1.5 to 7.4m deep. The receiver device was a SIG-type streamer with 48 channels, they are towed with minimum oﬀset of 136.5 m from the source, and the distance between each channel is 1 m. After time-shift correction, all recorded channels are stacked to compose a single station per shot. The data is recorded at a 0.001 s sampling rate. Four seismic lines are used in this study (Figure 1) and they are named JKm, which m means line number: 109, 114, 117 124 and 153. JK153 is a strike line paralell to Joetsu Knoll hinge northeast ward. From southwest to northeast (Figure 1) there are dip lines JK109, JK114, JK117 and JK124, they are orthogonal to JK153 and they have northwest direction. Those lines are selected because of their extensions and their long linear segments that favour the processing ﬂow and analysis.
Basically, on the next topics we present sections with ﬁve attributes or properties: seismic amplitude, EHA, dominant frequency, eﬀective Q and interval velocity. For all sections we show the BSR and the intersections with crossing lines. For strike line JK153 there are always four vertical lines that correspond to the intersection to dip lines JK109, JK114, JK117 and JK124. Dip lines are adressed in the discussion session and they are also displayed with intepreteted BSR and with a vertical line that represents the intersection with JK153. Strike line JK-153 is displayed from left, SW, to right, NE; and dip lines are all displayed from left, SE, to right, NW.
PROCESSING FLOW AND PROPERTIES ESTIMATION
The processing ﬂow described in Santos et al. (2020) was repeated individually on seismic lines JK109, JK114, JK117, JK124 and JK153. It involves trace edition, static correction, band-pass ﬁltering, geometric spreading correction, predictive deconvolution, diﬀraction velocity analysis (DVA), Kirchhoﬀ time migration and mute above sea level. During ﬁltering step we applied a trapezoidal ﬁlter equal to 5, 15, 180, 200 Hz. After the described processing ﬂow the resulting strike section JK153 is displayed at Figure 2.
Estimation of velocity along Haizume Formation
Normal moveout equivalent velocity is estimated for each line using the DVA method of Santos et al. (2020). Beyond being an input for imaging, interval velocity is estimated from NMO velocity (Dix, 1955). Despite the resulting interval velocity is too smooth and without resolution to detail thin events and gas chimneys, it is able to identify main trends. Figure 3 shows the resulting interval velocity in time domain for strike line JK153. The general trend increases from 1500 m/s at sea-bottom and reaches 1750 m/s at 2.4 s. Smooth lateral velocity changes are noticed along the section. One of them, in the shallow region is around station 2000 that is close to a mound and the steep slope of NE side (right) of the Joetsu Knoll.
Each interval velocity section is time-to-depth converted. From the smooth velocity ﬁeld in depth, we calculate vertical velocity gradient. The histogram, Figure 4, reveals dominant trend of 0.225 s−1. Such vertical gradient is much lower than it is expected for a normal clastic sequence in marine environment (Rosa, 2010), that is around 0.600 s−1. Negative gradients are present and they are mapped by DVA. They would be useful to map gas clouds, but a higher resolution is necessary to use this information. Gradients close to 0.600 s−1 and higher are found along the data set, but they are minor events.
Enhancement of BSR
BSRs are usually not diﬃcut features to be mapped. In Joetsu Basin, however, they often appear paralell to the layering (Matsumoto et al. (2011) and Freire et al. (2011)) which turns mapping of BSR a diﬃcult task. As bottom simulating reﬂector is an isotherm boundary and it deﬁnes a phase transition (solid hydrate above and gas below), it shows high amplitude due to its high reﬂectivity.
We power the processed seismic lines using a p equal to 10 (equation 6). This procedure enhances high amplitude events and highlighten the BSR along its expected position along EHA lines. Figure 5 show the EHA section for strike line JK153.
Q estimation along Haizume Formation
Application of windowed Fourier Transform, equation 3, needs the calibration of σ parame-ter of the gaussian function g(t) to set suitable time window size. Low σ focuses the spectral behavior and high σ causes bluring with adjacent events. Because we performed trapezoidal ﬁltering (5-15-180-200 Hz) in the processing ﬂow, the data has no period higher than 0.2 s. We applied a σ that imposes a time window of 0.4 s, twice the maximum period. This choice allows correct evaluation of periods equal or lower than 0.2 s at the central region of the gaussian, so considering low relevant frequency close to 5 Hz. Bluring due to adjacent events exists but it is attenuated by the gaussian tails.
From the amplitude spectrum of U (xrec, τ, ω), dominant frequency at each position and time is calculated by equation 4. Figure 6 presents dominant frequency at section JK153. There are lateral changes of the peak frequency, but the main behavior shows a decreasing pattern from the sea-bottom toward deeper depth or higher time.
The eﬀective Q (Qef f ) is calculated with equation 5 for each line. Due to lateral vari-ations of peak frequencies and their vertical gradients, there are remarkable changes in eﬀective Q. At strike section JK153, Figure 7, a region with Qef f averaging 50 is hugely limited to the occurence of BSR. The NE limit of BSR, close to station 2000, coincides to a noticeable low eﬀective Q invading shallow sediments, it agrees to a known gas chimney and it is expressed on the sea-ﬂoor by a mound (Figures 2 and 6).
We integrate the sections of enhanced high amplitude attribute, dominant frequency, eﬀective Q and velocity of each dip section JK109, JK114, JK117 and JK124, respectively at
DISCUSSION
Figures 8, 9, 10 and 11. that enhanced high amplitude attribute turns the BSR mapping easier at the study area of Joetsu. BSR is not observed with enhanced high amplitude section at JK124, Figure 11. Solid hydrate may disappear or become too sparse from somewhere between line JK117 and JK124. The dominant frequency general behavior shows decreasing values from the sea-bottom to higher times, or depth, along all analyzed seismic sections. However there are lateral changes that impose vertical frequency gradient variation along each line. At JK153, frequencies are higher than 120 Hz and reaches 200 Hz near the sea-bottom, Figure 6. The gradient toward low frequencies, below 90 Hz, is roughly higher along the region where the BSR is interpreted, thus indicating higher absorption in that domain. Along lines JK109, JK114 and JK117 the higher gradient toward lower dominant frequencies also agrees with mapped BSR (Figures 8.b, 9.b and 10.b) and coincides to the hinge of Joetsu anticline. At section JK124, despite there is no mapped BSR, the higher gradient from high to low dominant frequencies, also occurs along the anticline hinge, Figure 11.b. It indicates that, the JK124 region is a locus without massive hydrate, but there is upward gas migration beside a huge gas chimney, the same pointed at station 2000 of strike line JK153.
Along the anticline structure it is observed a pattern change on the lateral distribution of peak frequencies. At JK109 the SE ﬂank shows higher dominant frequencies than NW ﬂank, Figure 8.b. All other dip sections, JK114, JK117 and JK124, show opposite behavior, as their SE ﬂank show lower peak frequencies compared to NW ﬂank, Figures 9.b, 10.b and 11.b. The reason for such behavior is not completely understood.
Eﬀective Q lower than 100 and averaging 50 occurs along a region greater than the BSR limit as observed at strike line JK153 (Figure 7). At JK109 this low-Qef f occupies the SE ﬂank and hinge of the anticline, Figure 8.c. At JK114, hinge and both ﬂanks exhibit eﬀective Q averaging 50, Figure9.c. JK117 shows a pattern resembling JK109, but narrower than JK114 as observed at Figure 10.c. Line JK124 shows the narrowest region with Qef f averaging 50 (Figure 11.c). This northeastward narrowing of low-Qef f width agrees with anticline structure narrowing toward northeast and a progressive decrease in hydrate concentration at shallow region of Haizume Formation. Hydrate prone sediments has lower Q than sediments without hydrates (Dvorkin et al., 2004). Thus, the resulting geometry of low-Qef f at studied sections in Joetsu anticline allow to map gas-hydrate zone close to the sea-ﬂoor and gas-chimneys in depth.
All estimated velocities show quite monotonical behavior as observed at Figures 8.d, 9.d, 10.d and 11.d. Despite its low spatial frequency, interval velocity derived from diﬀraction velocity analysis highlighten some upward gas chimneys just below mapped mounds. An example of that may be seen at station 600 of JK114, Figure 9.d, where a lateral velocity change occurs due to a gas chimney also expressed by two mounds at the sea-bottom. Diﬀraction velocity analysis allows to extract geologically feasible characteristics and gives normal move-out velocity for time migration. However, it lacks high frequency information (Zilmer et al., 2006) for further estimation and interpretation. Detailed velocity ﬁeld may be achieved with high resolution tomography over multi-channel seismic data, not accessed in this study.
The most often vertical velocity gradient of 0.225 s−1 is, indeed, too low for a shallow clastic sequence. The high heat ﬂow (Yasui et al.(2012), Matsumoto et al. (2011) and Machyiama et al. (2009)), hydrocarbon (gas) generation, upward ﬂuid migration, gas chimneys and local ﬂuid trapping increase pore-pressure, decrease eﬀective stress, so, reduce compressional speed and its vertical gradient.
Velocity gradient, peak frequency, low eﬀective Q and EHA sections are useful tools for fast evaluation areas like Joetsu Knoll. DVA in SCS does not allow estimation of detailed velocity ﬁeld. It delivers, however, a low frequency velocity that is able and is useful to estimate general trend of compressional velocity. At Haizume Formation in Joetu knoll, velocity ranges from 1500 to 1750 m/s with a gentle trend of 0.225 s−1 which suggests subcompaction of sediments. Low eﬀective Q area averages 50 and circumscribes gas-hydrate. Beyond mapping BSR and gas-hydrate occurence area, it is suitable to locate gas chimneys. The geometry and width of gas-hydrate is conditioned to the anticline geometry and it narrows toward northeast, circumscript to the low-Qef f area. Under this geologic context, sediment composition and granulometry, eﬀective Q section or volume is an important and useful seismic derived property to automatically locate gas exudation and gas-hydrate.
We would like to thank the geophysicists XXXX and YYYYYY, both from BRBR-BRBR for their valuable contribution and comments. We are also thankful to DDD
CONCLUSIONS
AKNOWLEGMENTS and the crew of JJJ cruises due to data availability.
Avseth, P., Mukerji, T., Mavko, G., 2005, Quantitative seismic interpretation, Cambridge University Press. Burnett, W., and S. Fomel, 2011, Diﬀraction velocity analysis by path-integral seismic imaging: 81st Annual International Meeting, SEG, Expanded Abstracts, 38983902.
Cavalca, M., Moore, I., Zhang L., Leng, S., Fletcher, R. and Bayly, M., 2011, Ray-based tomography for Q estimation and Q compensation in complex media, 81st Annual International Meeting, SEG, Expanded Abstracts, 3989-3993.
Castagna, J.P. and Sun, S., 2006, Comparison of spectral decomposition methods: First Break, 24, p.75-79.
Dasgupta, R. and Clark, R. A., 1998, Estimation of Q from surface seismic reﬂection data. Geophysics vol. 63, no.6, 2120-2128.
Dix, C.H., 1955, Seismic velocities from surface measurements: Geophysics, 20,1, p. 68-86.
Futterman, W. I., 1962, Dispersive body waves: Journal of Geophysical Research, v. 67, n. 13, p. 52795291.
REFERENCES
Gamar, F., Carotti, D., Guillaume, P., Gacha, A. and Lopes, L., 2015, Success of high-resolution volumetric Q-tomography in the automatic detection of gas anomalies on oﬀshore Brunei data, 85th Annual International Meeting, SEG, Expanded Abstracts, 5184-5188.
Li, S., Gao, J., Zhang, B. and Wang, S., 2018, Q estimation method and its application on the middle of Sichuan basin, 88th Annual International Meeting, SEG, Expanded Abstracts, 1549-1553.
Machiyama, H., Kinoshita, M., Takeuchi, R., Matsumoto, R., Yamano, M., Hamamoto, H., Hiromatsu, M., Satoh, M and Komatsubara, J., 2009, Heat ﬂow distribution around the Joetsu Gas hydrate ﬁeld, Western Joetsu Basin, Eastern Margin of the Japan Sea: Journal of Geography, v. 118, n.5, p. 986-1007.
Okui, A., Kaneko, M., Nakanishi, S., Monzawa, N., Yamamoto, H., 2008, An Integrated Approach to Understanding the petroleum system of a Frontier deep-water area, oﬀshore Japan. Petroleum Geosciences 14, 1-12.
Ramos, E.C., Costa, F.T., Santos, M.A.C., Santos, L.A., Santos, R.A., Soares Filho, D.M., 2019, Frequency Domain Q Analysis and Stabilized Inverse Q Filtering: Blake Ridge data application. XVI International Congress of the Brazilian Geophysical Society.
Santos, R. A., 1986, Perﬁl Sismico Vertical: Separa¸c˜ao de Campos de Onda e Obten¸c˜ao do Fator Q. Master Thesis Universidade Federal da Bahia.
Santos, L.A., Freire, A.F.M., Matsumoto, R., 2009, Q estimation in hydrate bearing sediments at Joetsu Knoll - Japan Sea. XI International Congress of the Brazilian Geophysical Society.
Son, B.K., Yoshimura, T., Fukazawa, H., 2001, Diagenesis of Dioctahedral and Trioc-tahedral Smectites from Alternating beds in Miocene to Pleistocene rocks of the Niigata basin, Japan. Clays and Clay Minerals 49 (4), 333-346.
Zilmer, M., 2006, A method for determining gas-hydrate or free-gas saturation of porous media from seismic measurements. Geophysics, V. 71, n0 3, N21-N32.
NE NE NE NE NE time and space and, they show the intersection with the strike line JK153 represented by vertical lines close to station 500. a) enhanced high amplitude and BSR drawn in red; b) peak frequency with BSR drawn in black; c) effective Q and BSR mapped in white. The black arrow highlight two mounds and low-Q zones reaching the sea-floor just below the mounds; d) interval velocity and BSR mapped in black. The black arrow points to the lateral velocity change related to the region below the two mounds.
