ocl t y ­ Mr. J.;:. -l .£. ....'"" ..10n w did _ cal onEl eklrum 'J n •
REs ction TH] AL 
PETROBRA.S
PETltOI.EO IU{ASII.EIRO S. A.
• •
•
• I P E -
PETROBRAS
- Cl 
I P E -
PETROBRAs
CCOCllDtU1Y After the usual polarity checks the wellphone was lowered in the hole, Shots were taken from both sides for gach wellphone position, When it seemed there would be a shortage of holes on the second day some positions were only shot from one direction. As — only one blaster was available (all spare blasters had been sent to Hr McDonald in Bahia) the crew experienced delays in moving the one blaster from one side to the other.“ lhe survey was stopped on the first day at 2350 hours as batteries were low and wellphone sensitivity seemed to have fallen off. ‘the survey was completed on the second day. A repeat shot at shallower level after the survey Was ended indicated that the wellphone sensitivity level had dropped appreciably (enel. 2).
•
• I P E.
PETROBR.AS
PETROI,EO BRASILEIRO 8. A.
The velocity curves obtained from this well survey show a normal amount of scattering of the observations, Below 600 meters we find a steady increase of the average velocity. lhe section between the surface and 600 meters seems to be anomalous. the higher interval and average velocities may be caused by dolomite, gypsum and graniteboulder conglomerate, the lower velocities by a postulated fault zone,
.....11 t 1 • The same thing happened in uphole No Z. But, as charges were blown out, this hole was washed and loaded one charge at a time, o tl " ~ A C ~ t 0 0 <:"; I P E -
PETROBRA.S
PETROLI<:O RRASIJ.EIRO 8. A • o • I P E -
PETROBRA.S
Comparison with the results of uphole No 1 shows that ali depths are erroneous.
I P E - à b 2 A é 4 à 4 1 - 7 ram e o , - - meme a e a gastam creo mar ent ti im mara mama _ PET CORTA IPEN CRS IRF DEC TE Sar, Shs png a tin as PT ae aman Ah ais PR re hae. pr EI Vice Es vee cient ata RR mi en eae Ab TLD TT ieee NTE SE STA Rc RT EG RAT NS RE ERE SCY ANS TREAT Pa (DTT ST IRC PRE en REC Pa Ui ea 0] EST O Oa, Cana ne : 7 ” ad ISSA VE - 1 i 3 i : y i FI ‘ ¢ f ' pow A 1 ; À { ¥ / , i i ond K “e O ee Po ro ra pre pi era e e ta ma mr ar e im ter e ir e e epa tr e rn rir eS e rr dry GT O a O a ND aC TR E O GO E Ten me A PS Se OU 1 ar at gema eae o ee ee meo r i : a i : 4 ; 7 ; | - ; | Ar | lM F . . by sty } A : ‘ 4 ) i , , 3 ; i { | y } Ris ; Se ee aa a A a at a ne ee ae OE emacs recai am capas nto ie ia rio e pera mn maio imita mpi pa iria ee tiene a ar ee CE SS wha 1 : E | i , : , À i , y , ; i À cee = wae) Lute nd, an o a a oro a SSD Cao caem Ena Dn casar Ee no andas a Rea es Do AD E SE ES A SS DO DO O a SO) De SOI So Se eme emo em mem DR RR SSS Se a? a ; p A aS | : } { : aes ‘ V «A À SST IO fee mena MEE TAY sr e" O CR E a ae ee (Ed E UT SS E a E CE SU DU As E a Le CL a ener (i a Th as > : . i , ? RES? | vein? en Hd (ech enna y Ar Aa et es ged: } . } i rg | : ? a PE 2 i : r 1 ! pte H ‘ | eden i 4 y E : 5 ‘ Report No ZF —" a iene EAD memo ra eco em mai e eee rtp dt e en a mt a e rea mer rien pi terei rr at a rar tri rear iai rins Be, on rae ae ee Ne ee “mo tm ot te e E a ae a O an eee O A ec O So cao co eso «am een e EL er é ça ja ees 2 NA ; . 1 ; í ; 4 | ; f . ‘ V peal TR et A a a a Ta mr erem SEM ne RES SEE On Te OT I OC OA LCN LEON LOO LAT ELL OS A OO ha IY LE med a ERIN BC me tr bh ei e teme mt tri mr ar nn tt ts fit ee rt ne we a cp thar VOA. oy ee aro feed ema EA | i 4 { | Ce o 5 ce | | é AM O aaa Oe Sd ed DS DS SOS UND. UNE ESSES UU NES GUNS a OU O O SS a See oe am mera nm neo acta tag mea a oro ra ag rea et ae net aa A ne eee nf arraia come rem imem gêmo lien — LL E array eo A 3 : 7 , j aa fabian ee coa vaneve tt if i : ! É E A ; ' , ER) fc aaa Ra tt e e o ed raio terre a aerea rear er tr eder import mi De prt rio mese prt mes ra iris cm tre nc a ER EE A EUA TIA Da A CD qt e 1 O SÁ eed PPS at DADO NOC A A Ás a cn AR (SONI 2) ne Ta Ve miar Sr aum mae NIV TATE oo a 5 ; ' . ; 4 1 ; 4 ‘a : : é x RA eS tr pm a EN a no DS a SOUNDS SUN UNS AS RS ES NS SUDO OA a An param isa nen ep cs a tee dm de e eme tee prato pure dear mm mA i qi e IO a ta laio ii a ane PETROBRÁS — Bene at ny) Se ‘ | 1 ‘Lang ; : : } ee Neder SSE SD ae o op ig tag MO Se Gia SANE IY Nei SEE I ic LD SIE, Th a ce SE ee arbre ool E
PETROBRAs
PETROI,EO BRASlI,EIRO !§. A.
IPE-
PETROBRAs
Positions of well geophone in IM-1-Al for well velocity survey tin mo) 55 175 Top dolomite, gypsum and bituminous shale section 226 Base of sane : 361 Base granite boulder conglomerate 495 ‘Yop postulated fault zone with associated asphaltic oil in fractures 600 Base of sane 700 Pronouneed change in dip and strike, unconformity or fault? 835 Change to normal dip amount and direction (base of above unconformity?) 950 First massive sand with good oil show and porosity 10 1220 Top of shale interval plus possible unconformity; dip change 1530 lho Base of sme . 1550 1800 1900 2000 Din irregularities, minor unconformity? 2100 a “ a " j 2300 “ ay a “o 2500 2600 Change from Weil, to N.Z, dip PO I P E -
PETRODRA.S
• • • •
Enel,
I F' E - r i l l i ng an oot ' the e l t to ODe t •
