As paginas citadas referem-se ao documento original e nao ao arquivo eletrOnico We enclose one copy of a geological subsurface progress report of the Rio Sao Francisco Embayment area, The enbayment constitutes one of the most favorable areas in the basin for petroleum exploration, The small production obtained from several wells and the favorable stratigraphic section in the embaymemt make regionel and detailed subsurface studies imperative, The enclosed report is a study of the formation thicknesses and structure contours, and their relationship with primary oil migration and entrapment, In general, isopach maps often reveal old structures which may have been masked during later periods of tectonic movenent, Quite often oil accumulations are “related to these older structures rather than to present day structures defined by surface or geophysical eel This seems to be true of the oil discoveries in the Muribeca formation in RSF-l-Al and Pia-l-Al, Subsurface studies of the type presented in this report will be expanded "to other areas in the basin, In addition, detailed facies studies will be incorporated with the isopach and structural contour mapping in erder to locate maximum sandstone developments along old structural trends, These favorable areas will then be superimposed en seismic contour maps, By this method we hope te upgrade our prepesed well locations, The maps of the progress report indicate that the interpretations presented in the Basin Study have stood the test of time, and that the general concepts are valid end will be modified only in local areas as additional information is obtained from the wells. surface geology and seismic surveys, EJB/-keb ees Drs Ls Mota Pastas «6 Reading file Colel Maceio, Alagoas 30 Novenbro
SFRGIPE-ALAGOAS BASIN BRAZIL by E.J.Bauer GEOLOGICAL SUBSURFACE PROGRESS REPORT OF THE RIO SÃO FRANCISCO IMBAYMENT AREA INTRODUCTION: The Rio São Frantisco Embayment is located in the general region of the mouth of the Rio Sao Francisco, in the state of Sergipe and Ala goas, Geologically, it is a structural minimum which contains a thick sedi = mentary section composed of essentially all of the formations encountered in the Sergipe-Alagoas Basin, The discovery of small amounts of oil in 5 wells on the À lagoas side of the enbayment has given hope to finding commercial oil reser ves in the area, The oil occurrences are related to either structural or stratigraphic traps, or a combination of both, However, all oil sandstones are apparently lenticular, and thus it is difficult to predict their presence or absence from one area to another, PURPOSE OF REPORT: The report deals principally with isopach and structure contour maps of the formations which have apparent economic importance in the embayment area, The first, clear analysis of the regional subsurface geo= logy of the area was presented in the Basin Study, Since the time of comple= tion of this study, additional information has been obtained from other wells. These deta are incorporated into the various maps included with this progress report, The maps will serve as general guides for the more detail ed studies being made by the various geologists and seismologists working in the basin, Local geological anomalies, either structural or stratigraphic , will necessarily modify portions of the regional illustrations, This will be especially true of the structure contour maps as essentially no consideration was given to local structure during the preparation of these maps, Because of insufficient data the Meruim formation was not studied, and therefore, is not discussed in this report, Calumbi Formation: The isopach map of the Calumbi formation confirms earlier interpretations as presented in the Basin Study, Modifications were made in the Piaçabuçu area as a result of the new information obtained from the wells in this wildcat areas E The closely spaced isopach lines between the Fiaçabuçu and Rio São Francisco wells illustrate the magnitude of sedimentary thickening in the latter wells, in addition te the structural downwerping which accompanied depesition, According te the paleontological studies, the Calumbi formation represents onlap deposition onto the shallower areas of the south flank of the Penedo Arch, Younger Calumbi sediments were deposited progressively on older recks as the Calumbi sea slowly advanced toward the northwest, Setex-Serdeste's September monthly report contains paleontologist Troelsen's discug gion and panel diagram illustration of the Calumbi onlap.
The Calumbi formation apparently is completely eroded and overlapped by “Older Tertiary" sediments a short distance northwest of the Piacabucu and Feliz Deserto wells, A structure contourinap on the top of the Calumbi formation is not included with this progress report as the top is essentially a plane surface, and apparently does not reflect underlying structures, A contour map of the base of the formation was made in order to illustrate the regional structy res of the pre-Calumbi erosion surface, This map is discussed in later pa ragraphs under the heading of STRUCTURE CONTOUR-BASE OF THE CAIWMBI FORMA= TION, Sapucari Formation: Detailed studies are being made of the Sapucari forma tion although as yet the formation has unproven economic importence as an accumulator of petroleum, It should be mentioned, however, that oil shows have been observed in the limestone fractures of the formation in several wells in the basin, In addition, the formation's favorable stratigraphic position in the Calumbi covered areas of the embayment indicated that pro= duceable oil may be found in the fractures or porosities of the Sapucari .
All of the Piaçabuçu wells have encountered Sapuceri sections of varying thicknesses, The isopach map shows that the formatioh pinches-out between these wells and the Rio São Francisco and Feliz Deser= to wildcats, and conversely, quite probably thickens west of Pia-4-Al, The maximum Sapucari development occurs in the area of the SJst-l-Se and BGst-1-Se wells where there is found also increased amounts of sandstone inter= calated with the limestones, Paleontological studies reveal that deeper water fos= sils are found in the easternmost Sapucari subcrops, in such wells as Pu-l-Se and the Piaçabuçu wildcats, Paleontologist Troelsen suggests that forma tion thinning in the areas of these wells is related to non-deposition ra= ther then to erosion, The thick Sapucari sections of the BGst-1-Se and Pacatuba wells contain near shore, shallow water fauna, Although Troel*sen's theory of non-deposition is quite interesting from a paleontological.envi= ronmental viewpoint, we suspect that the absence of the Sapucari in several of the deep wells with thick Calumbi sections, as IdF-1-Se, Mo-l-Se, and RSF-1, 2, 3, 4~Al, is due to erosion. Even if the limestone of the Sapuca= ri were deposited only in near shore sreas, it is likely that shale time - equivalents would be encountered in the above wells if no or very little e= rosion occurred priot to Calumbi deposition, The structure contour mep of the top of the Sapucari formation reveals no obviously interesting structural anomalies, Regional dip is toward the southeast, with steeper dips apparent in the Piaçabuçu eres compared to shallower dips in the Baixe Grande-Timbo area, Riachuelo Formation: The isopach map of the Riachuelo formation conforms with the general configuration of the enbayment area as shown on the Bouguer gravity map, Regional formation thinning occurs along the São Jose-Baixa Grande anomaly, the Pacatuba gravity ridge, and the postulated, old off-shore high near the mouth of the Rio Sao Francisco, The Riachuelo formation thickens in adjacent structurel lows, as the Badajos and Rio São Francisco minimum areas.
The Riachuelo formation (marine Albian) is absent in Pia-l-Al, Pia-2-Al, Pia~3-Al, and Pia-6-Al (?), but is present in the near by Pia-4-Al well, Very thin Riachuelo sections occur in RSF-1-Al, RSF-3-Al and RSF-4-Al, but the formation is absent in RSF.2-Al, Thus, the zero iso= pach line is clearly defined, and represents the erosional wedge-edge of the formation, The widely spaced control points for structure con touring the Riachuelo top limit the interpretations to a presentation of only the large, regional structure features as the Pacatuba arch, the broad monoclinal south flenk of the Penedo Arch, and the adjacent structural mini mums, Consequently, the map is of little value fer delineating local strug tures for wildcat drilling, Except for the Pacatuba arch, the structure contour map does not reveal the prominent highs indicated by the interpretg tion of the isopach map. The isopach map reveals an old structural trend in the Rio Sao Francisco wildcat area, This Albian high has been partielly masked by subsequent structural dow-warping during upper Cretaceous time , It is interesting to note that the oil discoveries in the Albian section og cur in wells that are located on the flank of the old Albian arch, These oil occurrences probably represent primary oil entrapment which occurred prior te the structural development of the Rio São Francisce Embayment du= ‘ying the upper Cretaceous period, Preset day structures mapped by geophy= a methods may not offer necessarily the most promising drilling loca = OnSe Ferbeca Homations The isopach map of the Muribeca formation follows e general configuration shown on the Riachuelo isopach map, The thinning ‘of the formation in the areas of possible old highs coincides with similer anomalous conditions noted on the Riachuelo map, Again, it is interesting to note that the oil discoveries in the Muribeca formation in the Piaçabuçu and Rie São Francisco wells occur on the flank of the old Rio Sao Francisco high, The lack of oil in the Muribeca formation in the Pia-2-Al and Pia-4-Al wells may be due partially to the fact that these wells are located in an area which was a structural trough during Albian time, and hence, was um favorable for oil entrapment during primary migration, The thickest Muribeca section (1378 meters) occurs in Pia-2-Al, Although the IdF-1.Se well is located in the center of the present dey Bouguer minimum, regional studies indicate that the Muribeca in this area probably does not exceed 700 meters (the IdF-1-Se final report shows the well bottomed in the Alagoas formation which, according to the pa leontologist, should be included with the non-marine Albian, or Muribeca) .
The zero isopach line of the Muribeca in the Fiaça buçu-Feliz Deserto area represents the erosional wedge-edge of the forma = tion although thinning of the formation in the FD.1-A1 and Rio São Francis= co wells may be due partially to non-deposition, The structure contour map on the top of the Muribe ca demonstrates the broad structural features of the enbayment, The Pacatu ba arch is the most prominent structure, The old Rie São Francisco high in dicateê on the isopach map has been effectively masked by later tectonic mg vement, and is barely perceptible on the contour map.
STRUCTURE CONTOUR MAP-BASE OF CALUMBI-WITH SUBCROP CONTACTS OF UNDERLYING FORMATIONS.
The contour map of the base of the Calumbi forma= tion illustrates the regional structure of the pre-Calumbi erosion surface. In addition, sufficient well control permitted the delineation of the sub - crop contacts of the formetions overlapped by the Calumbi formation, The structure Gontours show the regional eastwabd deepening of the Calumbi "basin", Rapid basin sinking during Maestrichtien time accounts for the steepening of contours between the Piaçabuçu and Rio São Francisco wildcat wells.
EN, 
The dashed contour lines southwest of the Feliz Deserto wells are projected on the erosion surface, and actually represent contours at the base of the "Older Tertiary" which has overlapped the completely eroded Calumbi sedimen ts in thig area, The Calumbi formation progressively overlies 5 truncated formations ranging in age from lower to upper Cretaceous, The pre-Calumbi erosional and enguler centact at the base of the Calumbi formation is obvieus, The structure contour map of the base of the Muri= beca formation illustrates the regional structure of one of the major erosi onal surfaces in the Sergipe part of the basin, The superimposed subcrop contacts ef the pre-Muribeca formations clearly reveal the discordant natu= re of the truncated formations with the overlying Muribeca sediments, Tem formations ranging in age from Pre-Cambrian te lower Cretaceous Aptian have been truncated and overlapped by the Muribeca fermation, The amount of an= gulerity at the Muribeca-elder formation contact appears to be of a small magnitude in lecal areas, but over the entire basin it is obviously very lerge when viewing the regional relationship of thw widespread Muribeca for mation with underlying fermations, Truly, the unconformity at the base of the Muribeca is one of the most significant and key discordances in the ba= gin.
The dip of the Muribeca base in the Em pas ix area 4s about 12º degrees south to southwest, while dipmeter readings cate É only slightly greater dips in the underlying formations, The small diffe = rence in dip accounts for the wide outcrop band of the Jequia formation,and Clearly shews that the Maceio formation can no longer be expected to be pre sent in the Piaçabuçu wildcat area, The regional dip of the Muribeca base in the east Pacatuba area is approximately 8º degrees te the southeast, whi le the underlying formations in some wells have considerably larger dips . The difference in dips allews for an interpretation of a er Jequia suberop band in the Pacatuba area than is postulated for th baa area, thus inereasing the probability of encountering the Maceio tion at reg sonable depths in the Penta dos Mangues area, and possibly in other portions of the central Sergipe coastal strip,
, Our previous interpretetiong which show the Maceio or Jequia formation to be present in the Feliz Deserto wells have been modj fied in accordance with paleontological information and the regional studies presented in this report, Neither of these formations are present in either ‘FD~L-Al or FD-2..Al, the petroleum possibilities of the Rio Sao Frencig co Embayment seem to be limited to 3 horizons; the Calumbi, Upper Maceio , and Muribeca formations, All of these formations have yielded oil or gas in drill stem or preduction tests of wells in the embayment, 011 shows have been observed in the other formations drilled in the area but subse = queat testing produced no significant results, On the other hand, too lit= tle information is available to fully evaluate potentially faverable forma= tions as the Riaçhuelo and Jequia, A better understanding of the stratigra phy and paleogeology of the Sapucari formation may lead eventually to oil discoveries in this marine wit.
A thorough and detailed study of the facies changes, formation thicknesses, and unconformities will be the most important contribu tion te an understanding of oil migration and entrapment in the embayment, It is obvious that all favorable present day structures may not necessarily offer the best opportunities to find commercial oil deposits, ‘In some cases, it ap pears that the recognition of old structures (magked by later tectonics) may hold the key to successful oil exploration in the basin, q Se A map showing probable favorable areas for wildcab locations 48 included with the report, The areas are delineated according to the formational drilling objectives, depth relationship to rig capacity, and possible oll-water contacts, Calumbi Formation: The favorable area for pessible oil production from the Calumbi formation is along the south flenk of the Penedo Arch, This area received some coarse clastic deposition during Maestrichtian time, The shore line facies of the Calumbi further to the south along the Pacatuba structural trend may have been completely removed by erosion, Small quantities of oil have been recovered from thin Calumbi sands in Pia-2-Al and Pia-3-Al, The sendstones are quite lenticular, but may be better developed in the area about 5 or 6 kilometers northwest of the village of Piaçabuçu, The entire Cg lumbi formation in thig area should be well within the capacity of a shallow drilling rig as the Cardwell K..200, VIC, ser Mac 5 Fo : Little economic importance has been given to the Ma= e ormation in the embayment, A review of the drill stem testing of the 3 ceio sandstones in the RSF..2-Al well leads us to believe that the Ma= ceio formation may yet prove to have commercial importance, É Detailed subsurface studies indicate that the upper ~ Maceio formation has been nearly completely removed by pre-Muribeca erosion in the area of RSF-1-Al and RSF-4-Al, and is entirely absent in RSF-2-Al and the Fe Deserto wells, Isopach end structure contour mapping indicate that the BE denoocié unit may be present in the areas show in red on the enclosed fa vorable area map, The formation in these areas should be within the capacity of the Cardwell "OC" rig, Muribeca Formation: The writer postulates that the Muribeca oil—bearing trend exists along the flanks of the old structures interpreted from the Murj beca isopach studies, The occurrence of oil in Pia-l-Al gives this theory a certain amount of credence because this well is located on a flank of the old Rio Sao Francisco high, The Pia-2-Al and Pia-4-Al wells encountered no Muri= beca oil zones, and are located in an old troughal or synclinal srea, The Muribeca favorable trend may extend along the east flank of the Pacatuba Arch, and southward into the Badajos-Baixa Grande region, Several conclusions are presented, and are based on he interpretations of the isopach and structure contour mapping, They are listed as follows:
1)- The Pacatuba Arch existed at least prior to Albian time, and was a promi= nent feature throughout the remaining geological periods, The arch affect ed the deposition and partial erosion of the Muribeca, Riachuelo, Sapucari end Calumbi formations, end Vaiumbi Lormations, 2)- A pre-Calumbi, north-south trending arch existed along the immediate, present day offshore area along the southeast tip of Alagoas, This structu - ral high has been partially masked by later tectonic movement during upper Cretaceous time, 3)- Produceable oil accumulations in pre-Calumbi formations arewelated appa= rently to primary migration along the flanks of old structural highs, Fa= worable present day structures in areas of these old highs offer the maxi mum opportunity to discover commercial oil deposits, h)- Conversely, favorable present day structures along old troughel areas will likely contain no oil of primary migration, and thus, offer very li= )- Conversely, favorable present day structures along old troughal areas will likely contain no oil of primary migration, and thus, offer very li= mited possibilities te establish commercial production, Regional and detailed subsurface geological studies of the type presented in this report should be expanded to all areas in the Sergipe-Alageas Basin, Several wildcat locations should be drilled in the untested portions of the favorable areas shown on the enclosed map, These lo cations should be situated whenever possible on good, geophysically located structures. In the absence of suitable structures, it would be advisable to drill several stratigraphic test in these areas,
EJB/-keb 
